<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
     <title>Use Cases</title>
    <section>
        <title>Use Case: Komet Application</title>
        <para>This section outlines three key components of the Knowledge Management Environment
            (Komet) application, Terminology Knowledge Architecture (Tinkar) knowledge architecture,
            and open-source contributions.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Komet Use Case – Rapid Knowledge Management</title>
            <para>A primary benefit of Komet and the Tinkar architecture used to manage integrated
                knowledge is the ability to rapidly update integrated knowledge in accordance with
                emerging or needed concepts and to address irregularities or errors. </para>
            <para>Komet is capable of not only identifying errors but also resolving them. For
                example, if you searched for “chronic lung disease” and opened the “Chronic lung
                disease (disorder)” that takes an user to the concept navigator. The user may notice
                that this concept only displays two children concepts, which seems incomplete as
                there should be many more children concepts for such a broad disorder. To explore
                and understand why this potential error is occurring, the user then could click on
                both the ‘Properties’ and ‘Timeline’ buttons to open additional information about
                the “Chronic lung disease (disorder)” concept. In the ‘Properties’ frame, the user
                could select ‘Hierarchy’ and turn the ‘Range’ option on in the Timeline frame. Doing
                so will display how the concept has changed over time, additions to concepts, and
                allows users to compare select versions of a concept.</para>
            <para>While a user may see version history, there is still no information on why there
                are only two children concepts. The user can then go back to the concept navigator
                and edit the EL++ Axiom from ‘Necessary Set’ to ‘Sufficient Set’, select reasoner,
                and run the ‘ELK Reasoner’. This then shows the recent edit and update, which shows
                the increased number of children concepts to over
                20.<?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?></para><?oxy_custom_end?>
            <para>While Komet, Tinkar, and our open-source approach allow the user to identify an
                error by navigating the site, understanding the concept versioning and history,
                making edits to resolve the issue in real-time, and committing the changes to the
                community at large, other Terminology Standards lack in coordinating this rapid
                approach. if a user identified this error and submitted it to Systemized
                Nomenclature of Medicine – Clinical Terms® (SNOMED CT®), they might have to wait a
                full six months before SNOMED CT® pushes their bi-annual updates and might be forced
                to employ sub-optimal work arounds to address the issue until then. This real-time
                approach of managing integrated knowledge management also allows the creation of
                concepts, such as SARS-CoV-2 (COVID-19), to meet emerging conditions and clinical
                needs.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Komet Use Case – Integration of Terminology Standards</title>
            <para>Another fundamental component of Komet is the integration of various terminology
                standards. When searching “urine homocysteine measurement”, a user can see the
                SNOMED CT® concept ‘Urine Homocysteine Measurement (procedure)’ in the navigation
                panel, while simultaneously viewing Logical Observation Identifiers Names and Code®
                (LOINC®) children concepts. Komet can seamlessly integrate concepts from different
                terminology standards and identify which concepts are associated by using a
                localized common language in the form of Analysis Normal Form (ANF).</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Komet Use Case – Detecting Equivalent Concepts</title>
            <para>Komet is also able to easily and clearly identify concepts that are equivalent and
                display any minor differences between them. If an user were to search for a concept
                to describe ankylosis in the left and right knees, they would be presented with
                ‘Observation of ankylosis of both knee joints (procedure)’ and ‘Ankylosis of
                bilateral knee joints (disorder)’. By running the Komet reasoner, selecting detect
                equivalencies, right clicking these two concepts, and selecting ‘Compare Concepts’,
                a user could determine that these concepts are equivalent. A user could then do a
                deep-dive into the concept axioms using a side-by-side comparison to understand if
                there were any minute differences between the two.</para>
        </section>
        
    </section>

</chapter>

