<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Proposed Study to Evaluate the Impact
        of Solor</title>
    <section>
        <title>Purpose</title>
        <para>Solor provides an easier way to verify that value sets are up to date and covered.
            Solor can also suggest and add additional codes based on Solor concepts to value set
            specifications. In this study, our objective is to use Solor to identify codes from eCQM
            value sets, to better understand the usage of these codes against clinical data, and to
            assess the impact of the pre and post Solor codes on eCQM performance. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Methods</title>
        <para>First, we will identify differences in the coverage of vocabulary specifications –
            unique identifiers, concepts, code groups, and coding systems – between what is covered
            in VSAC value sets and what is intended to be covered in value sets according to Solor
            to define global concepts in measures. After this, we will query clinical data at xxx to
            determine the frequency of patients for whom the new Solor codes are used. Finally, we
            will implement the measures in a quality measure calculation registry and CDS
            environment to estimate the performance differences before and after Solor’s mapping of
            non-covered value set codes. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Evaluation</title>
        <para>We will compute the frequency of patients who use any of the codes contained in CQM
            value sets, stratified by measure. We will compare the change in frequencies before and
            after Solor’s addition of equivalent codes. We will use Fisher’s exact test to compare
            aggregate-CQM performance rates between the original versions of measures and the
            versions of measures after Solor value sets are implemented. We will use the Jaccard
            similarity index to assess the similarity between the patients included in the original
            versions of the measures, and the versions including complete value set coverage. Number
            Needed to Treat and Number Needed to Harm Statistics can be used to calculate the
            potential harms avoided, and harms causes based on pre and post Solor encoded data. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Goals</title>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Assess VSAC value sets before and after the use of Solor.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Understand the frequency of patients that are impacted by newly added Solor
                    value set concepts. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Understand how increasing value set code coverage impacts CQM performance
                    estimates, and the patients included in measure populations, and implications on
                    population health. </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Example Results</title>
        <para><inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190430T212054-0500" comment="Convert to SVG?
"?>
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/NNT.png" scale="50"/><?oxy_comment_end?>
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
        </para>   
        <para>Assuming that the Solor value set specifications of a measure represent
            “perfect” inclusion, then every newly included patient can be thought of as
            needing the evidence-based therapy (such as aspirin for secondary prevention
            of heart attacks) in order to avoid bad outcomes. Under the same assumption,
            every dropped patient between value set versions of a measure can be thought
            of as avoiding potential harm caused by the promoted therapy. For aspirin
            use, Number-Needed-to- Treat (NNT) statistics show that of patients with
            known cardiovascular risk who took aspirin, 1.3% were helped by preventing a
            non-fatal heart attack, and 0.25% were harmed by a major bleeding event. In
            the Cholan et al study [33], 121 (92%) of the patients dropped in the Solor
            version of the Aspirin measure were also taking an anticoagulant medication,
            so the Number-Needed-to-Harm (NNH) statistic for this subset of patients is
            likely much higher, and for these clinics, 1 to 2 people may have been
            harmed if the pre-Solor definition persisted, as Hansen et. al showed that
            patients with combinations of aspirin, warfarin, and clopidogrel are
            associated with up to a three-fold higher risk of bleeding for patients on
            dual therapy and triple therapy.
            <?oxy_comment_start author="ecundiff" timestamp="20250713T212002-0400" comment="Added citation"?>[34]<?oxy_comment_end?>
            With another measure for statin therapy, 1 in 21 people have a repeat heart
            attack, stroke or death avoided, so even 10 missed people have significant
            risk of events. Similarly, 10% are harmed by muscle damage or pain, or ~1 of
            the 14 inappropriately included.<citation>efficacy</citation> Even in this
            small study, failure to include or exclude patients could have led to real
            harm. With eCQM implementation and QI infrastructure increasing, the problem
            of having, and using, antiquated CQM versions of value sets could have
            significant potential negative impact on population health by not avoiding
            events, and avoiding harms for patients.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
