<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Terminology Knowledge Example</title>
    <para>In this section, we will be discussing a use case using questionnaires and
        responses.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Terminology Knowledge Problem Statement</title>
            <para>As a real-world use case, we focused on improving the diagnosis of emerging acute
                chronic infectious diseases, initially focusing on Long COVID as an example. There
                are numerous areas within clinical workflows for COVID-19 exposure and Long COVID
                diagnosis that are open to improvements that will ultimately help provide safe and
                effective patient care. There is a need to determine clear prioritization principles
                around focus areas for data capture within these COVID-19 workflows. To date, Long
                COVID has been primarily a diagnosis of exclusion, meaning that it is often only
                diagnosed after all other conditions are eliminated as a possible cause of symptoms.
                Clinicians need to make quick decisions based on objective and subjective
                observations to determine if a patient has signs and symptoms compatible with Long
                COVID and whether the patient should be admitted to the hospital. Clinicians are
                encouraged to leverage technology, virtual visits, and other Health Information
                Technology (IT)-generated clinical data to assist with decision making and
                information sharing. Unfortunately, electronic clinical data is plagued by data
                quality challenges, including variation in how data elements are encoded by
                terminology standards, and stored in clinical information models. These challenges
                can cause inefficiencies in how clinical data elements are identified, retrieved,
                analyzed, and operationalized into workflows at the point-of-care. </para>
            <para>In the current workflows for COVID-19 and Long COVID, clinicians are encouraged to
                rely on electronic clinical data to determine which patients should be prioritized
                for being tested, hospitalized, and/or isolated. Failure to include or exclude
                patients’ screening, testing, and treatment could lead to life-threatening
                situations for patients and could impact the overall trajectory of the outbreak at a
                population-level. Overall, the ability to measure and improve healthcare outcomes
                relies on consistent, high-quality electronic data that is aggregated from a variety
                of Health IT systems across numerous medical centers and healthcare facilities.
                Clinicians need to be able to easily access and fully trust the electronic data they
                are using to make determinations at the point-of-care, key components of High
                Reliability Organizations and Learning Health Systems. </para>
            <para>Using ANF as a standardized statement model to streamline analysis could
                potentially lead to improved and earlier Long COVID diagnoses. This body of work
                aims to focus on workflow areas of data as it is captured for Long COVID – perhaps
                iPad data entry, EHR collection of signs and symptoms, emergency warning signs,
                patient-reported data, etc. – to understand how the collection of data elements in a
                consistent and high-quality manner, and the subsequent data analysis, fit into the
                overall goal of achieving coordinated, national and highly-reliable care.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Terminology Knowledge Demonstration Objectives</title>
            <para>The objective of this work is to document data collection methods and statement
                model standards to demonstrate the importance of an interoperable data system and
                downstream analytical scenarios through a use case for Long COVID as an example of
                an emerging acute chronic infectious disease. We aim to highlight how Analysis
                Normal Form (ANF) can be used to standardize the representation of equivalent
                concepts associated with data capture, storage and aggregation within the Long COVID
                workflow. This work utilized four main aims to demonstrate how ANF-thinking could
                improve use case outcomes and reduce the clinical burden on data consumers during
                data collection and aggregation:</para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Aim 1: Review Workflow Schematic for Emerging Acute
                    Chronic Infectious Diseases, specifically focused on Data Capture Elements and
                    Long COVID Value Sets</emphasis></para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Aim 2: Draft Potential Questionnaires to Standardize Use
                    Case Data Acquisition </emphasis></para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Aim 3: Outline Variability in Statement
                    Representations</emphasis></para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Aim 4: Demonstrate ANF Ability to Standardize Terminology
                    and Capture Critical Data</emphasis></para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Terminology Knowledge Methods</title>
            <para><emphasis>Aim 1: Review Workflow Schematic for Emerging Acute Chronic Infectious
                    Diseases, specifically focused on Data Capture Elements and Long COVID Value
                    Sets</emphasis>. In support of Task 3.2.1, our team documented a generalized
                workflow and use case schematic for a patient’s journey from COVID-19 exposure to
                Long COVID diagnosis. We focused on decision points related to data capture of signs
                and symptoms related to COVID-19 and outlined key terminology and clinical
                information modeling considerations within the workflow artifacts that were
                developed. </para>
            <para>The team then gathered and reviewed value sets from the National Institute of
                Health’s (NIH) NLM Value Set Authority Center (VSAC) to identify common concepts and
                data elements that would need to be captured to support a Long COVID diagnosis. Each
                team member was assigned a value set and identified common and well documented
                concepts from their respective set, including signs and symptoms, laboratory tests,
                laboratory test results, potential and confirmed exposure, and suspected and
                confirmed infection. The concepts were organized by value set and documented in a
                table.</para>
            <para><emphasis>Aim 2: Draft Potential Questionnaires to Standardize Use Case Data
                    Acquisition</emphasis>. Long COVID is a poorly understood condition where
                patients experience COVID-19 symptoms long past the expected symptomatic period and
                whose symptoms, test results, and timelines can vary drastically between patients.
                The team developed sample questionnaires based on the VSAC value sets to collect
                additional data that patients or providers could enter into a Clinical Input Form or
                questionnaire. Traditional, current-state questionnaires were developed for the Long
                COVID use case to demonstrate how users may struggle to identify the optimal
                selections to document certain symptoms and may result in inconsistent and/or
                duplicative clinical data. The team then worked to develop an improved questionnaire
                that removes redundant and vague concepts and forces more granular and detailed
                selections to highlight ways to enhance the quality, accuracy, and interoperability
                of collected data.</para>
            <para><emphasis>Aim 3: Outline Variability in Statement Representations</emphasis>.
                Current terminology standards vary in the way they represent and code many data
                points that can be acquired through patient questionnaires. Critical information
                regarding severity, site, associated concepts, and data elements can be spread
                across the respective fields, incorporated directly into the concept code, or a
                combination of the two. The table aims to highlight the need for a normalized way to
                represent concepts to prevent loss of critical data and meaning as it is transformed
                and transmitted within and between systems. Improving the data collection, encoding,
                and storage of both present and absent concepts is essential in the effort to
                achieve lossless and interoperable data.</para>
            <para><emphasis>Aim 4: Demonstrate ANF Ability to Standardize Terminology and Capture
                    Critical Data</emphasis>. This paper ultimately aims to improve the acquisition,
                storage, and use of data across a variety of clinical situations, with the Long
                COVID use case as an example. We propose ANF as the tool to standardize and
                normalize the way critical data concepts from patient questionnaires are represented
                before transmitting to other systems for secondary use. The same concepts that were
                shown to have varying representations across terminology standards were modeled
                using a tabular ANF representation to demonstrate how ANF captures the same or more
                detail as other standards and normalizes the formatting of equivalent concepts
                across terminologies. The ANF table captures key data elements for the concept of
                loss of sense of smell since onset of COVID-19 symptoms. The concept ID, author, and
                topic are clearly documented along with timing of onset and recording. Not only is
                the concept itself represented in a normalized way that captures all pertinent
                values and details, but other normalized concepts, like linking to the beginning of
                symptom onset can be linked as associated clinical statements that add additional
                value and context.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Terminology Knowledge Example Results</title>
            <para><emphasis>Aim 1: Review Workflow Schematic for Emerging Acute Chronic Infectious
                Diseases, specifically focused on Data Capture Elements and Long COVID Value Sets.
            </emphasis>The team downloaded and reviewed the COVID-19 VSAC value sets outlined in the
            table below. The team used these value sets to extract an initial list of generalized
            clinical concepts associated with a COVID-19 diagnosis that could potentially contribute
            to a Long COVID diagnosis. [1]</para>
                <table>
                    <title>VSAC Value Sets</title>
                    <tgroup cols="3">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Value Set Name</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Steward</entry>
                                <entry>Value Set OID</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">COVID19 Potential Signs and
                                        Symptoms</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>CareEvolution</entry>
                                <entry>2.16.840.1.113762.1.4.1223.22</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Nonspecific Respiratory Viral
                                        Infection</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>CareEvolution</entry>
                                <entry>2.16.840.1.113762.1.4.1223.25</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">C19HCC SARSCoV2
                                    Exposure</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>MITRE</entry>
                                <entry>2.16.840.1.113762.1.4.1032.120</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">COVID19 Potential
                                    Exposure</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>CareEvolution</entry>
                                <entry>2.16.840.1.113762.1.4.1223.18</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">COVID19 Suspected
                                    Infection</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>CareEvolution</entry>
                                <entry>2.16.840.1.113762.1.4.1223.6</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">LIVD SARS CoV2 Test
                                    Codes</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>ONC</entry>
                                <entry>2.16.840.1.113762.1.4.1114.9</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">LIVD SARS CoV2 Test Result
                                        Codes</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>ONC</entry>
                                <entry>2.16.840.1.113762.1.4.1114.10</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            <para><emphasis>Aim 2: Draft Potential Questionnaires to Standardize Use Case Data
                Acquisition</emphasis>. An initial questionnaire was developed for the generalized
            concepts extracted from the COVID-19 VSAC value sets that poses a simple yes or no
            question for each of the concepts that could potentially aid in a Long COVID diagnosis.
            This chapter focuses on potential questionnaires for ‘Signs and Symptoms’ and
            ‘Non-Specific Respiratory Diagnoses’, outlined in <xref
                linkend="HypotheticalSignsandSymptomsQuestionnaires"/> and <xref
                linkend="HypotheticalNonSpecificRespiratoryDiagnosesQuestionnaire"/> respectively.
            [2]</para>
            <figure xml:id="HypotheticalSignsandSymptomsQuestionnaires">
                <title>Hypothetical Signs and Symptoms Questionnaires</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/Hypothetical%20Signs%20and%20Symptoms%20Questionnaires.svg" align="center" scale="50"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>While the initial version of the questionnaire on the left can collect important
                information and data, the format was improved in the version on the right to reduce
                redundancy, improve clarity, and collect more accurate and granular detail. The
                improved questionnaire forces patients or physicians completing the survey to select
                more granular symptoms and reduces ambiguity. Rather than allowing for individuals
                to select ‘cough’ and ‘dry cough’ or ‘productive cough’, the improved questionnaire
                forces a more accurate selection of either ‘dry cough’ or ‘productive cough’ to
                reduce redundant data. Additionally, the improved questionnaire utilizes
                user-friendly definitions like rapid breathing rather than highly technical
                terminology like ‘tachypnea’ to reduce duplicative symptoms and support accurate
                data collection from a wider audience. The value sets and questionnaires will need
                to be updated as symptoms are more comprehensively understood, and as new symptoms
                are identified. </para>
            <para>The team developed additional questionnaires for non-specific respiratory
                diagnoses below in <xref linkend="HypotheticalNonSpecificRespiratoryDiagnosesQuestionnaire"/>. The diagnoses questionnaires continue to improve data
                quality by reducing duplicative selections and improving granularity by forcing an
                Upper or Lower ‘Viral Respiratory Tract Infection’ rather than allowing the
                selection of both Upper or Lower Viral Respiratory Tract Infection and “Viral
                Respiratory Tract Infection’. These additional questionnaires demonstrate how
                improvements can be made to data collection across a variety of areas associated
                with patient care and can be applied to other emerging acute and chronic infectious
                diseases.</para>
            <figure xml:id="HypotheticalNonSpecificRespiratoryDiagnosesQuestionnaire">
                <title>Hypothetical Non-Specific Respiratory Diagnoses
                    Questionnaire</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/Hypothetical%20Non-Specific%20Respiratory%20Diagnoses%20Questionnaire.svg" align="center" scale="50"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para><emphasis>Aim 3: Outline Variability in Statement Representations</emphasis>.
                Building upon the concepts found in the VSAC value sets, the team developed tabular
                representations of certain symptoms to display the variability in the way concepts
                could be represented and coded. <xref linkend="HypotheticalNonSpecificRespiratoryDiagnosesQuestionnaire"/> depicts the symptom of ‘Fever Greater Than
                100.4 Fahrenheit with Chills’ across three example terminology standards as well as
                the null value of a normal body temperature. After reviewing the table, one could
                conclude that the first three examples are semantically the same. Each describe a
                condition of fever greater than 100.4 Fahrenheit, but critical information is spread
                out across the severity, site, and code fields depending on how the respective
                terminology standard represents the condition. This variability leads to sub-optimal
                data capture that can hinder data querying, data use, and the ability to identify
                semantically equivalent concepts.</para>
                <table>
                    <title>Variability in Representation of Fever</title>
                    <tgroup cols="5">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                        <colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
                        <colspec colnum="5" colname="col5"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry> </entry>
                                <entry><link
                                    xlink:href="https://covid-19-ig.logicahealth.org/StructureDefinition-covid19-symptoms-present.html#root"
                                        ><emphasis role="bold">COVID19 Symptoms Present
                                        Example</emphasis></link><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis
                                        role="underline"> 1</emphasis></emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><link
                                    xlink:href="https://covid-19-ig.logicahealth.org/StructureDefinition-covid19-symptoms-present.html#root"
                                        ><emphasis role="bold">COVID19 Symptoms Present Example
                                        2</emphasis></link></entry>
                                <entry><link
                                    xlink:href="https://covid-19-ig.logicahealth.org/StructureDefinition-covid19-symptoms-present.html#root"
                                        ><emphasis role="bold">COVID19 Symptoms Present Example
                                        3</emphasis></link></entry>
                                <entry><link
                                    xlink:href="https://covid-19-ig.logicahealth.org/StructureDefinition-covid19-symptoms-present.html#root"
                                        ><emphasis role="bold">COVID19 Symptoms
                                    Absent</emphasis></link></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <para><link
                                            xlink:href="https://covid-19-ig.logicahealth.org/StructureDefinition-covid19-symptoms-present-definitions.html#Condition"
                                                ><emphasis role="bold"
                                        >Condition</emphasis></link></para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>Fever Greater Than 100.4 Fahrenheit with Chills
                                    Present</entry>
                                <entry>Fever Greater Than 100.4 Fahrenheit with Chills
                                    Present</entry>
                                <entry>Fever Greater Than 100.4 Fahrenheit with Chills
                                    Present</entry>
                                <entry>Body Temperature Within Normal Range</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><link
                                        xlink:href="https://covid-19-ig.logicahealth.org/StructureDefinition-covid19-symptoms-present-definitions.html#Condition.id"
                                            ><emphasis role="bold">…...</emphasis></link></entry>
                                <entry><link
                                        xlink:href="https://covid-19-ig.logicahealth.org/StructureDefinition-covid19-symptoms-present-definitions.html#Condition.id"
                                            ><emphasis role="bold">…...</emphasis></link></entry>
                                <entry><link
                                        xlink:href="https://covid-19-ig.logicahealth.org/StructureDefinition-covid19-symptoms-present-definitions.html#Condition.id"
                                            ><emphasis role="bold">…...</emphasis></link></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <link
                                        xlink:href="https://covid-19-ig.logicahealth.org/StructureDefinition-covid19-symptoms-present-definitions.html#Condition.id"
                                            ><emphasis role="bold">…...</emphasis></link></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <link
                                        xlink:href="https://covid-19-ig.logicahealth.org/StructureDefinition-covid19-symptoms-present-definitions.html#Condition.id"
                                            ><emphasis role="bold">…...</emphasis></link></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="underline"
                                            >Severity</emphasis></emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>Null </para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>Greater than 100.4 Fahrenheit</entry>
                                <entry>Greater than 100.4 Fahrenheit</entry>
                                <entry>Between 97.6 and 99.6 Fahrenheit</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <para><link
                                            xlink:href="https://covid-19-ig.logicahealth.org/StructureDefinition-covid19-symptoms-present-definitions.html#Condition.code"
                                                ><emphasis role="bold">Code</emphasis></link></para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>Fever Greater Than 100.4 Fahrenheit with Chills
                                    (finding)</entry>
                                <entry>Fever with Chills (finding)</entry>
                                <entry>Fever with Chills (finding)</entry>
                                <entry>Regular Body Temperature (finding)</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <para><link
                                            xlink:href="https://covid-19-ig.logicahealth.org/StructureDefinition-covid19-symptoms-present-definitions.html#Condition.bodySite"
                                                ><emphasis role="bold">Site</emphasis></link></para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>Null </entry>
                                <entry>Null </entry>
                                <entry>Mouth/Tongue</entry>
                                <entry>Null </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            <para><emphasis>Aim 4: Demonstrate ANF Ability to Standardize Terminology and Capture
                    Critical Data</emphasis>. The team demonstrated the value of ANF by developing a
                tabular ANF representation for loss of sense of smell since onset of COVID-19
                symptoms. ANF provides a singular, normalized way to represent concepts from
                different terminology standards by restricting various data elements to certain
                fields, like the severity of a particular symptom in the results section.
                Standardizing how data elements are reported facilitates the identification of
                equivalent terminology and improves the quality and interoperability of data. In the
                example below, ANF captures all the pertinent information including the symptom
                itself, option for the severity or numerical value of an observation, and the method
                of the observation, as well as additional information like the timeframe when a
                symptom first occurred. This additional information is an associated term that adds
                value and context to a measurement. </para>
            <para>While documenting symptoms that are marked as present on the improved
                questionnaire in a normalized format is essential, it is also important to represent
                signs and symptoms that are absent in a patient. Corresponding present and absent
                concepts for a certain symptom do not always exist across terminology standards, but
                ANF is able to represent the absence of a symptom using a numerical countable
                quantity, ensuring relevant and pertinent information is not lost.</para>
                 <table>
                    <title>ANF Standardized Representation of Anosmia and Associated Term Narrative 1</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Narrative 1: <emphasis
                                        role="bold">Loss of Sense of Smell</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
                                    <para>id: <emphasis role="bold"
                                            >XXXXXXXX-XXXX-XXXX-XXXX-XXXXXXXXXXXX</emphasis></para>
                                    <para>time: <emphasis role="bold">1:17pm 2023-02-14
                                            T09:20:00.00+01:00</emphasis></para>
                                    <para>subjectOfRecordId: <emphasis role="bold"
                                            >Participant</emphasis></para>
                                    <para>author: <emphasis role="bold">Healthcare
                                            Professional</emphasis></para>
                                    <para>subjectOfInformation: <emphasis role="bold">Subject of
                                            Record</emphasis></para>
                                    <para>type: <emphasis role="bold">Performance</emphasis></para>
                                    <para>topic: <emphasis role="bold">Loss of Sense of
                                            Smell</emphasis></para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry morerows="7">Circumstance</entry>
                                <entry>PerformanceCircumstance</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>status: 
                                                <emphasis role="bold">[Complete]</emphasis></para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>result: 
                                                <emphasis role="bold">[1,1]</emphasis></para>
                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>resolution: 
                                                      <emphasis role="bold">[N/A]</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>semantic: 
                                                      <emphasis role="bold">[N/A]</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                            </itemizedlist>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>healthRisk: 
                                                <emphasis role="bold">[N/A]</emphasis></para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>participant: 
                                                <emphasis role="bold">[Participant]</emphasis></para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>referenceRange 
                                                <emphasis role="bold">[N/A]</emphasis></para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>timing: 
                                            <emphasis role="bold">12:40pm 2023-02-14
                                                T09:20:00.00+01:00</emphasis></para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>purpose: 
                                                <emphasis role="bold">[N/A]</emphasis></para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Associations:</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
                                    <para>associatedStatement: </para>
                                    <para>[UUID] (Table: Associated Clinical Statement 1)</para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <table>
                    <title>ANF Standardized Representation of Anosmia and Associated Term Narrative 2</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Narrative 2: <emphasis
                                        role="bold">Since Onset of COVID-19
                                    Symptoms</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
                                    <para>id: <emphasis role="bold">[UUID] Associated Clinical
                                            Statement 1</emphasis></para>
                                    <para>time: <emphasis role="bold">1:17pm 20123-02-14
                                            T09:20:00.00+01:00</emphasis></para>
                                    <para>subjectOfRecordId: <emphasis role="bold"
                                            >Participant</emphasis></para>
                                    <para>author: <emphasis role="bold">Healthcare
                                            professional</emphasis></para>
                                    <para>subjectOfInformation: <emphasis role="bold">Subject of
                                            record</emphasis></para>
                                    <para>type: <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic"
                                                >Observation Procedure</emphasis></emphasis></para>
                                    <para>topic: <emphasis role="bold">Since onset of COVID
                                            symptoms</emphasis></para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry morerows="7">Circumstance</entry>
                                <entry>PerformanceCircumstance</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>status: 
                                                <emphasis role="bold">[Complete]</emphasis></para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>result:
                                                <emphasis role="bold"> [1,1]</emphasis></para>
                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>resolution: 
                                                      <emphasis role="bold">[N/A]</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>semantic: 
                                                      <emphasis role="bold">[N/A]</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                            </itemizedlist>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>healthRisk: 
                                                <emphasis role="bold">[N/A]</emphasis></para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>participant: 
                                                <emphasis role="bold">[Participant]</emphasis></para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>referenceRange: 
                                                <emphasis role="bold">[N/A]</emphasis></para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>timing: 
                                            <emphasis role="bold">1:17pm 20123-02-14
                                                T09:20:00.00+01:00</emphasis></para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>purpose: 
                                                <emphasis role="bold">[N/A]</emphasis></para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Associations:</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">associatedStatement: <emphasis
                                        role="bold">[N/A]</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Recommendations to Address Terminology Issues</title>
            <para>This section aims to highlight some of the current shortcomings with the way data
                is collected and represented. We propose the following recommendations for data
                collection via patient questionnaires to reduce duplicative and vague data
                collection, facilitate secondary data usage, and improve data
                interoperability:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Restrict data entry and collection with pre-populated patient
                        questionnaires based on established concepts from the appropriate value sets
                        to standardize data collection. This will work when questionnaire designers
                        and data consumers know the data that they are trying to capture. In the
                        context of a condition where the signs and symptoms are less well defined,
                        or have not yet been defined, this methodology may inhibit knowledge
                        discovery and should be supported by integrated knowledge management
                        constructs that facilitate data agility and regular updates to value sets.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Use detailed concepts to force granular selections that reduce ambiguity
                        or the need for duplicative data in pre-populated patient
                        questionnaires.</para>
                    <para>Questionnaires should not allow the selection of just ‘<emphasis
                            role="italic">Cough’</emphasis> and should prompt patients or providers
                        to select if it is a ‘<emphasis role="italic">Productive Cough</emphasis>’
                        or ‘<emphasis role="italic">Dry Cough</emphasis>’. </para>
                    <para>Questionnaires should not allow the selection of ‘<emphasis role="italic"
                            >Viral Respiratory Infection</emphasis>’ and should prompt patients or
                        providers to select a body site or location like ‘<emphasis role="italic"
                            >Upper Viral Respiratory Infection</emphasis>’ or ‘<emphasis
                            role="italic">Lower Viral Respiratory Infection</emphasis>’.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Group concepts by critical information like ‘<emphasis role="italic"
                            >Confirmed</emphasis>’ and ‘<emphasis role="italic"
                        >Potential</emphasis>’ exposure to prevent accidental selection of
                        inaccurate responses. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Add patient friendly terminology, like ‘<emphasis role="italic">Rapid
                            Breathing</emphasis>’, to value sets and questionnaires to facilitate
                        the collection of critical patient health data from a wider audience rather
                        than highly technical terms such as ‘<emphasis role="italic"
                            >Tachypnea</emphasis>’.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>These recommendations can and should be applied across all data collection
                questionnaires, not just the ‘Signs and Symptoms’ and ‘Non-Specific Respiratory
                Diagnosis’ questionnaires represented in this chapter. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
        <title>Technologies that Support ANF </title>
        <para>While standardizing data collection methods is a critical step towards data
            interoperability and ANF data transformations, there are still common sources of errors
            associated with normalizing clinical data. Errors normalizing terminology content,
            terminology semantics, and poorly defined interactions between the input and
            presentation of clinical data are three key problems that still need to be addressed.
            Several transformation languages and architectures exist for expressing and executing
            transformation logic to address the issues above and to normalize specific instances of
            clinical data into ANF. Users can choose a language that is best tailored for the format
            of the data source, while transformation quality and accuracy is left to the
            transformation author. Below is a list of four transformation languages and the
            associated benefits and limitations. While each option has its own limitations and cost,
            the ability to address or minimize common normalization errors justifies their use.
            [1]<?oxy_comment_start author="naylee" timestamp="20231130T110056-0600" comment="The table below needs to define QVT = Query/View/Transformation in the first colum of the table. "?></para><?oxy_comment_end?>
        <table>
            <title>Benefits and Limitations of Transformation Languages and Architecture</title>
            <tgroup cols="3">
                <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" align="left" rowsep="1"/>
                <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="left" rowsep="1"/>
                <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="left" rowsep="1"/>
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Standard or Language</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Benefits</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Limitations</emphasis></entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>eXtensible Stylesheet Language Transformation (XSLT)</entry>
                        <entry>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Robust language </para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Easily extensible via extension functions and calls</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Auto matches templates to data</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Easy tooling</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Good documentation</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Transformation specifications are difficult to read and
                                        understand</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Transformations are syntactic </para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>XML input only, other formats not translated </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>FHIR Mapping Language (FML)</entry>
                        <entry>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Supports input formats other XML</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Semantic DAGs can be rendered in variety of
                                        syntaxes</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Concise and easy to read mapping specifications</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Input and output outside of FHIR logical models require
                                        extra custom programming</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Only XML and JSON supported as output syntaxes, otherwise
                                        custom programming is required</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>To date, only one implementation </para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Limited tools needed for editing and authoring
                                        scripts</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Limited documentation sources</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Limited pool of knowledgeable programmers</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>QVT</entry>
                        <entry>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Great flexibility and configurability to create custom
                                        transformation languages</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Limited learning resources making it difficult to learn
                                        and understand</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Model Driven Message Interoperability (MDMI)</entry>
                        <entry>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Any-to-any transformations support reuse of transformation
                                        models for different use cases</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Minimal changes to other models if model changes</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Simplifies development, tooling supports development by
                                        SMEs and not dependent on developers</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Enables automation tooling for models</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Available open-source models for HL7 formats</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Limited experience working with transformations of
                                        detailed clinical models.</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Lacking user documentation</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Complex runtime tool</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
        <para> </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>References</title>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Covid-19 value sets in VSAC [Internet]. U.S. National Library of Medicine.
                    National Institutes of Health; [cited 2023 Mar 10]. Available from:
                    https://www.nlm.nih.gov/vsac/support/usingvsac/covid19valuesets.html</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>McDonald C, Huff SM, Suico J, Mercer K. Logical Observation Identifiers Names
                    and Codes (LOINC) users’ guide. Indianapolis: Regenstrief Institute.<emphasis
                        role="italic"> </emphasis>2004</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
</chapter>
