<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>LOINC® and SNOMED CT® Licensing Information</title>
    <section>
        <title>LOINC® License</title>
        <para>The LOINC® database can be obtained from the Regenstrief LOINC®
            website (<link xlink:href="http://www.regenstrief.org/loinc/"
                >http://www.regenstrief.org/LOINC®/</link>), as a PDF report
            sorted alphabetically by class, as a tab-delimited ASCII text file,
            and/or as an Access database. The LOINC® database and associated
            documents and programs are copyrighted, but the copyright permits
            all commercial and noncommercial uses in perpetuity at no cost. If
            the LOINC® database or its contents are distributed as a database,
            such distributions must include all parts of the formal LOINC® term,
            the LOINC® short name, the LOINC® code, the deprecated flag, and the
            copyright. The copyright notice is needed to prevent variants, which
            would defeat the purpose of this standard. No such notice is
            required when LOINC® codes are used in messages to report test
            results.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>SNOMED CT® License</title>
        <para>Use of SNOMED CT® is subject to the SNOMED International Affiliate
            license provisions and is free in Member territories including the
            United States, in low income countries, and for Qualifying Research
            Projects in any country. To learn more, please see the SNOMED CT®
            and Licensing page. Users should carefully read the license
            agreement before re-distributing any content in any type of
            application as there may be additional restrictions, permissions or
            copyright considerations imposed by the content providers. Users
            must contact the vocabulary content providers regarding any use that
            is not covered by the license. The content providers may charge fees
            for these additional uses of their content. Appendix 1 of the
            license agreement lists contact information for each content
            provider. The SNOMED CT® Affiliate License Agreement is included as
            Appendix 2 of the UMLS Metathesaurus License and outlines possible
            costs. NLM is a member of SNOMED International and there is no
            charge for SNOMED CT® use in the United States and other Member
            territories. For information about fees in non-member countries, see
            the SNOMED International website.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>

