<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Strengthening AI Capabilities</title>
    <section>
        <title>Structured Data Enables Enhanced AI Output</title>
        <para>By collaboratively enhancing and integrating existing laboratory standards, clinical
            care organizations can reduce maintenance burdens and move towards achieving data
            interoperability, enabling scalable solutions as the healthcare ecosystem evolves.
            Healthcare must move beyond siloed, fragmented data toward integrated, curated
            information that powers intelligent systems. Our logical model, backed by the HL7 Tinkar
            ballot, helps enable this approach by enhancing the quality of healthcare data,
            unlocking reliable innovation, faster decision-making, and improved interoperability.
            Flexible data structures that can adapt to changes in regulatory and clinical
            requirements are needed so that both human and Artificial Intelligence systems can
            continue to use and benefit from the data as the healthcare landscape evolves. The
            structured data can then serve as the backbone for advancing AI capabilities in
            healthcare.</para>
        <para>Currently, AI systems often struggle with gaps and inconsistencies due to unstructured
            data, such as free text, resulting in variable answers and hallucinated responses. A
            recent study published in the Journal of the American Medical Association demonstrates
            that AI models perform dramatically better when enriched with linked, structured
            information, improving accuracy and reliability in complex tasks such as the US Medical
            Licensing Examinations [6].</para>
        <figure xml:id="ScoreontheUSMLE3">
            <title>Score on the USMLE (Step 3)</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/AIFig1.svg" scale="25" align="center"/> 
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>As public health agencies explore AI implementations, the data model provides various
            capabilities that offer a robust data foundation to support reliable large language
            models and regulatory automation. Device Extension (DeX) is one of the many use cases
            enabled by the model. DeX creates a machine-readable network of relationships across
            identifiers and attributes, providing an extendable pathway for AI tools to consistently
            reason across datasets and deliver more accurate answers. It helps to organize and
            connect critical device data, (such as product codes, manufacture data, naming
            conventions, detection limits, reference ranges, etc.) by capturing essential
            information from sources such as SNOMED, LOINC, and GUDID databases and define
            relationships between devices, attributes, and regulatory metadata. Komet plays a key
            role in structuring the information, as it works to create and store DeX content. The
            interface also helps edit and reliably manage existing relationships as device data
            evolves over time and export these relationships in standard, computable formats that AI
            systems can easily ingest. </para>
        <para>To take advantage of these functionalities, a robust data pipeline is essential to
            help transform raw, fragmented healthcare information into structured, high-quality
            datasets that fuel advanced AI systems. Industry leading tools such as GitHub, Maven,
            SonarCloud, and more are used to help strengthen the data pipeline, which can then
            systematically ingest, validate, and link data from diverse sources, including
            laboratory standards, device registries, and regulatory databases, to ensure
            consistency, completeness, and interoperability. This process not only eliminates
            inaccuracies but also enriches the data with meaningful relationships and metadata,
            making it readily accessible for AI models. Supported by this strengthened data
            pipeline, AI systems can deliver more accurate, reliable, and context-aware insights,
            enabling complex decision-making and driving innovation across clinical, regulatory, and
            public health domains.</para>
        <figure xml:id="DataPipeline">
            <title>Data Pipeline</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/AIFigure2.svg" scale="25" align="center"/> 
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>Looking forward, our flexible, interoperable data model supports a diverse array of
            use cases across the healthcare ecosystem. For example, it can support population health
            analytics by aggregating and harmonizing data from multiple sources, enhance clinical
            decision support tools that require real-time access to accurate information, and
            facilitate regulatory reporting by automating the extraction and submission of required
            data. Researchers can leverage higher quality data to accelerate healthcare
            advancements, while public health agencies can more confidently rely on data to help
            respond to emerging health threats. By providing a reliable foundation for these and
            many other applications, the logical model provides a reliable foundation to enhance the
            output of evolving technological capabilities in the healthcare ecosystem. </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
