<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>References</title>
    <para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Osheroff JA, Teich JM, Middleton B, Steen EB, Wright A, Detmer DE. A
                    Roadmap for National Action on Clinical Decision Support. Journal of the
                    American Medical Informatics Association [Internet]. 2007 Mar 1 [cited 2025
                    Jul 31];14(2):141–5. Available from:
                    https://academic.oup.com/jamia/article-lookup/doi/10.1197/jamia.M2334</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Lobach D, Sanders GD, Bright TJ, Wong A, Dhurjati R, Bristow E, et al.
                    Enabling health care decisionmaking through clinical decision support and
                    knowledge management. Evid Rep Technol Assess (Full Rep) [Internet]. 2012
                    Apr [cited 2025 Jul 31];(203):1–784. Available from:
                    https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4781172/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Smithburger PL, Buckley MS, Bejian S, Burenheide K, Kane-Gill SL. A
                    critical evaluation of clinical decision support for the detection of
                    drug–drug interactions. Expert Opinion on Drug Safety [Internet]. 2011
                    [cited 2025 Jul 31];10(6):871–82. Available from:
                    http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1517/14740338.2011.583916</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Sönnichsen A, Trampisch US, Rieckert A, Piccoliori G, Vögele A, Flamm M,
                    et al. Polypharmacy in chronic diseases–Reduction of Inappropriate
                    Medication and Adverse drug events in older populations by electronic
                    Decision Support (PRIMA-eDS): study protocol for a randomized controlled
                    trial. Trials [Internet]. 2016 [cited 2025 Jul 31];17(1):57. Available from:
                    http://trialsjournal.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13063-016-1177-8</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Fritz D, Ceschi A, Curkovic I, Huber M, Egbring M, Kullak-Ublick GA, et
                    al. Comparative evaluation of three clinical decision support systems:
                    prospective screening for medication errors in 100 medical inpatients. Eur J
                    Clin Pharmacol [Internet]. 2012 [cited 2025 Jul 31];68(8):1209–19. Available
                    from: http://link.springer.com/10.1007/s00228-012-1241-6</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Felcher AH, Gold R, Mosen DM, Stoneburner AB. Decrease in unnecessary
                    vitamin D testing using clinical decision support tools: making it harder to
                    do the wrong thing. Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association
                    [Internet]. 2017 Jul 1 [cited 2025 Jul 31];24(4):776–80. Available from:
                    https://academic.oup.com/jamia/article/24/4/776/3038206</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Cleveringa FGW, Gorter KJ, Van Den Donk M, Rutten GEHM. Combined Task
                    Delegation, Computerized Decision Support, and Feedback Improve
                    Cardiovascular Risk for Type 2 Diabetic Patients. Diabetes Care [Internet].
                    2008 Dec 1 [cited 2025 Jul 31];31(12):2273–5. Available from:
                    https://diabetesjournals.org/care/article/31/12/2273/24934/Combined-Task-Delegation-Computerized-Decision</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Garg AX, Adhikari NKJ, McDonald H, Rosas-Arellano MP, Devereaux PJ, Beyene
                    J, et al. Effects of Computerized Clinical Decision Support Systems on
                    Practitioner Performance and Patient Outcomes: A Systematic Review. JAMA
                    [Internet]. 2005 Mar 9 [cited 2025 Jul 31];293(10):1223. Available from:
                    http://jama.jamanetwork.com/article.aspx?doi=10.1001/jama.293.10.1223</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Wells S, Furness S, Rafter N, Horn E, Whittaker R, Stewart A, et al.
                    Integrated electronic decision support increases cardiovascular disease risk
                    assessment four fold in routine primary care practice. European Journal of
                    Cardiovascular Prevention &amp; Rehabilitation [Internet]. 2008 [cited 2025
                    Jul 31];15(2):173–8. Available from:
                    https://academic.oup.com/eurjpc/article/15/2/173-178/5933040</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Wu WY, Hripcsak G, Lurio J, Pichardo M, Berg R, Buck MD, et al. Impact of
                    Integrating Public Health Clinical Decision Support Alerts Into Electronic
                    Health Records on Testing for Gastrointestinal Illness. Journal of Public
                    Health Management and Practice [Internet]. 2012 [cited 2025 Jul
                    31];18(3):224–7. Available from:
                    https://journals.lww.com/00124784-201205000-00006</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Calloway S, Akilo HA, Bierman K. Impact of a clinical decision support
                    system on pharmacy clinical interventions, documentation efforts, and costs.
                    Hosp Pharm. 2013 Oct;48(9):744–52.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Wright A. Improving Quality by Maintaining Accurate Problems in the
                    Electronic Health Record [Internet]. clinicaltrials.gov; 2023 Feb [cited
                    2025 Jul 31]. Report No.: NCT02596087. Available from:
                    https://clinicaltrials.gov/study/NCT02596087</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Medicine NA of, Series TLHS, Lopez MH, Weingarten S, Teich JM, Middleton
                    B, et al. PRIORITIES FOR ACCELERATING CDS PROGRESS. In: Optimizing
                    Strategies for Clinical Decision Support: Summary of a Meeting Series
                    [Internet]. National Academies Press (US); 2017 [cited 2025 Jul 31].
                    Available from: https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK594839/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Wright A, Hickman TTT, McEvoy D, Aaron S, Ai A, Andersen JM, et al.
                    Analysis of clinical decision support system malfunctions: a case series and
                    survey. J Am Med Inform Assoc. 2016 Nov;23(6):1068–76.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Department of Health and Human Services, Office of the National
                    Coordinator for Health Information Technology [Internet]. Rollout of
                    Effective CDS Interventions. Available from:
                    https://www.healthit.gov/sites/default/files/3-4-3-rollout-effective-cds.pdf</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Kassakian SZ, Yackel TR, Gorman PN, Dorr DA. Clinical decisions support
                    malfunctions in a commercial electronic health record. Appl Clin Inform.
                    2017 Sep 6;8(3):910–23.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Wright A. Best Practices for CDS Knowledge Management.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Bates DW, Kuperman GJ, Wang S, Gandhi T, Kittler A, Volk L, et al. Ten
                    Commandments for Effective Clinical Decision Support: Making the Practice of
                    Evidence-based Medicine a Reality. J Am Med Inform Assoc [Internet]. 2003
                    [cited 2025 Jul 31];10(6):523–30. Available from:
                    https://academic.oup.com/jamia/article-lookup/doi/10.1197/jamia.M1370</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>McCallie DP. Clinical Decision Support: History and Basic Concepts. In:
                    Weaver CA, Ball MJ, Kim GR, Kiel JM, editors. Healthcare Information
                    Management Systems: Cases, Strategies, and Solutions [Internet]. Cham:
                    Springer International Publishing; 2016 [cited 2025 Jul 31]. p. 3–19.
                    Available from: https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-20765-0_1</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Jiang G, Prud’Hommeax E, Solbrig H. Developing A Semantic Web-based
                    Framework for Executing the Clinical Quality Language Using FHIR.
                    Proceedings of a SWAT4LS Workshop. Available from:
                    www.swat4ls.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/SWAT4LS-2017_paper_40.pdf</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>NCCIH [Internet]. [cited 2025 Jul 31]. Clinical Practice Guidelines.
                    Available from:
                    https://www.nccih.nih.gov/health/providers/clinicalpractice</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Clinical Practice [Internet]. [cited 2025 Jul 31]. Available from:
                    https://captions.snmmi.org/CAPTIONS/Web/Clinical-Practice/Default.aspx</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Clinical Practice Guideline Manual [Internet]. [cited 2025 Jul 31].
                    Available from:
                    https://www.aafp.org/family-physician/patient-care/clinical-recommendations/cpg-manual.html</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Guidelines and Measures | Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality
                    [Internet]. [cited 2025 Jul 31]. Available from:
                    https://www.ahrq.gov/gam/index.html</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Rao TSS, Radhakrishnan R, Andrade C. Standard operating procedures for
                    clinical practice. Indian J Psychiatry. 2011 Jan;53(1):1–3.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>CDC. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. 2023 [cited 2025 Jul 31].
                    Million Hearts® Treatment Protocols. Available from:
                    https://millionhearts.hhs.gov/tools-protocols/protocols.html</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Order set - Clinfowiki [Internet]. [cited 2025 Jul 31]. Available from:
                    <link
                        xlink:href="https://clinfowiki.org/wiki/index.php/Order_Set#:~:text=An%20order%20set%20is%20a%20group%20of%20related"
                        >https://clinfowiki.org/wiki/index.php/Order_Set#:~:text=An%20order%20set%20is%20a%20group%20of%20related</link></para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </para>
</chapter>