<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Emergency Preparedness</title>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>For the purpose of this chapter, we define emergency disaster response in regard to
            four different categories of disaster: natural disasters, public health crises, acts of
            terrorism and radiation and chemical emergencies. [109] Natural disasters include
            earthquakes, hurricanes, floods, tornadoes, tsunamis, wildfires, volcanic eruptions and
            extreme temperatures, and these events can cause great damage to the environment,
            property, wildlife and human health. [110] Public health crises include epidemics,
            pandemics, and other disease outbreaks ranging from new influenza strains to potentially
            deadly diseases, as seen during the recent COVID-19 pandemic. Acts of terrorism can
            range from bomb threats to the threat or usage of biohazardous materials. [111] Lastly,
            radiation and chemical emergencies include the accidental or intentional release of
            radioactive materials or other toxic substances that can cause widespread damage in a
            specified area, as seen in the Chernobyl Accident in 1986 or the Tokyo subway nerve gas
            attack in 1995. [112-113]</para>
        <para>The year 2024 marks 45 years of emergency management for the U.S. Federal Emergency
            Management Agency (FEMA) and celebrates the presence and dedication of public services
            before, during and after an emergency disaster. [114] The rapid development of
            technology, such as individuals’ access to smartphones during 9/11, has greatly
            motivated the need for applying innovative technology solutions during emergency
            situations. Up to this point we have understood the failures and successes of knowledge
            management in healthcare settings, but it is important to understand them as part of an
            emergency response as well. For instance, communications and knowledge sharing was
            critically lacking during the September 11<superscript>th</superscript> attacks,
            ultimately hampering the emergency response. The 9/11 Commission Report describes the
            issues with interoperability and included recommendations for better communication
            systems between emergency authorities. [115]</para>
        <para>As we have previously discussed, the primary challenge with the adoption of new
            technology and standards revolves around adapting technology to the local context and
            need. Addressing user understanding of technology, ensuring interoperability, and
            implementing data standardization - all while respecting current knowledge - are
            critical aspects of this overarching challenge. Integrating communication systems into
            all public and private spheres and integrating social media and social services requires
            a strong strategy for designing and testing interfaces and interactions for usability.
            Promoting open data and using open-source technology to support a wide range of
            technical solutions is part of implementing IKM. This chapter explores the level of
            current adoption of IKM in the existing emergency natural response system and further
            discusses challenges and recommendations for better practice in the near future. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Landscape of Emergency Management in the United States</title>
        <para>FEMA was founded in 1979 by President Jimmy Carter. However, federal emergency
            management in the United States dates back to 1802, when the government responded to the
            destruction of a seaport in New Hampshire caused by a natural disaster. Since its
            establishment, FEMA has undergone several organizational transformations and expanded
            its services. Today, it serves as an agency that assists people before, during, and
            after emergencies. [116]</para>
        <para>Emergency management and disaster response consists of five mission areas as defined
            by FEMA. These five areas include prevention, protection, mitigation, response, and
            recovery. These areas are part of the National Preparedness Goal which is to have a
            “secure and resilient nation with the capabilities required across the whole community
            to prevent, protect against, mitigate, respond to, and recover from the threats and
            hazards that pose the greatest risk” [117], and includes risks such as natural
            disasters, disease pandemics, chemical spills, man-made disasters, and terrorist and
            cyber-attacks. The five mission areas are defined as follows:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Prevention</emphasis>: Prevent, avoid or stop an
                    imminent, threatened or actual act of terrorism.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Protection</emphasis>: Protect our citizens, residents,
                    visitors, and assets against the greatest threats and hazards in a manner that
                    allows our interests, aspirations and way of life to thrive.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Mitigation</emphasis>: Reduce the loss of life and
                    property by lessening the impact of future disasters.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Response</emphasis>: Respond quickly to save lives,
                    protect property and the environment, and meet basic human needs in the
                    aftermath of a catastrophic incident.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Recovery</emphasis>: Recover through a focus on the
                    timely restoration, strengthening and revitalization of infrastructure, housing
                    and a sustainable economy, as well as the health, social, cultural, historic and
                    environmental fabric of communities affected by a catastrophic incident.
                    [118]</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>A straightforward approach to understanding emergency management is to consider its
            activities in three phases: before, during, and after an emergency. In this paper we
            explore how IKM can play into each of these response phases.</para>
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Examples of Knowledge Management in Emergency Response</title>
        <para>Emergency preparedness can broadly be split in pre-emergency, emergency response, and
            post emergency. Knowledge management and communications are critical during all stages
            of preparedness. In the pre-emergency timeframe, during the mitigation and preparedness
            stages of emergency management, knowledge management can be used to bolster training and
            education. For example, FEMA’s Emergency Management Institute (EMI) offers online
            training courses for emergency preparedness through its partnership with affiliated
            centers. [119] Training and education of first responders can help orient and prepare
            those involved once an emergency occurs and is a core tenet of knowledge management best
            practices. </para>
        <para>Another example of a national approach to emergency knowledge management is FEMA’s
            National Incident Management System (NIMS). NIMS is an example of a system that uses
            knowledge management to integrate resources across organizations by sharing and
            communicating compiled information. NIMS provides standardized vocabulary, systems and
            processes, and are large players when it comes to training and education. [120]</para>
        <para>The National Emergency Response Information System (NERIS) is another example of a
            system that employs interoperable data and information into an analytics platform used
            by the U.S. Fire Administration to support decision making. [121] Information and data
            from fire departments across the country is integrated into the system, and these
            departments can then access timely and accurate data to provide actionable intelligence. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>IKM In Emergency Response</title>
        <para>As discussed, the interoperability of data and communications is already a large part
            of emergency preparedness and response. IKM has a place in emergency preparedness by
            enhancing the ability of organizations to share and integrate critical data.
            Standardizing data can help improve emergency preparedness outcomes and enable the
            government to respond more efficiently, ultimately lessening the damage caused by an
            emergency. However, current standards organizations such as LOINC® and SNOMED CT® do not
            mention emergency preparedness, suggesting the emergency response system could be a
            valuable area for the application of IKM. Furthermore, the lack of organizations that
            standardize emergency response terminology generates an opportunity to build a knowledge
            management and crowdsourcing framework for emergency preparedness. </para>
        <section>
            <title>The COVID-19 Pandemic and IKM</title>
            <para>During the COVID-19 pandemic the absence of interoperable laboratory data was a
                challenge to response efforts. The lack of interoperable data during the pandemic
                showcased the inability of the government to properly estimate disease incidence and
                other metrics, ultimately cascading into inadequate communications and erosion in
                the public’s trust. The Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act
                (P.L. 116-136) was established to require laboratories to report COVID-19 test
                results to the United States Health and Human Services (HHS) Secretary. [122]
                Systemic Harmonization and Interoperability Enhancement for Laboratory Data (SHIELD)
                developed the LOINC® to In vitro Diagnostics (LIVD) mapping specifications for IVDs
                for SARS-CoV-2 diagnostic use, and in 2020 HHS ordered the use of LIVD test results
                provided to SHIELD. A study of five medical centers that used LIVD concluded there
                is potential for LIVD to improve semantic interoperability and data quality of LIS
                data. Although the benefit of LIVD is well documented, further efforts to promote
                its widespread use to achieve true laboratory interoperability are desirable.
                [123]</para>
            <para>The pandemic also pushed forward other new technologies to help facilitate the
                response through the introduction and expansion of Artificial intelligence (AI). One
                of the main issues facing emergency responders and the public during the pandemic
                was the inability of policy and communications to efficiently update when new data
                and information was made available. Dealing with inaccurate, unreliable, and
                incomplete data all contributed to a flat emergency response effort. [124-125]
                Interoperability challenges were part of lessons learned from the COVID-19 pandemic,
                and fostered advancements in AI and advanced analytics.</para>
            <para>AI trains machines to learn from experience, taking new inputs and performing
                human-like tasks in a logically programmed sequence with advanced analytics. As a
                result of rapidly developing AI, generative AI, a category of AI system that is able
                to produce meaningful content of its own, is known to be far superior to the
                traditional role of AI that primarily deals with numeric data with a limited amount
                of text. This generative AI has become a powerful tool to leverage existing data for
                enhancing data analysis and decision-making steps. Generative AI can touch on many
                parts of emergency response and preparedness, including optimizing resource
                allocation, creating alerts based on environmental scans, enhancing trainings and
                educational initiatives. [126]</para>
            <para>Although AI is a powerful tool in the field of Emergency Response &amp;
                Preparedness, the output of AI is solely dependent upon the quality of numerical
                data with limited texts. Even with the existence of generative AI and its advanced
                outputs, public health institutions in the U.S. must navigate through a complex web
                of data paths with limited interoperability and data access. For example, more than
                a third of public health agencies were unable to access surveillance data during the
                COVID-19 pandemic, hampering their response. [127] </para>
            <para>IKM can help unlock the full power of AI by ensuring data is of high quality,
                complete, reliable, and interoperable. [128] </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <para>Organizations across local, state, federal, national, and international levels must
            continually navigate the complexities of adopting and implementing emerging technologies
            in diverse ways. Simultaneously, they not only need to keep up with the interoperability
            of their legacy systems with new systems, but also need to maintain an interoperable
            system with other institutions’ Incident Command System (ICS). </para>
        <para>Adopting IKM becomes an additional layer for response organizations to incorporate.
            Having experienced the global pandemic in recent years, the role of compliance is
            imperative for public safety. Enforcement in the areas of public safety and emergency
            planning remain crucial and requires government support to upgrade existing digital
            technologies. Achieving this upgrade at the state and local levels will empower and
            facilitate the federal level in maintaining interoperable ICS systems with the latest
            available technology for many years to come. </para>
        <para>The field of emergency response and preparedness is well established with many
            agencies and organizations serving in this space. Emergency preparedness is an important
            part of public health and requires a thorough management plan. In an ideal setting,
            emergency response systems work as well-oiled machines with complex processes and actors
            spanning across every field. The use of IKM in emergency preparedness and response can
            sharpen these processes and facilitate timely decision making and a more successful
            response. </para>
    </section>
    
</chapter>
