<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> 
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?> 
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?> 
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1"> 
    <title>Summary of Findings - Safety Systems Framework for Knowledge Management and Advanced
        Analytics</title> 
    <section> 
        
        <title>Executive Summary</title>
        <para>Real-World Data (RWD) and Real-World Evidence (RWE) are frequently low-quality despite
            FDA efforts to ensure rigorous labeling for devices, prescription drugs, and over the
            counter (OTC) medications [1]. These labels may include Medication Guides, Patient
            Package Inserts, and Instructions for Use and are available with the device or drug.
            Information within these labels could be used as a resource to improve the quality and
            utility of RWD and RWE if properly processed. </para>
        <para>These labels are frequently the primary source of guidance associated with a Food and
            Drug Administration (FDA) regulated product; however, the information in these labels is
            underutilized [2]. Product users and prescribers might avoid or have a difficult time
            with these labels because they can be lengthy or take the form of a high-density,
            multi-panel, origami-like leaflet. The language used on these labels often includes
            complex medical terminology and jargon that can be difficult for users to understand.
            The layout and organization of the information can also contribute to the difficulty, as
            important details may be buried within dense blocks of text or presented in a confusing
            manner. The necessity to include extensive information to comply with regulatory
            requirements can result in overcrowded labels, where critical usage instructions and
            warnings are not easily distinguishable. Using these labels to directly improve
            health-care quality and subsequent RWD quality is even more challenging secondary to the
            unencoded state of these labels. </para>
        <para>Secondary benefits that could be derived from encoding the knowledge contained within
            these labels—such as codifying indications for use, proper data encoding of an implanted
            device, or proper encoding of test results generated from a regulated instrument and
            test kit—are unrealized because the underlying knowledge remains largely in a textual
            form intended for human consumption, rather than also being provided in a structured and
            encoded form optimized for clinical, regulatory, and public health decision making,
            automated decision support, and RWD generation and quality assurance [2]. </para>
        <para>For instance, having specific manufacturer, method, and target information for a test
            encoded in both human-readable and machine processable ways could help better understand
            the significance of test performance in the community during viral evolution and
            changing disease prevalence, and can also help ensure that the underlying RWD is
            properly encoded and transmitted. The following example shows a textual example of the
            types of knowledge that are contained within these labels:</para>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">The product is a lateral flow immunochromatographic assay
                intended for in vitro rapid, simultaneous qualitative detection and differentiation
                of influenza A and influenza B nucleoprotein antigens and SARS-CoV-2 nucleocapsid
                antigen directly from anterior nasal swab specimens of individuals with signs and
                symptoms of respiratory infection consistent with COVID-19 [3]</emphasis></para>
        <para>Because these types of narrative text cannot easily be ingested by Electronic Health
            Records (EHR), Laboratory Information Systems (LIS), public health databases, and other
            systems without the help of extensive manual intervention or inconsistently trained
            Natural Language Processing (NLP) tools at the organizational level, Real World Data
            (RWD) across the entire ecosystem—from the patient to the regulatory levels—is
            represented in inconsistent and often erroneous ways.</para>
        <para>If FDA product knowledge were instead encoded into a machine-processible knowledge
            representation, health IT and other systems could leverage this knowledge in
            increasingly powerful ways, such as generating more accurate and insightful clinical
            decision support alerts, more accurate predictive population health analytics, and
            faster, more informed regulatory decision making.</para> 
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Background</title>
        <section>
            <title>Laboratory Interoperability Device Reference (LIDR) Summary</title>
            <para>Laboratory Real-World Data (RWD) is encoded inconsistently and incompletely, which
                limits its value for clinical, regulatory, and public health and creates patient
                safety risks. To improve the quality and interoperability of laboratory data, Unique
                Device Identifiers (UDIs) link each In-vitro Diagnostic Device (IVD) to a database
                that contains metadata about the test, including the units of measurement, LOINC®
                code, and more. This database, known as Laboratory Interoperability Device Reference
                (LIDR), ensures that laboratories can be a source of safe, high-quality, and
                interoperable RWD, suitable for use in regulatory submissions, review, and
                post-market surveillance as well as into clinical care, public health, and coverage
                determination. By implementing Artificial Intelligence (AI) tools in conjunction
                with the LIDR repository, a streamlined and validified knowledge base can be created
                and maintained to equip clinicians with easy access to decision guiding resources. A
                shared knowledge base, as shown in Figure 1, can be used to simplify the
                relationships across disparate knowledge standards by extracting common elements and
                representing them in a common form. </para>
            <figure xml:id="NameofImageWithNoSpaces"> 
                <title>Shared Knowledge Base Overview</title> 
                <mediaobject> 
                    <imageobject> 
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/4.4.1.1.svg" 
                            scale="25" align="center"/> 
                    </imageobject> 
                </mediaobject>
                <para>These principles of building a shared knowledge base can also be applied to
                    healthcare terminology where hierarchal concepts and their relationships can be
                    represented in this form. New concepts can build on this pre-existing
                    representation. AI can aid in extracting these unique elements as well as the
                    meaning and purpose of their respective concepts in a reproducible
                    format.</para> 
            </figure> 
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Overview of Approach</title>
            <para>AI can improve the granularity, consistency, and overall quality of data generated
                by and about FDA approved products by translating the existing, human-readable FDA
                product labels into a machine-processable, proof-of-concept knowledge base that can
                be published by the FDA and made available to the entire healthcare ecosystem. </para>
            <para>Consider the lateral flow assay example provided in the previous section, the
                textual information can be machine processed to propose the best way to encode data
                derived from the referenced assay, which can then be reviewed by subject matter
                experts within a rigorous statistical process control framework [4]. The statement
                that the assay detects the SARS-CoV-2 nucleocapsid antigen can be linked to the
                Global Substance Registration System entry,<superscript/>and if also associated with
                the FDA Unique Device Identifier in the resulting RWD, can enhance the ability to
                capture high-quality data, and to use complete information about the product for
                pre-market, post-market, clinical research, and other public health purposes [5]. </para>
            <para>Machine learning and large language models can be applied to FDA product labels to
                generate proposed facts (assertions and propositions) and represent those facts as
                knowledge graphs (a <link
                    xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Graph_(discrete_mathematics)"
                    >graph</link>-structured <link
                    xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_model">data model</link>), which
                can be processed by machine reasoners and included in analytic processes.
                Statistical process control with expert human review then assures the quality of
                generated facts and ensure the resulting statistics can deliver a curated knowledge
                resource with the statistical quality assurance and validity needed to function as a
                reliable training set for machine learning and a safe and effective resource for
                clinical, regulatory, and public-health decision making. </para>
            <para>These knowledge graphs will be represented using standard encoding systems, such
                as the clinical terminologies used to represent RWD (Logical Observation
                Identifiers, Names, and Codes [LOINC®], Systematized Nomenclature of Medicine
                Clinical Terms [SNOMED CT®], RxNorm®, and the National Drug Code [NDC] Codes). These
                knowledge graphs will also include representations of supporting systems, such as
                the FDA’s Global Substance Registration System (GSRS), which generates Unique
                Ingredient Identifiers (UNIIs) used in electronic listings like DailyMed and other
                regulatory activities throughout the product lifecycle [5]. These activities include
                clinical trial phases, product marketing, and post-market surveillance. Existing,
                FDA-approved devices, medications, biologics, and other products will be used to
                serve as a proof-of-concept to gauge the accuracy and feasibility of converting
                existing data into a machine processable knowledge representation. Statistical
                Independent Verification and Validation (IV&amp;V) methodologies would be employed
                with product manufacturers and subject matter experts (SME) to quantify the accuracy
                of the AI tool and to also support continuous process improvement [6]. </para>
            <para>Eventually, these knowledge graphs could be integrated into device, biologic, and
                medication extensions to SNOMED®, LOINC®, and RxNorm® as part of the FDA SHIELD
                program’s effort to provide integrated knowledge management and integrated knowledge
                exchange capabilities. As extensions, this encoded knowledge can be made generally
                available and consumable by the FDA, other HHS and health-care focused agencies,
                health IT providers, health-care providers, and the citizenry at large. </para>
            <para>General knowledge organized by domain, written in a formal language, and combined
                with expert curation and human validation of generated knowledge will allow
                enterprises to tap into and utilize knowledge previously locked away in disparate
                documents, sources, and systems. In the process, they enable faster and more
                accurate decision-making. </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Methods</title>
        <section>
            <title>Objectives and Purpose</title>
            <para>This AI project will open the door for extensive secondary use of knowledge
                derived from FDA product labels that will provide insights and information
                previously either inaccessible—or of poor or inconsistent quality—due to the high
                resource and time commitment needed to manually query data. </para>
            <para>The team would first work to develop a process to transcode data from the existing
                human-readable and text-based files into a highly structured, machine-readable, and
                standardized format which the FDA SHIELD program has been developing as part of
                their HL7 standards activities [7]. AI models would need to be trained on existing
                FDA labels for approved products and existing medical terminology standard
                specifications (e.g., SNOMED®, LOINC®, RxNorm®, etc.), and a small subset of FDA
                products (drugs, devices, biologics, etc.) would need to be selected for testing and
                creation of a proof of concept to validate processes and begin statistical process
                control efforts. </para>
            <para>Once the knowledge base has matured and grown, organizations and individuals
                submitting products to the FDA centers for review can use this resource to identify
                a standardized and repeatable way to represent the pertinent medical terminology
                concepts, codes, and information associated with their products. This information
                can then be shared with manufactures, health systems, and users to drastically
                improve the standardization and representation of FDA-approved products across the
                healthcare ecosystem and the quality, interoperability, and queryability of data
                associated with these products. </para>
            <para>Finally, once this resource has been approved for public use, healthcare
                professionals will be able to query the knowledge base to gain new insight into
                various healthcare products, like understanding the specific LOINC code to use for a
                laboratory test, the excipient ingredients in each medication, and the correct units
                of measure to report the results of a test.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Systems Safety Framework</title>
            <para>To incorporate AI capabilities in LIDR database management, utilizing a system
                safety framework to diagnose, control, and solve safety hazards can proactively
                identify and mitigate hazards before they occur. This framework analyzes and
                considers the dependencies present between components of the system and their
                culmination to produce safety hazards. It details <emphasis role="italic"
                    >how</emphasis> hazards occurred with the surrounding context, not just simply
                what caused them. </para>
            <para>System Safety analyses the hierarchical control structures with a system using a
                top-down approach. Differing from other transitional forms of hazard management,
                Systems Safety views the pieces of systems and systems as more than a linear chain
                of events and rather accounts for complexities that other approaches do not. </para>
            <para>It is important for this change effort to be synchronized, rigorous, and optimized
                to achieve the desired goals at scale. To facilitate the type of change required to
                build a machine-processible knowledge representation, it is necessary to embrace a
                system engineering approach for redesigning the current health data ecosystem to be
                more trustworthy, reliable, and safe. Taking a system approach, we have been able to
                address safety and quality management in a holistic manner – instead of a fragmented
                approach which could produce small improvements in one part of the system while
                simultaneously jeopardizing quality in other parts of the system.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Required Data and Information</title>
            <para>Existing FDA Product labeling information, in a variety of forms, would need to be
                collected from different sources. In most cases, this information is publicly
                available [7]. Some of these files are stored in the FDA’s Structured Product
                Labeling (SPL) archive and can be accessed via the FDALabel or the National Library
                of Medicine’s DailyMed web-based applications [8,9].<superscript/></para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Potential Risks</title>
            <para>This approach does not pose any direct safety issues to patients, the public, or
                general users beyond what is present in the current process. While any errors or
                incorrect entries in the standardized representation of these labels should be
                caught by FDA during the review process, submitters are strongly encouraged to
                manually review and verify these inputs for accuracy and applicability. </para>
            <para>Embarking on this effort and adding statistical process control to validate the
                encoding and curation of these labels will improve the quality, safety, and
                effectiveness of FDA product labels and of the products associated with these
                labels. </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Benefits of Approach</title>
        <para><anchor xml:id="Toc121912435"/>This approach will benefit a wide range of individuals
            in the healthcare ecosystem at every stage of the Total Product Lifecycle (TPLC) [10].
            By providing a highly structured knowledge base that captures critical information
            associated with FDA-approved products and provides guidance on how to encode this
            information, FDA can help to ensure safer patient care through improved RWD quality. </para>
        <para>The first group that will benefit are the individuals, groups, or organizations that
            are submitting medical products to the various centers at FDA for review and approval.
            This proposition will help them represent pertinent information regarding their product
            in a standardized way that can be shared with other organizations to improve data
            capture and secondary use. </para>
        <para>The other organizations or systems using their product, like health informaticists
            encoding a new medication into their electronic health record system or laboratories
            reporting tests and test results, will benefit by using the knowledge base to gain
            access to clear, authoritative guidance and information for how to encode data generated
            by or about FDA-approved products. </para>
        <para>Once product developers and health systems have standardized the representation of
            their products, FDA and the various centers that perform review processes, like the
            Center for Drug Evaluation and Research (CDER), the Center for Biologics Evaluation and
            Research (CBER), the Center for Veterinary Medicine (CVM), the Center for Devices and
            Radiological Health (CDRH) will have more accurate, reliable, and impactful RWD for use
            in review and determination. By converting human-readable, text-based information into a
            more machine-processable format and standardizing the representation of the devices,
            medications, biologics, and products they are reviewing, these centers will have precise
            information to gather insights and perform expansive analyses in a more resource and
            cost-efficient way. </para>
        <para>This approach also opens the door for extensive secondary use and could lead to a
            drastic increase in the use and impact of data associated with FDA-approved products,
            while simultaneously improving the efficiency and accuracy of encoding said information.
            Ultimately, the improvements to the quality of data being used by these various
            healthcare professionals, organizations, and FDA will lead to improved patient outcomes,
            more informed policy making, and faster reactions to emerging health conditions as
            reliable and trustworthy data is more readily accessible.</para>
        <para>Finally, this effort would increase the output quality of other healthcare-based AI
            tools. As the knowledge base we propose is increasingly used by players in the
            healthcare ecosystem, the consistency, granularity, and reproducibility of RWD will
            improve, which will thereby enable secondary-use, custom AI tools (EHR AI-based Clinical
            Decision Support) and mega-LLMs (e.g., ChatGPT) to be trained on better inputs and
            generate more useful, actionable outputs.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Discussion</title>
        <para>Tools developed through this effort will be highly leveraged, providing widely
            available—as well as high value—knowledge resources while only requiring a limited set
            of expert reviewers to curate the knowledge. In addition, the provided knowledge
            resources can be used in training sets, and in test sets, further leveraging the upfront
            investment. Hundreds of thousands of healthcare professionals and citizens will be able
            to use the knowledge base and associated products. </para>
        <para>First, experts in data representation and SMEs from the CDER, CBER, CVM, CDRH, and
            others are anticipated to use our tool to verify and validate the accurate conversion of
            human-readable data into the highly structured computer-readable knowledge base. Once
            the tool and knowledge base have matured, manufacturers could directly use these tools
            to encode their product labels as part of their submission to the FDA. These tools could
            reduce the manufactures documentation burden, improve the quality and utility of the
            submitted application, and speed time to market. </para>
        <para>The FDA, organizations, clinicians, researchers, laboratorians, health policy experts,
            informaticists and other healthcare professionals around the country are expected to
            query the resulting FDA regulated product knowledge base as a source of critical
            information on medications, tests, biologics, and devices and as a guide for encoding
            FDA-approved products and associated information. </para>
        <para>This tool is center-agnostic and would impact medications, biologics, devices, and
            other products reviewed by CDER, CBER, CVM, and CDRH.</para>
        <section>
            <title><anchor xml:id="Toc192080261"/>Quantitative Impact:</title>
            <para>As of November 18th, 2024, the FDA, and its respective centers oversee roughly
                175,000 medical devices, 97,000 over-the-counter medications, 58,000 prescription
                drugs and biological products, 3,000 animal medications, and more
                [11].<superscript/></para>
            <para>This approach would provide guidance for how to encode all relevant information
                associated with these products in a standardized and repeatable way that replaces
                the current unstandardized and manual process of encoding FDA-approved product
                information. It would provide guidance on the existing medications, biologics,
                devices, and products to ensure they are accurately represented and encoded around
                the country and provide recommendations for novel products that have not been
                reviewed previously. FDA’s CDER approved 55 new drugs in 2023, all of which would
                benefit from knowledge base entries that representing product information and
                guidance on how to represent them in RWD and in analytics [12]. Detailing how to
                encode these products would then support secondary use of the data in a way that
                would save users countless hours and extensive manual review as they could easily,
                accurately, and efficiently query a large knowledge base for pertinent and impactful
                information.</para>
            <para>Improving the quality of the RWD used by FDA will also have substantial financial
                benefits as poor data quality costs organizations, on average, $12.9 million per
                year and the US $3.1 trillion per year [13,14]. Perhaps the greatest quantitative
                impact would be on patient safety. Improving the quality of data could reduce the
                250,000 annual patient deaths cause by preventable medical and electronic health
                record errors [15].<superscript/></para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title><anchor xml:id="Toc192080262"/>Qualitative Impact:</title>
            <para>This approach would improve the quality, interoperability, and reusability of data
                collected by the FDA and would enhance the use and impact of RWD. </para>
            <para>By developing a process to standardize how devices, products, medications, tests,
                and pertinent information are encoded, the FDA and other organizations will gain
                unprecedented insight into the data associated with these products. Currently, these
                products are encoded in non-standardized and suboptimal ways, which limits the
                ability to query and collect comprehensive and complete information on a product. If
                the query is not manually built in an extremely accurate way to capture all the
                potential representations, the results could be incomplete and provide only a
                partial picture. </para>
            <para> Implementing AI would reduce the variation in representation of data about or
                generated by FDA-approved products and would allow users to query our knowledge base
                to extract trustworthy information, trends, and changes to inform decision making
                and the delivery of care. This proposal would open the door for secondary use that
                is currently not viable due to suboptimal data representation. It would also
                drastically improve the interoperability and reusability of data, as all parties in
                the healthcare ecosystem would have the same understanding and representation of a
                product.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>References</title>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>U.S. Food and Drug Administration. (2021, August 27). Considerations for
                        the use of real-world data and real-world evidence to support regulatory
                        decision-making for drug and biological products. FDA. 
                    <link
                        xlink:href="https://www.fda.gov/regulatory-information/search-fda-guidance-documents/considerations-use-real-world-data-and-real-world-evidence-support-regulatory-decision-making-drug"
                        >https://www.fda.gov/regulatory-information/search-fda-guidance-documents/considerations-use-real-world-data-and-real-world-evidence-support-regulatory-decision-making-drug</link>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>U.S. Food and Drug Administration. (n.d.). FDA's labeling resources for
                        human prescription drugs. FDA. <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.fda.gov/drugs/laws-acts-and-rules/fdas-labeling-resources-human-prescription-drugs"
                            >https://www.fda.gov/drugs/laws-acts-and-rules/fdas-labeling-resources-human-prescription-drugs</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>U.S. Food and Drug Administration. (2023, September). Mifepristone REMS
                        program: Patient agreement form. FDA. <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.fda.gov/media/177984/download"
                            >https://www.fda.gov/media/177984/download</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences. (n.d.). Substance
                        record for d3a9972a-392a-4ce8-b10f-d1120b4b393b. Global Substance
                        Registration System. <link
                            xlink:href="https://gsrs.ncats.nih.gov/ginas/app/ui/substances/d3a9972a-392a-4ce8-b10f-d1120b4b393b"
                            >https://gsrs.ncats.nih.gov/ginas/app/ui/substances/d3a9972a-392a-4ce8-b10f-d1120b4b393b</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>U.S. Food and Drug Administration. (n.d.). FDA's global substance
                        registration system. FDA. <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.fda.gov/industry/fda-data-standards-advisory-board/fdas-global-substance-registration-system"
                            >https://www.fda.gov/industry/fda-data-standards-advisory-board/fdas-global-substance-registration-system</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>U.S. Food and Drug Administration. (2015, July). Analytical procedures and
                        methods validation for drugs and biologics. FDA. <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.fda.gov/files/drugs/published/Analytical-Procedures-and-Methods-Validation-for-Drugs-and-Biologics.pdf"
                            >https://www.fda.gov/files/drugs/published/Analytical-Procedures-and-Methods-Validation-for-Drugs-and-Biologics.pdf</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>U.S. Food and Drug Administration. (n.d.). Structured product labeling
                        resources. FDA. <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.fda.gov/industry/fda-data-standards-advisory-board/structured-product-labeling-resources"
                            >https://www.fda.gov/industry/fda-data-standards-advisory-board/structured-product-labeling-resources</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>U.S. Food and Drug Administration. (n.d.). FDA labels by application
                        number. FDA. <link xlink:href="https://labels.fda.gov/applicationnumber.cfm"
                            >https://labels.fda.gov/applicationnumber.cfm</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>National Library of Medicine. (n.d.). DailyMed. U.S. National Institutes
                        of Health. Retrieved [today's date], from <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.dailymed.nlm.nih.gov/dailymed/index.cfm"
                            >https://www.dailymed.nlm.nih.gov/dailymed/index.cfm</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>U.S. Food and Drug Administration. (n.d.). Total product life cycle
                        advisory program (TAP). FDA. <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/how-study-and-market-your-device/total-product-life-cycle-advisory-program-tap"
                            >https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/how-study-and-market-your-device/total-product-life-cycle-advisory-program-tap</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>U.S. Food and Drug Administration. (n.d.). What does FDA regulate? FDA.
                            <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.fda.gov/about-fda/what-we-do/what-does-fda-regulate"
                            >https://www.fda.gov/about-fda/what-we-do/what-does-fda-regulate</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>U.S. Food and Drug Administration. (n.d.). Novel drug approvals for 2023.
                        FDA. <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.fda.gov/drugs/novel-drug-approvals-fda/novel-drug-approvals-2023"
                            >https://www.fda.gov/drugs/novel-drug-approvals-fda/novel-drug-approvals-2023</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Wealth DCI. (2023). The hidden cost of bad data [White paper]. <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.wealth-dci.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/dci-whitepaper-the_hidden_cost_of_bad_data.pdf"
                            >https://www.wealth-dci.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/dci-whitepaper-the_hidden_cost_of_bad_data.pdf</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Anodot. (2022, March 15). The price you pay for poor data quality. <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.anodot.com/blog/price-pay-poor-data-quality/"
                            >https://www.anodot.com/blog/price-pay-poor-data-quality/</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Mack, H. (2018, February 22). Medical errors are the third-leading cause
                        of death in America. <link>CNBC.
                            https://www.cnbc.com/2018/02/22/medical-errors-third-leading-cause-of-death-in-america.html</link></para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
    </section> 
    
</chapter> 
