<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.1">
    <title>Versioned Foundation</title>
    <para>In the following sections we will discuss the Versioned Foundation Layer of the Knowledge
        Architecture. </para>
    <para>The Versioned Foundation provides the essential building blocks for a common model,
        enabling the consistent transformation of diverse standards into this model to support
        interoperability across different systems. It ensures that all architectural modules are
        strictly version controlled over time. This layer incorporates key interoperability elements
        such as object identity, versioning, modularity, data exchange methods, and knowledge
        representation as outlined in the figure below.</para>
    <para> </para>
    <figure xml:id="KnowledgeArchitectureVersionedFoundation">
        <title>Versioned Foundation Layer</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/KnowledgeArchitectureVersionedFoundation.svg"
                    scale="25" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>As reviewed in the TermINology Knowledge Architecture (Tinkar)
        <?oxy_comment_start author="rgeorgacopoulos" timestamp="20250718T205956-0500" comment="taken from &quot;TermINology Knowledge Architecture (Tinkar)&quot; section of the IKM Background Part. need to pull in reference

HL7 Logical Model: Standardized Terminology Knowledgebase, Release 1. Terminology Knowledge Architecture Informative Ballot. HL7 Vocabulary Work Group. August 2021. "?>
        we are aiming to improve IKM capabilities and advancing an existing Health Level Seven
        International (HL7) project within the Vocabulary Working Group known as the ‘Guidelines for
        a Standardized Terminology Knowledge base”, also known as TermINology Knowledge Architecture
        (Tinkar). Tinkar is intended to provide an architecture that delivers integrated terminology
        to the healthcare enterprise and its information systems. Tinkar addresses the differences
        in management and structure across reference terminology, and with local concepts and code
        lists/value sets.</para><?oxy_comment_end?>
</chapter>
