<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.1">
    <title>DeloitteBAA_Task 1.4.1 Summary of Findings - Functional and non-Functional Issues Related
        to Knowledge Management Proof of Concept_Months 13-24</title>
    <section>
        <title>Disclaimers and Notes</title>
        <para>This document reflects the views of the authors and should not be construed to
            represent FDA’s views or policies.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Purpose</title>
        <para>In today’s healthcare ecosystem, there is a need for high-quality and accurate data as
            healthcare organizations becoming increasingly reliant on electronic health records
            (EHRs), laboratory information systems (LISs), and other electronic information systems.
            Terminology standards are a primary tool that many organizations use to work towards
            this goal and improve the quality and accuracy of their data. Terminology standards aim
            to ensure information is captured and represented in a repeatable and standardized
            format so that other organizations and stakeholders using said terminology standard have
            a common understanding of the data. While terminology standards are a useful tool,
            extensive knowledge management (KM) is needed to identify, manage, and share the
            standardized data that these systems and standards capture. However, as data flows
            within and between healthcare systems, the use of different terminology standards, KM
            processes, and systems themselves can pose a threat to the integrity of data.</para>
        <para>Integrated Knowledge Management (IKM) is an approach to data management that aims to
            maintain the meaning, integrity, and quality of data as it travels within and between
            healthcare systems. IKM is an evolving approach to manage disparate terminology
            standards using a common, centralized, and repeatable representation of data. The use of
            a common model supports the interoperability of data between disparate terminology
            standards, well documented version control even when different terminology standards
            employ their own versioning practices, and the incorporation of new or emerging
            terminology standards. IKM will use an iterative approach to build upon previous work on
            Resource Description Frameworks (RDFs) and property graphs with novel ideas and
            concepts. There is no reference or best practice guide for how an IKM solution can or
            should operate and will therefore require extensive research, prototyping, and
            development. </para>
        <para>While IKM may pose as a daunting task for many organizations due to the large barrier
            to entry and resource commitment, our team is not the only stakeholder working towards
            IKM solutions. Systematized Nomenclature of Medicine Clinical Terms (SNOMED CT®) and
            Logical Observation Identifiers, Names, and Codes (LOINC®) have announced a
            collaborative partnership to increase the interoperability of their data and standards
            by facilitating the identification of synonymous concepts and reducing duplication in
            the standards. Our work prototyping and trialing an IKM reference implementation has
            given us insight into various challenges, work arounds, and best practices. Our work has
            identified functional and non-functional areas of IKM that require further exploration
            and refinement to support more widespread adoption, which can be shared with other
            organizations and stakeholders to shape their work and support a unified
            approach.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Aims</title>
        <para>The aims of this document are to summarize our current experience working with,
            implementing, and promoting integrated knowledge management.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Summary of Findings</title>
        <para>Over the past two years, our team has been working to develop an IKM reference
            implementation, the Knowledge Management Environment (Komet), to demonstrate IKM
            capabilities. Our work with Komet builds upon data property graph and RDF foundations
            and incorporates new concepts like versioned concept-oriented property graph
            representation. Due to the relatively novel nature of Komet and IKM, our team did not
            have guidelines or best practices to follow. Our initial work serves as a prototype that
            identifies functional and non-functional areas related to IKM that should be further
            explored. Throughout our experience, we have documented the following lessons learned,
            best practices, and challenges to improve the adoptability, functionality, and
            development of IKM as our team and other stakeholders work towards future
            iterations.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Knowledge Management</title>
            <para>The Food and Drug Administration (FDA) Systemic Harmonization and Interoperability
                Enhancement for Laboratory Data (SHIELD) team rapidly developed an IKM prototype
                leveraging the latest Terminology Knowledge Architecture (Tinkar) data model
                standard to showcase IKM capabilities at the SNOMED CT® conference in October of
                2023. Further development was completed to mature the initial prototype and
                introduce new features and industry standards, such as Fast Healthcare
                Interoperability Resources (FHIR). These latest developments were showcased at two
                Health Level Seven (HL7) Connectathons – events where our solutions were tested with
                others in the healthcare industry. Through this effort over the last two years,
                we’ve identified multiple findings that have been since resolved or will need to be
                resolved in the future.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Requirements Gathering and Tracking</title>
                <para>As each clinical terminology standard has its own proprietary data
                    representation and tooling to both view and author data, the ability to
                    represent multiple standards with a common underlying data model and view or
                    author across standards in a single environment is an unprecedented idea. IKM
                    would influence a large community of users, such as hospitals, laboratories and
                    clinical informaticists so there are many thoughts and opinions about how IKM
                    should work and what features would be important. Though the potential
                    stakeholder base is large, the access to the community to illicit requirements
                    is very limited. While we were able to conduct user interviews during our User
                    Interface/User Experience (UI/UX) analysis to gain some understanding of
                    necessary system functionalities, we do not have regular access to those
                    participants. </para>
                <para>To solve this, we’re leveraging experts within the SHIELD community to
                    identify high priority capabilities that will be prioritized for upcoming
                    milestones. These milestones will take shape in conferences, community events,
                    and other demonstration opportunities. For example, we have leveraged HL7
                    Connectathon events to conduct real-world testing scenarios with interested
                    stakeholders.</para>
                <para>Leading up to the 2023 SNOMED CT® conference, we found that while we wanted to
                    support rapid development, we still needed a clear understanding of what system
                    capabilities were important to showcase for the demonstration, detailed
                    documentation in the form of user stories for the developers to reference and
                    the ability to track that they were completed on schedule. </para>
                <para>As seen in Figure 1: IKM Product Backlog Epic Board, we established a new
                    process to describe the system capabilities in the form of Agile epics and plot
                    them against the appropriate milestones to generate our product feature backlog.
                    As per agile development best practices, these epics are revisited weekly to be
                    defined, refined, and prioritized. These epics are then decomposed into user
                    stories with defined acceptance criteria for the development teams to develop
                    against in 3 week increments or sprints. [1]</para>
                <para><figure xml:id="IKMProductBacklogEpicBoard2">
                        <title>IKM Product Backlog Epic Board</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="../images/IKM%20Product%20Backlog%20Epic%20Board.svg"
                                    scale="100" align="center"/> 
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                </para>
                <para>As the IKM community grows, we will leverage the open-source nature of the
                    project to track feature requests through submitted GitHub issues. [2] This
                    external issue tracker will be integrated more fully in the future but will
                    allow us to track feature requests against other priorities and communicated
                    releases back to the IKM community. [3]</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Team Dependency Management</title>
                <para>In our ongoing efforts to enhance the development of the Komet application, we
                    have significantly matured our processes to track work across teams and manage
                    dependencies more effectively. In order to scale the development efforts to work
                    across multiple domains at once, we have divided the teams into multiple
                    workstreams, each focused on a particular area of development. We currently have
                    six different workstreams, including two international teams with deep JavaFX
                    expertise, contributing to the same code base.</para>
                <para>By adopting advanced project management techniques such as story mapping and
                    ticket linking, we have created a more transparent and collaborative
                    environment. Story mapping, as seen in Figure 2 allows us to visualize the
                    entire user journey, ensuring that all team members have a clear understanding
                    of the product's goals, priorities, and the steps needed to achieve them. The
                    defined epics and prioritization are revisited weekly to ensure that the teams
                    are focused on the highest priority tasks and that the requirements are
                    clear.</para>
                <para><figure xml:id="IKMEpicBacklogStoryMapinJira">
                        <title>IKM Epic Backlog Story Map in Jira</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="../images/IKM%20Epic%20Backlog%20Story%20Map%20in%20Jira.svg"
                                    scale="100" align="center"/> 
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                </para>
                <para>Ticket linking, depicted in Figure 3, enables us to track dependencies and
                    relationships between tasks, ensuring that work is seamlessly coordinated across
                    different teams. </para>
                <para><figure xml:id="ViewofEpicwithCrossTeamStoryDependencies">
                        <title>Name of Image Normally Written</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="../images/View%20of%20Epic%20with%20Cross%20Team%20Story%20Dependencies.svg"
                                    scale="100" align="center"/> 
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                </para>
                <para>Furthermore, we have shifted our focus from a broad array of features to
                    prioritizing high-impact features that align with our strategic objectives. This
                    prioritization ensures that our development efforts are concentrated on
                    delivering the most valuable functionalities to our users, thereby improving the
                    overall quality and efficiency of the Komet application. By streamlining our
                    processes and honing in on priority features, we have enhanced our ability to
                    deliver a robust, user-centric product that meets the evolving needs of our
                    stakeholders.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Naming Convention</title>
                <para>One of the significant challenges in the development of the IKM team within
                    the Komet application is the consistent and clear naming and terminology of
                    features and architecture in the databases. Firstly, the lack of standardized
                    naming conventions can lead to confusion and miscommunication among development
                    teams, as different teams might use varied terms for the same feature or
                    component. This inconsistency can result in errors during integration and
                    maintenance phases, as developers may struggle to understand or locate specific
                    elements within the database. Secondly, the evolving nature of the project often
                    introduces new features and architectural changes, necessitating frequent
                    updates to the terminology and documentation. Keeping all teams aligned on these
                    updates can be challenging, especially in a fast-paced development environment. </para>
                <para>Additionally, the complexity of the Komet application, which integrates with
                    multiple systems and data sources, further complicates the naming conventions.
                    Ensuring that the terminology is intuitive and reflective of the tool's
                    functionality is crucial for maintaining clarity and efficiency. Lastly,
                    aligning the terminology with regulatory requirements and industry standards
                    adds another layer of complexity, as it requires continuous collaboration with
                    regulatory experts to ensure compliance. Addressing these challenges requires a
                    concerted effort to establish and enforce standardized naming conventions,
                    regular communication and training sessions, and a robust documentation process
                    to keep all stakeholders informed and aligned.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title><anchor xml:id="Toc185598261"/>User Experience and User Interface (UI/UX)
                    Design</title>
                <para>In early 2023, a UI/UX assessment for IKM was conducted by Deloitte/Amplified
                    to better understand the needs and pain points of healthcare professionals in
                    their daily operations working with healthcare knowledge. The goal was to use
                    findings from the assessment to determine user profiles, requirements, and
                    priority, which were then used to strategize a human centered UI/UX design for a
                    Next Gen IKM platform that promotes data interoperability. </para>
                <para>The assessment was conducted in five phases:</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A landscape analysis to evaluate the competitive landscape of similar
                            products.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A heuristic evaluation of the old Komet version to identify features
                            to keep in the Next Gen version.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>User interviews with multiple professionals in the healthcare
                            space—such as clinicians, health informaticists, public health
                            scientist—to uncover specific needs and pain points of potential
                            users.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A UI/UX workshop to discuss findings from interviews and align on
                            future UI/UX strategy.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Creation and prioritization of user stories for future sprints based
                            on workshop results.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
                <para>Some of the challenges faced by the UI/UX team include representing different
                    knowledge standards with different requirements for viewing/editing in a
                    standardized way, abstracting complexities behind-the-scenes for an easier user
                    experience and designing in a way that supports iterative development while
                    still meeting future requirements.</para>
                <para>The team plans to tackle these challenges by identifying commonalities and
                    differences between user interfaces and data schema of existing knowledge
                    standards. The aim of these planned activities is to better understand how to
                    design a standard UI and conduct periodic user evaluation sessions for voluntary
                    user feedback within the healthcare industry. Healthcare stakeholders can help
                    the UI community explore the latest design and share insightful information in
                    the user experience. They can also influence the process of building modular and
                    re-usable UI components that allow flexible and adaptable development in an
                    agile environment with changing requirements.</para>
                <para>Over the past two years, significant progress has been made in the development
                    and enhancement of the Next Gen IKM platform. The insights gained from the
                    original assessment were instrumental in shaping the initial design and
                    development of the platform. As we continue to develop the Next Gen IKM
                    platform, new challenges have emerged that require innovative solutions. One of
                    the primary challenges we are currently facing is ensuring that the designs are
                    intuitive and user-friendly for the healthcare professionals who will be using
                    the platform. Despite the extensive user interface research and designs that
                    have been developed, there is still uncertainty about whether these designs are
                    truly intuitive for the end-users. This uncertainty can potentially impact the
                    overall usability and adoption of the platform.</para>
                <para>To address this challenge, we plan to conduct comprehensive user interviews
                    using both wireframes and developed functionality. These reviews involve
                    presenting the wireframes and functional prototypes to a diverse group of
                    healthcare professionals, including clinicians, health informaticists, and
                    public health scientists. Participants will be asked to perform specific tasks
                    using the platform, while observers take note of any difficulties or confusion
                    encountered.</para>
                <para>These interviews will be crucial in gaining perspectives on the platform's
                    usability and adoptability, as well as identifying any missing or key features
                    that need to be incorporated. The feedback gathered from these sessions will be
                    meticulously analyzed to identify common pain points and areas for improvement.
                    This iterative process ensures that the platform evolves in a way that aligns
                    with the real-world needs and workflows of its users. Additionally, usability
                    reviews will help in validating the design decisions made so far and provide
                    actionable insights for future development sprints. By continuously engaging
                    with users and incorporating their feedback, we aim to create a platform that is
                    not only functional but also intuitive and easy to use. We remain committed to
                    continuous improvement and user-centered design, ensuring that the platform
                    evolves in a way that supports the dynamic and complex nature of healthcare
                    knowledge management.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>DevOps Processes</title>
                <para>In the current state of health IT, healthcare data standard organizations have
                    implemented restrictive licensing around their proprietary data and technology
                    which creates siloes and the inability to collaborate across standards. IKM
                    provides an open-source solution that could be used across the community to
                    collaborate and further reduce these data siloes. Komet is an open-source
                    solution in the form of an installed Java application that provides users the
                    ability to visualize, manage and extend disparate medical terminologies.
                    [4]</para>
                <para>Early in the development phase, we identified that we would need to make an
                    investment in DevOps technologies and tooling to allow our open-source solutions
                    to be rapidly developed and released to reach the largest audiences possible. We
                    began by hosting our DevOps tools, as it was the quickest way to begin rapid
                    prototyping. However, through this process, we’ve found that the hosting of
                    these tools requires more overhead and manhours than we would like. Our larger
                    goals and priorities require developers’ time to contribute to our solutions
                    rather than supporting our DevOps tools. </para>
                <para>Within the past 6 months, we’ve been able to significantly reduce the
                    investment in maintaining our DevOps tools by migrating from hosting services to
                    cloud services. We’ve fully transitioned from GitLab and Jenkins to GitHub,
                    utilizing GitHub Actions for Continuous Integration/Continuous Delivery (CI/CD)
                    processes and decommissioned unused tools and infrastructure. This has
                    streamlined the development process in many ways, such as allowing us to have a
                    single code repository and more simplified DevOps processes for releases.
                    However, due to the limitations around the licensed data that Komet leverages,
                    we will continue to host an internal artifact repository that houses the
                    transformed versions of various medical terminology standards, such as SNOMED
                    CT.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Data Layer Development</title>
                <para>As new knowledge standards are transformed into the Tinkar model, the more the
                    need for ease of code troubleshooting and management becomes apparent. [5]
                    Reinforcing the code to also handle different types of data and types of
                    programming languages will also keep the data ingestion and export free of
                    conflicts. Additionally, adding in a layer of abstraction is needed to allow all
                    types of users to set up and use Komet. For large scale development and
                    automation to be possible these improvements to code and architecture will be
                    crucial. </para>
                <section>
                    <title>Bindings</title>
                    <para>Currently, Tinkar Core uses Tinkar Terms to call certain Java variables
                        that represent retrievable concepts from the Tinkar datastore. As the
                        codebase develops and changes, maintaining these terms can become
                        challenging, especially with increasing complexity. Each affected Tinkar
                        Term must be manually identified and updated, which is time-consuming and
                        prone to human error. By creating an automated solution like a bindings
                        library, updates can be made efficiently and integrated into a dependency
                        management system. This approach would streamline the process and reduce the
                        risk of errors.</para>
                    <para>During the past year, the IKM team implemented bindings to be run as an
                        asynchronous task, which can be easily implemented in Komet and wrapped to
                        run as a plugin in the Maven data architecture. Generating bindings from
                        Komet is beneficial because if you are authoring starter data in Komet, and
                        you will need to export it so that your data transformation has the
                        necessary variables to use. Additionally, it allows us to generate
                        meaningful bindings from modules, membership patterns, and arbitrary
                        selections of concept patterns and semantics. During development, the team
                        determined that generating bindings from a module or membership pattern is
                        the most useful approach for our data architecture and user needs.</para>
                </section>
                <section>
                    <title>Data Architecture</title>
                    <para>In managing the complexity and collaboration required for IKM, there is a
                        critical need for tools that can automate dependency management. These tools
                        should standardize build processes, enforce project structure, integrate
                        automated testing, and generate documentation to ensure consistency and
                        reliability across development environments. Additionally, robust version
                        control is essential. This includes facilitated collaboration through
                        branching and merging, support for distributed development, and maintenance
                        of a detailed history of changes. Integration with CI/CD pipelines is also
                        crucial to enhance efficiency and accountability. Without these tools,
                        development efforts can become fragmented, inconsistent, and inefficient.
                        This fragmentation hinders reliable software delivery and effective project
                        management.</para>
                    <para>The IKM team implemented a new Maven data architecture to support a
                        reliable and repeatable data transformation process was determined to be
                        necessary. This standardizes and streamlines the handling of SNOMED CT data,
                        facilitating internal distribution and integration. This approach enhances
                        data integrity and consistency, ultimately supporting accurate and efficient
                        reasoning and inference within IKM. It starts with the SNOMED CT origin
                        module, which involves unzipping, packaging, and deploying raw data files
                        from an official SNOMED CT distribution. Then, the Manifest Maven plugin
                        creates a manifest file and assembles everything into a new zip file with an
                        appropriate name and version. This standardized zip file can be uploaded to
                        nexus for internal distribution. Next, the pipeline module builds a database
                        in spined-array format, which is the native Tinkar format, by way of
                        invoking the Tinkar starter data, SNOMED starter data, and SNOMED
                        transformation plugins. Then the Web Ontology Language (OWL) Transformation
                        plugin is executed, which converts the raw OWL syntax from the source
                        distribution file into a format that can be read by the IKM Reasoner. Next
                        the Reasoner plugin runs which creates inferred definitions for each of the
                        OWL stated axioms from the previous step. In the verification process, a set
                        of integration tests are executed which validate that all the concepts,
                        semantics, and patterns that are present in the source distribution files
                        are present in the generated spined-array database. The final output is a
                        re-zipped file with a manifest in the target directory, ready for further
                        use or export.</para>
                    <para>The approach provides users the ability to Bring-Your-Own-Data (BYOD) in
                        terms of the standard they want to be transformed and run it through the
                        data transformation pipeline based on a few simple commands. This allows us
                        to avoid the issue of distributing these transformed data artifacts in a
                        private and secure way.</para>
                </section>
                <section>
                    <title>Integration Testing</title>
                    <para>Validation of transformation process has proven to be a significant
                        challenge. Manual testing of SNOMED CT's 350,000+ concepts to ensure
                        accurate transformation, for example, is impractical due to the sheer
                        volume, complexity of relationships, and dynamic nature of the dataset. The
                        task would require an enormous amount of time and resources, and even then,
                        it would be highly prone to human error and inconsistencies. The intricate
                        web of connections and continuous updates further complicate manual
                        validation efforts.</para>
                    <para>Automated testing, on the other hand, offers significant advantages in
                        terms of efficiency, accuracy, and scalability. Automated tools can quickly
                        and precisely validate large volumes of data, ensuring comprehensive
                        coverage of all aspects of SNOMED CT, including relationships, attributes,
                        and hierarchical structures. This approach reduces the risk of errors and
                        ensures consistent and repeatable validation processes, which are essential
                        for maintaining the integrity and reliability of the dataset.</para>
                    <para>As part of data transformation validation, the IKM team developed a suite
                        of integration tests that evaluate each of the SNOMED CT data files to
                        validate data loss. These tests have allowed the team to identify potential
                        areas where data might have been compromised and address those.</para>
                    <para>One further challenge we encountered is how to escalate issues found to
                        the appropriate groups. SNOMED International, for example, provides a
                        Content Request Service for the community to request changes or identify
                        issues. While this process provides the user visibility into where their
                        request stands, it does not allow for dialog and consensus driven approach
                        like an open-source community would.</para>
                </section>
                <section>
                    <title>Data Distribution Format</title>
                    <para>One issue identified in data distribution for knowledge standards is
                        ensuring interoperability and seamless data exchange across diverse
                        information systems. The challenge lies in finding a programming
                        language-neutral format that can efficiently serialize structured data while
                        accommodating the specific requirements and preferences of different
                        industries. By leveraging protocol buffers, the goal is to create a
                        versatile and open-source solution that facilitates easy sharing and
                        importing of data. Additionally, the IKM team has noticed limitations of
                        existing standards like FHIR in capturing the full complexity of models like
                        Tinkar which would lead to less data being exchanged. Additionally, it is
                        open-source code and does not require a licensing to implement. This would
                        allow the data to be exported in easy to share formats that can be simply
                        shared and imported.</para>
                    <para>One recent challenge that the team encountered is that the healthcare
                        industry prefers that healthcare data is exchanged via FHIR (Fast Healthcare
                        Interoperability Resources), which is a standard developed by HL7 (Health
                        Level Seven International). In support of the Tinkar standard ballot, we
                        participated in the HL7 Connectathon where we demonstrated Komet and a
                        FHIR-based change set export. Through this effort, we determined that the
                        FHIR format does not capture the robustness of the Tinkar model.</para>
                </section>
                <section>
                    <title>Data Retrieval and Curation</title>
                    <para>As the Komet user base grows, it is essential to accommodate users with
                        varying levels of experience. Currently, the Tinkar database requires
                        significant coding skills and knowledge of lower-level data structures to
                        retrieve and manipulate data elements, limiting the number of users who can
                        implement meaningful solutions. Additionally, integrating new knowledge
                        standards demands handling intricate data mappings, transformations, and
                        validations to ensure data conforms to standardized formats.</para>
                    <para>The project also requires robust data retrieval mechanisms to support
                        real-time access and updates, including efficient query systems, optimized
                        data storage, and seamless integration with existing healthcare information
                        systems. Addressing these technical complexities is crucial for the success
                        of the FDA SHIELD project and for enabling users to leverage the full
                        capabilities of Komet and the Tinkar data model.</para>
                    <para>Creating an abstraction layer and user-friendly interface will streamline
                        working with and updating Tinkar data, allowing users to utilize Komet to
                        its full potential. Additionally, automated data mapping and transformation
                        tools, scalable data infrastructure, and collaborative features with
                        community support can further enhance data retrieval and curation processes.
                        These solutions aim to reduce the need for extensive coding and technical
                        knowledge, improve user accessibility, and foster broader adoption and
                        effective use of Komet and Tinkar data.</para>
                </section>
                <section>
                    <title>Testing</title>
                    <para>As it stands, IKM supports multiple platforms – Windows, Mac, and web –
                        and we are continuing to investigate future platform support such as iPad,
                        mobile and embedded device support. Due to the nature of the application and
                        the multi-platform support, it is increasingly imperative that we conduct
                        comprehensive testing. Over the past year, as we’ve introduced additional
                        features, collaborators, and multi-platform support, this has proven to be a
                        significant challenge.</para>
                    <para>Our team has encountered issues with overwritten changes and unstable
                        environments, making the existing testing process difficult. These
                        challenges have resulted in delays, rework, and a higher likelihood of bugs
                        and issues reaching production. In a collaborative development environment,
                        multiple developers work on different features or bug fixes simultaneously.
                        When these developers merge their changes into the main codebase, there's a
                        risk of overwriting previously tested and approved functionality. Multiple
                        merges occurring simultaneously can lead to conflicts and overwrites,
                        especially when there is a lack of communication and coordination among
                        developers. Insufficient testing after each merge can also cause issues to
                        go unnoticed until later, resulting in delays and rework. To mitigate this
                        issue, teams can implement regular communication and coordination among
                        developers, as well as code reviews and approvals to ensure that changes are
                        thoroughly reviewed and unit tested before being merged into the main
                        codebase.</para>
                    <para>Trunk-based development is a methodology where all changes are merged
                        directly into the main codebase (trunk). While this approach can promote
                        collaboration and speed up development, it can also lead to an unstable main
                        environment. This instability can occur when untested changes are merged
                        directly into the trunk, or when there is a lack of a stabilization period,
                        preventing the main environment from settling and stabilizing. Insufficient
                        monitoring and feedback mechanisms can also allow issues to go unnoticed
                        until they cause significant problems. </para>
                    <para>To ensure the quality and stability of the codebase, the team relies on
                        testers to perform comprehensive testing on all major merge requests before
                        they are merged into the main codebase. This approach aims to catch bugs and
                        issues early on, preventing them from causing problems downstream. However,
                        this approach is resulting in testers conducting high-level smoke testing,
                        which is expanding the testing scope beyond the available testing resources.
                        Smoke testing focuses on verifying that the most critical features and
                        functionality are working as expected, but it is not a substitute for
                        comprehensive testing. By relying solely on smoke testing, testers may miss
                        important issues that could cause problems later.</para>
                    <para>Additionally, the lack of adequate testing resources can result in delayed
                        releases, as testers struggle to keep up with the demand for comprehensive
                        testing. To address this challenge, it is essential to strike a balance
                        between comprehensive testing and the available testing resources. This
                        might involve prioritizing testing efforts on the most critical features and
                        functionality, implementing automated testing to free up testers for more
                        complex and high-value testing. If building an automation test suite is
                        going to take time, it may make sense to add more manual testers in the
                        interim.</para>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Solution Adoption</title>
            <para>Since its inception in 2015, FDA SHIELD has connected over 70 entities from a
                variety of fields including federal, academia, and industry to support efforts
                improving health care data and technology. [6] FDA SHIELD has developed a robust
                community of experts and stakeholders that continues to further the advancement of
                data quality and integration between terminologies. The work is encapsulated by the
                overarching movement towards IKM and the ability for healthcare data to be impactful
                and actionable.</para>
            <para>Uptake, however, is ultimately dependent on buy-in from the leaders, clinicians,
                laboratorians, product developers, electronic healthcare companies, and many other
                stakeholders. The following (Figure 4) graphic serves as the base communication
                curve for FDA SHIELD on how to capture, educate, and ultimately build loyalty with
                potential users. </para>
            <para><figure xml:id="FDASHIELDCommunicationsCurve">
                    <title>FDA SHIELD Communications Curve</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="../images/FDA%20SHIELD%20Communications%20Curve.svg"
                                scale="50" align="center"/> 
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            </para>
            <para>To date, the IKM Solution Adoption team has worked to identify key stakeholders
                and tailor content to enhance their understanding of both the FDA SHIELD Program and
                the goals of IKM. In the phase of increasing awareness, the team has developed and
                disseminated informational presentations and trainings both internally to FDA
                leadership and centers and externally to federal and industry partners. Through
                these efforts, including additional presentations and demos of Komet at industry
                conferences (e.g., SNOMED International Expo, American Medical Informatics
                Association) and the HL7 FHIR May and September Connectathons, the team has been
                able to identify champions for the IKM movement across the ecosystem. As awareness
                has grown and the team looks to drive engagement, the team has tracked engagements
                across 82 organizations and 175+ individuals, overseeing a 32% increase in external
                engagement from 2023 to 2024. Additionally, the team maintains stakeholder
                relationships through personalized communications with individual stakeholders at
                organizations of significance (e.g., Food and Drug Administration, Assistant
                Secretary for Technology Policy, Graphite Health, Royal College of Pathologists of
                Australasia). [7] </para>
            <para>Through these engagements, the team has identified the following key findings to
                develop successful communications that will drive their efforts up the
                communications curve trajectory. In the future, the team seeks to move towards the
                acceptance and commitment stages of the communication curve to increase adoption of
                IKM. </para>
            <section>
                <title><anchor xml:id="Toc185598265"/>Curating Technical Communications</title>
                <para>FDA SHIELD has recognized a need in IKM communications to provide adequate
                    technical guidance for stakeholders interested in collaboration and/or
                    integration. Therefore, the development of proper processes and documentation of
                    work has been critical to the IKM strategic communications efforts and will
                    continue to be strengthened as we move towards driving engagement. </para>
                <para>To meet this need, the IKM Solution Adoption team has delivered communication
                    materials including briefing decks, reports, and use cases highlighting IKM
                    tools’ capabilities and benefits, tailored to relevant parties’ specific needs
                    both internal and external to FDA. This includes sharing key findings from real
                    world studies that showcase the continual loss of granularity could ultimately
                    result in patient harm. Findings such as these allow the Solution Adoption team
                    to communicate the need for an Integrated Knowledge solution. The team detailed
                    the various capabilities of the Komet shared knowledge base and laid out patient
                    stories wherein Komet could improve patient outcomes.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title><anchor xml:id="Toc185598266"/>Defining Integrated Knowledge
                    Management</title>
                <para>Integrated Knowledge Management is an evolving and novel movement in the
                    healthcare information technology field. Therefore, communicating to all
                    potential stakeholders effectively on its mission to increase cohesion in health
                    data standards and what problems that it may solve is paramount to advancing the
                    movement. Based on feedback from stakeholder engagement sessions, FDA SHIELD has
                    been iteratively refining strategic communications initiatives to develop
                    concise and aimed messaging to key stakeholders.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title><anchor xml:id="Toc185598267"/>Ensuring End User Adoption</title>
                <para>A more nuanced challenge that the IKM movement faces as technologies and
                    integration methods develop into end-user capabilities is the adoption and
                    implementation of these tools by the end-users themselves, whether they are
                    clinicians, healthcare organizations, laboratories, or other healthcare-related
                    entities. Many of these end-users may not have the technical background or
                    insight into the issues that IKM addresses and aims to solve and therefore may
                    not fully be invested in adopting such a solution into their operations. </para>
                <para>As future efforts in the Integrated Knowledge Management space are advanced,
                    there will be an increased need for intentional strategies centered around
                    communications to the various stakeholders that IKM impacts to ensure engagement
                    and ultimate adoption. Technical professionals in the data standards field will
                    need to have transparent and detailed information on the methodologies used in
                    previous efforts in order to continuously improve upon the collaborative
                    process. Further, end-user specific communication plans will be developed that
                    articulate both the problems that IKM attempts to solve along with a clear
                    explanation about the tools’ capabilities. </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Knowledge Representation</title>
            <para>The advantages of utilizing a generalized, self-describing data structure are
                well-documented. This data structure comprises not just the database but also
                includes metadata that outlines and explains both the data and the connections
                between tables [9]. Also, descriptions of data structures and constraints are
                included, allowing storage of a description of its own structure within the
                database. While this self-describing approach is reference terminology-agnostic,
                making it capable of accommodating various data sources, challenges for determining
                the importance of terminology-specific data components are introduced [10].</para>
            <para>Representing data properties such as concepts, patterns, or semantics becomes a
                complex task, especially when importing data from multiple terminology standards. As
                clinical reference terminologies, SNOMED CT® and LOINC® employ different data
                structures to represent their respective content. These data structures do not
                translate easily between terminologies. SNOMED CT® utilizes Concepts, Descriptions,
                and Relationships, organized hierarchically to convey clinical meanings to its
                terms. LOINC® codes are represented by five or six main parts. And hierarchical
                relationship between LOINC® terms is manually applied outside of the LOINC® SNOMED
                Collaboration. The components from each of these terminologies may function as
                crucial data structure components for axioms and related data properties within the
                database. [8]</para>
            <para>Once imported into a self-describing data structure, determining equivalence with
                another terminology standard or which parts of the data components are important may
                create unanticipated challenges [9]. Unlike more specific terminology models, Tinkar
                lacks pre-defined references to identify crucial components or properties within
                incoming data, necessitating a comprehensive understanding of the dataset. This
                challenge extends to determining the importance or equivalence of specific data
                components, prompting the creation of new properties and concepts before the data
                can be seamlessly imported into Tinkar. While the generic nature of Tinkar provides
                valuable flexibility for accommodating diverse data standards, it underscores the
                need for a proactive and nuanced approach to customization. This adaptability allows
                Tinkar to serve as a versatile platform capable of handling a variety of data
                sources, but it also highlights the importance of thoughtful customization to ensure
                effective integration. [5]</para>
            <para>SNOMED CT® and LOINC® release their data by providing the most recent version, or
                by selecting a specific version to view/use. Tinkar provides STAMP (Status, Time,
                Author, Module, Path) Coordinates which allows the full history of the data to see
                how it could have changed over time. As relationships may evolve and change over
                time users can go back and review potential similar cases from the past for
                consistency. SNOMED CT® and LOINC® also vary in their release schedule. While they
                are independent, they often provide supplemental information which indicates
                equivalence between some SNOMED CT® Concepts and LOINC® Codes or Parts. Due to the
                staggered releases any change from one may impact the other if they were previously
                determined to be equivalent. Tinkar provides a way to view the concept in a context
                of Integrated Knowledge Management and can report any potential impacts a change
                might have.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <para>This deliverable serves as an updated report to document the challenges our team has
            faced over the past two years of development of the IKM solution and environment. Our
            summary of findings identify functional and non-functional issues our team experienced
            with IKM have identified critical areas that will require additional and continued
            efforts to improve the implementation, functionality, and adoption of IKM
            solutions.</para>
        <para>While this deliverable will inform the direction and focus areas for our future work,
            this report can also function as a resource and reference implementation for SNOMED CT®,
            LOINC®, and other stakeholders working to develop IKM solutions. As our team works to
            develop an open-source environment for IKM, we look forward to and encourage
            collaboration with other stakeholders to gain a deeper understanding of the challenges
            they faced, best practices, and IKM as a whole.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Citations</title>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>IKM Epic Board - Agile board - Jira [Internet]. [cited 2024 Jan 8].
                        Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://ikmdev.atlassian.net/jira/software/c/projects/IPB/boards/40"
                            >https://ikmdev.atlassian.net/jira/software/c/projects/IPB/boards/40</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A library for manipulating with proofs that use inference rules.
                        [Internet]. GitHub. [cited 2023 September 15]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://github.com/liveontologies/puliz"
                            >https://github.com/liveontologies/puliz</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Bug and Issue Reporting Process Framework. [Deloitte Deliverable].
                        December 20, 2023 [Cited 2024 Jan 9] Available Internally at Deloitte
                        Consulting LLP. DeloitteBAA_Task_2.3.4_Bugs and Issue Reporting Process
                        Framework.pdf</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The Integrated Knowledge Management Application | Komet [Internet]. [cited
                        2024 Jan 19]. Available from: https://www.ikm.dev/application</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>HL7 International [Internet]. 2021. HL7 Logical Model: Standardized
                        Terminology Knowledgebase, Release 1. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.hl7.org/documentcenter/private/standards/HL7_LM_TERM_KB_R1_INFORM_2021AUG_FINAL.pdf"
                            >https://www.hl7.org/documentcenter/private/standards/HL7_LM_TERM_KB_R1_INFORM_2021AUG_FINAL.pdf</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Systemic Harmonization and Interoperability Enhancement for Laboratory
                        Data (SHIELD) | FDA [Internet]. [cited 2024 Jan 9]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/diagnostic-data-program/systemic-harmonization-and-interoperability-enhancement-laboratory-data-shield"
                            >https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/diagnostic-data-program/systemic-harmonization-and-interoperability-enhancement-laboratory-data-shield</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>SHIELD - Standardization of Lab Data to Enhance Patient-Centered Outcomes
                        Research and Value-Based Care | ASPE [Internet]. [cited 2024 Jan 9].
                        Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://aspe.hhs.gov/shield-standardization-lab-data-enhance-patient-centered-outcomes-research-value-based-care"
                            >https://aspe.hhs.gov/shield-standardization-lab-data-enhance-patient-centered-outcomes-research-value-based-care</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>LOINC — The freely available standard for identifying health measurements,
                        observations, and documents. [Internet]. Loinc.org. 2019. Available from: 
                        <link xlink:href="https://loinc.org/">https://loinc.org/</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>1.3: Chapter 3 Characteristics and Benefits of a Database - Engineering
                        LibreTexts [Internet]. [cited 2024 Jan 9]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://eng.libretexts.org/Bookshelves/Computer_Science/Databases_and_Data_Structures/Database_Design_(Watt)/01%3A_Chapters/1.03%3A_Chapter_3_Characteristics_and_Benefits_of_a_Database"
                        /></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Abad-Navarro F, Martínez-Costa C. A knowledge graph-based data
                        harmonization framework for secondary data reuse. Computer Methods and
                        Programs in Biomedicine [Internet]. 2024 Jan 1 [cited 2024 Jan
                        9];243:107918. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0169260723005849"
                            >https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0169260723005849</link></para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
