<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> 
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?> 
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?> 
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1"> 
    <title>Updated Knowledge Management Proof-of-Concept Roadmap</title> 
    <section> 
        
        <title>Purpose</title> 
        <para>Integrated Knowledge Management (IKM) is an evolving approach to data management with
            the primary goal of improving patient care by maintaining the integrity, meaning, and
            quality of data as it is shared within and between healthcare systems. Our work aims to
            drive IKM practices forward to improve the quality and interoperability of healthcare
            data and, ultimately, provide the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) with
            up-to-date real-world data (RWD) that can be used to make informed policy, public
            health, and other decisions. Over the past year, our team has been developing an IKM
            reference implementation that would serve as one of the tools that support IKM practices
            and the lossless transfer of data. As we continue our efforts, our team will support the
            development of other IKM tools that will facilitate IKM adoption, implementation, and
            optimization, such as General Authoring, Application Program Interfaces (API), and data
            quality validation harnesses. The purpose of this document is to highlight recent
            efforts and outline key objectives and events through September 2025 that will progress
            IKM forward. </para> 
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Background</title>
        <para>One of the FDA Systemic Harmonization and Interoperability Enhancement for Laboratory
            Data (SHIELD)’s team’s primary focuses over the past two years has been the development
            of an IKM reference implementation. While IKM is not a novel concept itself, a tool that
            facilitates and supports the integration, management, editing, and authoring of multiple
            clinical terminology standards is relatively new. Our efforts have been comprehensive,
            ranging from user interface/user experience (UI/UX) to back-end development to technical
            communications and more. This IKM prototype leverages Terminology Knowledge Architecture
            (Tinkar), a self-describing data structure and logical model that provides a
            standardized and repeatable way of representing various clinical terminology standards.
            Tinkar supports the identification of equivalent concepts and aims to address the
            differences in the management and structure of disparate terminology standards, local
            concepts, and code lists/value sets by normalizing the representation of concepts,
            properties, and associated information within and between terminology standards. A
            current version of the IKM reference implementation showcased the latest IKM
            capabilities during the October 2023 Systematized Nomenclature of Medicine Clinical
            Terms (SNOMED CT®) conference. </para>
        <para>In early 2024, the SHIELD community released the initial draft of the Laboratory
            Interoperability Data Repository (LIDR) data design. Once populated, LIDR will provide
            an authoritative source of which SNOMED CT® and Logical Observation Identifiers Names
            and Codes (LOINC®) codes are assigned to tests performed on various laboratory devices.
            An authoring environment is needed for the SHIELD community where LIDR records can be
            authored and reliably integrate knowledge from disparate sources, such as SNOMED CT® and
            LOINC®, in real-time to produce high-quality, interoperable, and accurate data. </para>
        <para>As our team refines the IKM reference implementation and drives IKM forwards, we will
            continue to collaborate with a variety of stakeholders and communities, particularly the
            Health Level Seven (HL7) community and Diagnostic Data Program (DxD). </para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">HL7</emphasis>: HL7 has developed a robust suite of
                    technical standards that define mechanisms for the management and exchange of
                    electronic health data across healthcare systems. As part of its role as a
                    standards development organization, HL7 hosts several Connect-a-thons throughout
                    the year that offer stakeholders the opportunity to test their work with
                    real-world scenarios and subject matter experts (SMEs), improving both their
                    implementations and the HL7 standards they use in the process. One HL7 standard
                    is Fast Healthcare Interoperability Resources (FHIR), which is a flexible and
                    adaptable set of rules and specifications for the exchange of health information
                    that builds upon previous HL7 data format standards. FHIR is a leading data
                    exchange format in the healthcare ecosystem and will serve as a key format for
                    testing and validation exercises. [1-2] </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">(DxD)</emphasis>: The DxD program aims to improve the
                    collection, usability, and portability of data collected in laboratories and
                    from at-home tests and other, non-laboratory data collection instances. The
                    program defines these focus areas as the Systemic Harmonization and
                    Interoperability Enhancement for Laboratory Data (SHIELD) and Digital
                    Diagnostics: Over the Counter (OTC) and Point-of-Care (POC). Collaboration with
                    this group is essential and will support IKM and Tinkar’s integration with FDA’s
                    RWD repository to support informed and timely decision making. [3] </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Proof of Concept Roadmap</title>
        <para>The following roadmap, depicted in Figure 1, details the key objectives and events
            from February 2024 through September 2025. While our team is planning and working
            towards these milestones, they are subject to change based on client priorities and
            requests. </para><figure xml:id="Figure1KnowledgeManagementProofofConceptRoadmap"> 
            <title>Knowledge Management Proof of Concept Roadmap</title> 
            <mediaobject> 
                <imageobject> 
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/1.4.3.1.svg" 
                        scale="25" align="center"/> 
                </imageobject> 
            </mediaobject> 
        </figure>   
        <para><emphasis role="bold">March 2024</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para>Throughout March 2024, our team worked to author an HL7 standard, based on Tinkar and
            HL7’s Fast Healthcare Interoperability Resources (FHIR), that will enable data agility
            in the standardized distribution of terminology change sets, such as those needing rapid
            distribution during a pandemic response context. At the same time, we developed a modern
            IKM authoring environment, known as Komet. We successfully transformed both the SNOMED
            CT® and SNOMED CT®-LOINC® Collaborative Agreement terminology data into the Tinkar
            format to be viewable, editable, and extensible within Komet. The team also focused on
            LIDR-to-Tinkar transformations and custom LIDR user interfaces, so that the SHIELD
            community can benefit from the power of integrated knowledge management as it authors
            and maintains LIDR data within Komet. </para>
        <para>By the end of March 2024, our team drafted an HL7 FHIR standard for the computable
            exchange of terminology change sets related to in vitro diagnostic (IVD) data encoding
            guidelines, specifically SNOMED CT® and LOINC®. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">May 2024</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para>Once initial LIDR authoring and terminology change set capabilities were ready within
            Komet, we coordinated with laboratory and terminology experts to test and validate our
            work at the May 18th – 19thHL7 Connect-a-thon in Dallas, Texas. Testing validated our
            ability to author new or edit existing SNOMED CT®, LOINC®, and LIDR concepts that could
            then be exchanged in FHIR or native Google Protocol Buffers formats. These tests
            demonstrated users’ ability to author provisional codes for new or evolving medical
            conditions, tests, diagnoses, and more using Komet and Tinkar and successfully exchange
            them with other Connect-a-thon participants. Rather than waiting months for disparate
            terminology standards to issue official codes, these provisional Tinkar codes can serve
            as placeholders so that critical health data and information can be shared across health
            systems. </para>
        <para>Secondly, in close coordination with SafeHealth Systems, we demonstrated how the
            exchange of clinical terminology change sets can be used to inform immediate changes
            within electronic forms so that Real World Data (RWD) can be captured more accurately as
            clinical knowledge advances. For example, if a new test kit becomes available on the
            market, we can leverage IKM principles and open-source tools to quickly author and
            publish a LIDR change set with the new test kit information and encoding guidelines.
            Then a data capture application, like a mobile application used to capture COVID-19 test
            results at rapid testing sites, could utilize the latest LIDR records to dynamically
            update and show the new test kit and begin to capture RWD results associated with it,
            consistently encoding them in alignment with the LIDR guidance. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">September 2024</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para>Following the successes of the May 2024 Connect-a-thon, we continued to iterate on
            integrated solutions with the SafeHealth team to demonstrate additional advanced
            analytic capabilities at the September 2024 Connect-a-thon. We had two demonstration
            goals: </para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Showcase the power of IKM to make knowledge changes that inform advanced
                    analytics </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Exchange FHIR-based terminology change sets with another system </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>In the first demonstration, we showed how the Analytic Data Repository (ADR), built by
            SafeHealth Systems, could consume IKM change sets that inform the results of the
            constructed queries and run against staged RWD stored in the ADR. The real-world
            scenario we used for this demonstration was based on the fact that, early in the
            development of IVD COVID-19 Test Kits, test kit manufacturers included a result of
            “presumptive positive” which was interpreted to be equivalent to positive or detected.
            For this scenario, we proposed that a researcher is interested in understanding the
            implications of the inclusion or exclusion of the presumptive positive result in the
            number of positive COVID-19 results. First, a query was built in the Query Builder and
            executed with the knowledge that “presumptive positive” was included in the definition
            of a positive COVID-19 test result. We then authored a change to that knowledge to
            remove “presumptive positive” from that definition, exported the knowledge, and
            exchanged the change set with the ADR system. Subsequently, the original query was
            re-run to show a change in the number of positive COVID-19 results returned after that
            knowledge was updated. </para>
        <para>In the second demonstration, we showed how rapidly new knowledge could be defined and
            distributed through IKM. For this scenario, we proposed that there was an emerging
            outbreak of a newly identified “Cyclops Rash”, as shown in Figure 2 below. We defined
            the new concept with all relevant attributes and description logic in Komet, exported it
            in FHIR format and uploaded it to our FHIR server. Clinical Architecture was then able
            to retrieve the change set, consume it, and show the new concept in their Symedical
            system, as shown in Figure 3. </para>
        <figure xml:id="Figure2-TableofingesteddatashowingtheCyclopsRashconceptbeingsuccesfullyingestedintoSymedical"> 
            <title>Table of ingested data, showing the "Cyclops Rash" concept being succesfully
                ingested into Symedical</title> 
            <mediaobject> 
                <imageobject> 
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/1.4.3.2.svg" 
                        scale="25" align="center"/> 
                </imageobject> 
            </mediaobject> 
        </figure>
        <figure xml:id="Figure3"> 
            <title> Visualization of Relationship between new concept and its parent concepts
                ('Eruption of skin of face' and 'Papular eruption') in Sydmedical</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject> 
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/1.4.3.3.svg" 
                        scale="25" align="center"/> 
                </imageobject> 
            </mediaobject> 
        </figure>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">January 2025</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para>From October 2024 through January 2025, the team has focused on developing General
            Authoring capabilities within Komet. General Authoring allows for the standardized
            representation of knowledge from disparate sources, such as SNOMED CT® and LOINC®. We
            have made substantial strides towards functionalities supporting the development and
            editing of patterns and general semantic editing. In January 2025, the team focused on
            General Semantic Editing capabilities for Strings, Integers, Boolean Logic, Floats,
            Components, Component sets, Component Lists, and Images. The team also confirmed that
            users can edit these data types and refresh and save changes to the data. </para>
        <para>As we continue to iterate and refine General Authoring, our team will explore
            opportunities for piloting this capability with a variety of stakeholders through
            outreach and developer previews. We met with representatives from SNOMED CT®, LOINC®,
            the Department of Veteran Affairs (VA), the National Institute of Health (NIH), and
            more. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">May 2025</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para>Ensuring General Authoring is implemented in a comprehensive and accurate way will
            require an iterative approach. From January 2025 through May 2025, the team will
            continue to work on General Authoring, using varied use cases as opportunities for
            process improvement and issue resolution. By the end of May 2025, the team aims to
            demonstrate the ability to comprehensively author health data from a variety of
            terminology standards in Komet using concepts, patterns, and semantics to properly
            capture all pertinent information. </para>
        <para>Another focus for our team in May 2025 will be further exploring the implementation of
            a plug-in architecture. Plug-ins are a type of software that support enhancements and
            customizations or improve the functionality of existing software without having to
            recode or rebuild the program. Plug-ins will help support the continued evolution of the
            IKM environment as data from new knowledge sources are added to Komet. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">September 2025</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para>September 2025 will culminate in an extensive effort to demonstrate and validate our
            ability to comprehensively and accurately author Laboratory in vitro diagnostic (LIVD)
            and/or LIDR data through general authoring capabilities. The LIDR data model is still in
            development by the SHIELD Collaborative Community and may not be available in time to
            incorporate into our demonstration by September. However, LIVD provides a mature data
            model and is planned to have the LIVD-on-FHIR specification released in March-April of
            2025. </para>
        <para>Our team will work with critical stakeholders and industry partners to run end-to-end
            validation exercises and data quality checks on the General Authoring capabilities to
            ensure LIVD, LIDR, and other knowledge can be authored, stored, and exported in a way
            that supports improved data quality and interoperability through transmission. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Key Events</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para>Our team is focusing on the September 13th - 14th 2025 Pittsburgh HL7 Connect-a-thon
            as the next key event. While this is our primary focus, events may arise that our team
            will look to participate in to gain industry and Subject Matter Expert (SME) feedback.
            This Connect-a-thons could be used to determine if our data encoding and capturing
            guidelines are specific enough to produce functional, high-quality, and interoperable
            data. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <para>Our primary goal is to demonstrate that IKM can measurably improve laboratory data
            quality and interoperability to ultimately feed into RWD so that FDA can make informed,
            real-time regulatory decisions. While this document outlines a variety of milestone
            targets, the exact timing of certain events leading up to the end-to-end validation
            study in September 2025 may change depending on client priorities, challenges, and
            results. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Beyond September 2025</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para>As the team looks beyond September 2025 and once we have developed the ability to
            successfully author and manage LIVD and/or LIDR through General Authoring capabilities,
            next steps would include furthering how these encoding guidelines can be distributed and
            used to improve the quality of RWD in collaboration with data experts and DxD
            stakeholders. One example of how this could be accomplished is through building a data
            quality validation harness that could be used to assess and validate IVD data captured
            as part of the FDA RWD sandbox and ensure that it meets the established LIVD or LIDR
            encoding guidelines.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>References</title>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Health Level Seven international [Internet]. [cited 2024 Feb 21].
                        Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.hl7.org/about/index.cfm?ref=nav"><emphasis
                                role="underline"
                                >https://www.hl7.org/about/index.cfm?ref=nav</emphasis></link>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Welcome to the HL7 FHIR Foundation [Internet]. [cited 2024 Mar 7].
                        Available from: <link xlink:href="https://fhir.org/"><emphasis
                                role="underline">https://fhir.org/</emphasis></link>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Diagnostic Data Program [Internet]. FDA; [cited 2024 Feb 21]. Available
                        from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/digital-health-center-excellence/diagnostic-data-program"
                                ><emphasis role="underline"
                                >https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/digital-health-center-excellence/diagnostic-data-program</emphasis></link>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
    </section> 
    
</chapter> 
