<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>GSRS/UNII Demonstration Project Progress Report
        (Months 13-24)</title>
    <section>
        <title>Purpose</title>
        <para>There is an increasing need for high-quality and accurate data as healthcare
            organizations becoming more reliant on electronic health records (EHRs), laboratory
            information systems (LISs), and other electronic information systems. A primary tool for
            many organizations, terminology standards work to improve the quality and accuracy of
            data. Terminology standards aim to ensure information is captured and represented in a
            repeatable and standardized format so that other organizations have a common
            understanding of the data. While terminology standards are a useful tool, extensive
            knowledge management (KM) is needed to identify, manage, and share the standardized data
            that these systems and standards capture. As data flows within and between healthcare
            systems, the use of different terminology standards, KM processes, and systems
            themselves can pose a threat to the integrity of data. A recent study found that only
            22-68% of data integrity is maintained in a single trip, posing challenges around
            interpretation, and resulting accuracy around patient care [1].</para>
        <para>Integrated Knowledge Management (IKM) is an approach to data management that aims to
            maintain the meaning, integrity, and quality of data as it travels within and between
            healthcare systems. IKM is an evolving approach to manage disparate terminology
            standards using a common, centralized, and repeatable representation of data. The use of
            a common model supports the interoperability of data between disparate terminology
            standards, well documented version control even when different terminology standards
            employ their own versioning practices, and the incorporation of new or emerging
            terminology standards. IKM will use an iterative approach to build upon previous work on
            Resource Description Frameworks (RDFs) and property graphs with novel ideas and
            concepts. There is no reference or best practice guide for how an IKM solution can or
            should operate and will therefore require extensive research, prototyping, and
            development.</para>
        <para>The Food and Drug Administration (FDA) created a Global Substance Registration System
            (GSRS) to facilitate the efficient and accurate information exchange on substances
            within regulated products. The creation of the GSRS knowledge base allowed for
            standardized, scientific descriptions of substances across regulatory lines, such as
            within and between countries. The collection and dependencies of knowledge within GSRS
            presents a direct use case in which IKM and its capabilities can improve GSRS.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Aims</title>
        <para>The aims of this document serve as a collection of landscape analyses of the GSRS
            system and its parts within the domains of Integrated Knowledge Management: Knowledge
            Management, and Knowledge Representation.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Global Substance Registration System (GSRS)/Unique Ingredient Identifier (UNII) Demonstrations</title>
        <section>
            <title>Knowledge Management: GSRS/UNII Demonstration Project Progress Report [Task
                1.3.2]</title>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Progress Report Week 26</emphasis></para>
            <section>
                <title>Temporal Change Assessment of GSRS</title>
                <para>GSRS is a comprehensive system designed to manage and track information about
                    substances, particularly in the context of regulatory compliance and safety. It
                    ensures that updates and modifications to its data are accurately managed and
                    recorded through several key mechanisms.</para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Version Control</emphasis></para>
                <para>GSRS employs a simple version control system to keep track of changes to its
                    data. With the use of its unique identifier, any modifications to the record
                    result in the creation of a new version. This allows users to track the history
                    of changes made to a substance, compare different versions of a substance record
                    and revert to previous versions, if necessary [2].</para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Audit Trails</emphasis></para>
                <para>An audit trail is maintained for each substance record, documenting every
                    change made to the data. This includes the nature of the change (e.g., addition,
                    deletion, modification), the date and time of the change, the user or system
                    that made the change, and the specific fields that were altered. Audit trails
                    ensure transparency and accountability, making it possible to review the history
                    of a substance and understand the context of each change [3].</para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Data Validation and Quality Control</emphasis></para>
                <para>GSRS incorporates data validation and quality control processes to ensure that
                    updates are accurate and consistent. These processes include automated
                    validation checks that verify the integrity and correctness of the data before
                    it is saved, and manual review and approval workflows where changes must be
                    reviewed and approved by authorized personnel before they are finalized
                    [4].</para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Role-Based Access Control</emphasis></para>
                <para>GSRS uses role-based access control (RBAC) to manage who can view and modify
                    substance data. Different roles (e.g., data entry, reviewer, administrator) have
                    different levels of access and permissions. This helps prevent unauthorized
                    changes and ensures that only qualified personnel can make updates [5].</para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Data Archiving</emphasis></para>
                <para>Older versions of substance records and audit logs are archived to ensure that
                    the system remains efficient and performant. Archived data can be retrieved if
                    needed, providing a complete historical record without cluttering the active
                    database [6].</para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Integration with External Systems</emphasis></para>
                <para>GSRS can integrate with other regulatory and data management systems with the
                    use of its Application Programming Interface (API), ensuring that updates made
                    in GSRS are propagated to other systems as needed [7]. This integration helps
                    maintain consistency across different platforms and reduces the risk of
                    discrepancies.</para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Reporting and Analytics</emphasis></para>
                <para>GSRS provides reporting and analytics capabilities via its API that allow
                    users to generate reports on changes made to substance data [7]. These reports
                    can be used for regulatory submissions, internal audits, and other purposes.
                    Analytics tools can also help identify trends and patterns in the data,
                    supporting better decision-making.</para>
                <para>IKM can significantly enhance GSRS by providing a structured framework for
                    capturing, storing, and managing data changes. By creating a centralized
                    repository, IKM ensures that all modifications to substance records are
                    consistently documented, including metadata, such as the date, time, user, and
                    rationale for each change. This facilitates robust version control, allowing
                    users to track, compare, and revert to different versions of records as needed.
                    Additionally, IKM enhances audit trails by providing detailed records of all
                    actions taken on substance data, supporting regulatory compliance, and internal
                    audits. Improved data validation and quality control processes, along with
                    enhanced reporting and analytics capabilities, enable GSRS to maintain data
                    integrity and gain insights into data change patterns. Overall, IKM promotes
                    transparency, accountability, and collaboration among stakeholders, ensuring
                    that data changes are accurately tracked and managed over time.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>GSRS Release Process</title>
                <para>The FDA's Global Substance Registration System (GSRS) releases new versions of
                    data by updating its public database with new substance information, typically
                    through a scheduled update process, and makes the updated data accessible via
                    its online platform, allowing users to search and download the latest
                    information using unique ingredient identifiers (UNIIs) as the primary access
                    point. New versions are often accompanied by version numbers and release dates
                    to indicate changes made to the dataset [8].</para>
                <para>The release process for new data versions in the Global Substance Registration
                    System (GSRS) is a meticulously structured procedure designed to ensure the
                    integrity, accuracy, and compliance of substance information. This process
                    begins with the identification and documentation of necessary updates or
                    modifications to existing substance records. These changes can stem from new
                    regulatory requirements, scientific discoveries, or corrections to previously
                    entered data. Once the need for an update is identified, the proposed changes
                    undergo an initial review by subject matter experts who assess the validity and
                    implications of the modifications.</para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Staging and Data Validation</emphasis></para>
                <para>Following the initial review, the changes are entered into a staging
                    environment within the GSRS, where they are subjected to automated validation
                    checks. These checks verify the integrity and correctness of the data, ensuring
                    that it adheres to predefined standards and formats. If the data passes these
                    automated checks, it moves on to a manual review process. During this phase,
                    authorized personnel, typically comprising senior data managers or regulatory
                    experts, meticulously examine the changes. They ensure that the updates are not
                    only accurate but also compliant with relevant regulatory guidelines and
                    standards [7].</para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Notifications to Stakeholders</emphasis></para>
                <para>GSRS utilizes its public website as the primary communication platform to
                    inform users about new updates and developments. The website is regularly
                    updated with the latest information, including new substance registrations,
                    regulatory changes, and enhancements to the system. Users can access detailed
                    announcements, release notes, and documentation that provide insights into the
                    updates. Additionally, the GSRS website may feature newsletters, alerts, and
                    other resources to ensure that users are well-informed and can seamlessly
                    integrate the latest changes into their workflows. This proactive approach helps
                    maintain transparency and keeps stakeholders engaged with the ongoing
                    improvements in the system [9].</para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Deployment and Documentation</emphasis></para>
                <para>The final step in the release process involves the actual deployment of the
                    new data version into the live GSRS environment. This deployment is carefully
                    monitored to ensure it proceeds smoothly and that the system remains functional
                    and efficient. Post-release, the system maintains an audit trail documenting
                    every change made to the data, including the nature of the change, the date and
                    time, the user or system that made the change, and the specific fields that were
                    altered. This audit trail ensures transparency and accountability, making it
                    possible to review the history of a substance and understand the context of each
                    change [10].</para>
                <para>An opportunity for GSRS seems to be enhancing its version control system,
                    which currently relies on the use of its unique identifier system. IKM can help
                    GSRS with versioning and the release of new data versions by providing a
                    centralized platform for managing and tracking changes. IKM ensures that all
                    updates and modifications are documented and version-controlled, allowing for
                    clear visibility of changes over time. It facilitates the creation and
                    maintenance of release notes and documentation for each new data version,
                    ensuring that all stakeholders are informed of updates. Additionally, IKM
                    supports the coordination and communication among team members, streamlining the
                    release process and ensuring that new data versions are deployed efficiently and
                    accurately.</para>
                <para>To elaborate more on IKM’s versioning capabilities, it facilitates the
                    systematic tracking of data changes, ensuring that every modification is
                    documented with detailed metadata, including timestamps, user information, and
                    change descriptions. This meticulous version control allows for precise auditing
                    and rollback capabilities, ensuring data integrity and consistency. By
                    implementing IKM, GSRS can maintain a comprehensive history of all data entries
                    and updates, which is crucial for regulatory compliance and accurate substance
                    registration. Furthermore, IKM supports collaboration among multiple users by
                    preventing data conflicts and ensuring that the most current and accurate
                    information is always available. This leads to enhanced data reliability,
                    streamlined workflows, and improved decision-making processes within the GSRS
                    framework.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Conclusion</title>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Summary of Findings</emphasis></para>
                <para>The GSRS system is a robust and comprehensive platform for substance
                    registration and management. Its open-source nature, combined with community
                    contributions and adherence to international standards, makes it a valuable tool
                    for the pharmaceutical and chemical industries. The system's functionalities,
                    user-friendly interface, and compliance support are key strengths that enhance
                    its utility and effectiveness.</para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Recommendations</emphasis></para>
                <para>To further improve the GSRS system, the following recommendations are
                    proposed:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Enhance User Training</emphasis>: Provide
                            additional training resources and support to help users maximize the
                            system's capabilities.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Increase Community Engagement</emphasis>:
                            Encourage greater participation from the community to drive innovation
                            and continuous improvement.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Strengthen Data Security</emphasis>: Implement
                            advanced security measures to protect sensitive substance data and
                            ensure compliance with data protection regulations.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Integrate Advanced Analytics</emphasis>:
                            Incorporate advanced analytics tools to provide deeper insights into
                            substance data and support decision-making processes.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Expand Data Model</emphasis>: Conduct additional
                            analysis to understand how database can be expanded by integrating into
                            other knowledge standards.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Utilize Validation Tools</emphasis>: Integrate
                            automated validation tools where possible to assist with routine checks,
                            reducing the burden on manual processes and minimizing human
                            error.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Implement More Robust Version
                                Tracking</emphasis>: Integrate an IKM system that helps track and
                            log every change made to substance data, including detailed metadata
                            such as user information, timestamps, and change descriptions to enhance
                            data integrity, facilitate auditing, and ensure accurate version
                            control.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>By implementing these recommendations, GSRS can continue to evolve and meet
                    the growing needs of the pharmaceutical and chemical industries, ensuring
                    accurate and reliable substance registration and management.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Knowledge Representation: GSRS/UNII Demonstration Project Progress Report [Task
                3.3.1]</title>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Progress Report Week 26</emphasis></para>
            <section>
                <title>Introduction</title>
                <para>Following the completion of the initial investigation and the designation of
                    data elements that can be represented by existing Tinkar components, we
                    continued with our representation of GSRS by establishing the additional data
                    used, authoring this starter data in Komet, and creating transformation logic to
                    be used to generate the data set. Our focus has been on expanding the Tinkar
                    framework to accommodate new patterns for data elements that could not be
                    represented by existing concepts. These enhancements are designed to provide a
                    more comprehensive and accurate representation of GSRS data and is part of our
                    broader IKM strategy, which aims to facilitate seamless data sharing and
                    collaboration across different regulatory and scientific databases.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Modeling GSRS</title>
                <para>Out of the 23 data elements, GSRS includes five key data elements that are
                    consistently present: UNII, Display Name, Ingredient Type, Substance Type, and
                    Universally Unique Identifier (UUID). UNII, Display Name, Substance Type, and
                    UUID can be represented using existing Tinkar concepts, as highlighted in Table
                    1. However, Ingredient Type could not be represented using an existing Tinkar
                    concept, so a new pattern was created for Ingredient Type.</para>
                <para>The team also created new patterns for Molecular Formula (MF) and Simplified
                    Molecular-Input Line-Entry System (SMILES). MF is the chemical formula that
                    lists all the elements, plus how many atoms of each element, are present in a
                    chemical compound [11]. It specifies the chemical proportions of the atoms
                    within a particular GSRS substance ingredient. The MF describes useful
                    information on the substance and is beneficial in ensuring accurate data. SMILES
                    stands for the Simplified Molecular-Input Line-Entry System and represents the
                    structure of a molecule using a simple string of characters [12]. It translates
                    the MF into a text format that is easier to understand and manipulate. Each
                    substances corresponding SMILES is useful in verifying consistency in the
                    data.</para>
                <para>The team included an identifier for RxCUI. RxCUI stands for RxNorm Concept
                    Unique Identifier and is a unique numeric code that identifies a drug entity in
                    RxNorm [13]. RxNorm is a data standard that includes normalized names for
                    clinical drugs. RxCUIs are used to support the semantic interoperation between
                    drug terminologies and various pharmacy knowledge base systems like GSRS. Since
                    RxNorm is also part of our greater IKM, RxCUI is a GSRS element that supports
                    the integration of drug and ingredient information and facilitates
                    interoperability across different systems.</para>
                <para>These eight elements serve as the first representation of GSRS. Table 1
                    details how this starter set was modeled.<table frame="all">
                        <title>
                            <emphasis>Table 1: GSRS Modeled Starter Data</emphasis></title>
                        <tgroup cols="2">
                            <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1"/>
                            <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2"/>
                            <thead>
                                <row>
                                    <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2">Description Semantics</entry>
                                </row>
                            </thead>
                            <tbody>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Display Name</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Preferred Term - Preferred Substance Name -
                                                  Display Name</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>FQN - Use the Official Name</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                    </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2" align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Identifier
                                            Semantics</emphasis></entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">UNII</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>FQN – Unique Ingredient Identifier</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                    </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">UUID</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>FQN – Global Substance Registration System
                                                  Universal Unique Identifier</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                    </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">RxCUI</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>FQN – RxNorm Concept Unique Identifier</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                    </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2" align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Stated Definition
                                        Semantics</emphasis></entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Substance_Type</emphasis> – for
                                            substances with NO RxCUI ID</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para>The ISO 11238 substance type used for the primary
                                            substance identity including:</para>
                                        <para>chemicals, nucleic acids, proteins, polymers,
                                            structurally diverse, mixtures and concepts
                                            (SpecifiedSubstanceG1).</para>
                                        <para>All substances will have at least a “simple” stated
                                            definition of what substance they are.</para>
                                    </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Substance_Type</emphasis> – for
                                            substances with a RxCUI ID</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>The substances that have an RXCUI ID will have a more
                                        hierarchical logical definition if RxNorm and SNOMED have
                                        been loaded and the reasoner has been run. The RXCUI ID will
                                        link to RxNorm to then link to a SNOMED CT concept code. The
                                        corresponding SNOMED CT concept code will provide a
                                        hierarchical logical definition.</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2" align="center"><emphasis role="bold">New
                                            Patterns</emphasis></entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Molecular Formula
                                        (MF)</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para>Semantic Purpose:</para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Molecular Formula Semantic</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <para>Semantic Meaning</para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Molecular Formula Semantic</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <para>Field 1:</para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Meaning: Molecular Formula</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Purpose: Molecular Formula</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Field Type: String</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                    </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">SMILES</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para>Semantic Purpose:</para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>SMILES Semantic</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <para>Semantic Meaning</para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>SMILES Semantic</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <para>Field 1:</para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Meaning: SMILES</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Purpose: SMILES</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <para>Field Type: String</para>
                                    </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Ingredient_Type</emphasis> –
                                            UNII grouping based on intended role: Ionic Moiety,
                                            Ingredient Substance, Molecular Fragment, Specified
                                            Substance, Unspecified Ingredient.</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para>Semantic Purpose:</para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Ingredient Type Semantic</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <para>Semantic Meaning</para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Ingredient Type Semantic</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <para>Field 1:</para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Meaning: Ingredient Type</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Purpose: Ingredient Type</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Field Type: Component Field</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <para>New Concepts for:</para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Ionic Moiety</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Molecular Fragment</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Ingredient Substance</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Specified Substance</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Unspecific Ingredient</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                    </entry>
                                </row>
                            </tbody>
                        </tgroup>
                    </table></para>
                <para>The remaining 15 data elements were not included in the GSRS starter data as
                    analysis concluded they are not essential for ensuring consistency, accuracy,
                    and interoperability across various systems. While the team was focused on
                    creating a starter set that encompassed the major areas of GSRS that form the
                    foundation of the shared knowledge base, these elements could be included as
                    Identifier Semantics in the future to build off the pre-existing relationships.
                    Table 2 highlights these elements and why they were not included for this
                    starter set.<table frame="all">
                        <title><emphasis>Table 2: GSRS Data That Is Not Included</emphasis></title>
                        <tgroup cols="2">
                            <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1"/>
                            <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2"/>
                            <thead>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Data Element</entry>
                                    <entry>Why this element was not included</entry>
                                </row>
                            </thead>
                            <tbody>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para><emphasis role="bold">EC</emphasis></para>
                                        <para>European Chemicals Agency registry number (formerly
                                            known EINECS)</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>This identifier is specific to chemical substances
                                        registered in Europe and may not be relevant for datasets
                                        focusing on broader or different geographical
                                        regions.</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para><emphasis role="bold">NCIT</emphasis></para>
                                        <para>NCI Thesaurus Concept Code</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>This code is specific to the National Cancer Institute's
                                        thesaurus, which might be too specialized for datasets not
                                        focused on cancer research or related fields.</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para><emphasis role="bold">RN</emphasis></para>
                                        <para>Registry Number used by many public chemical
                                            information systems particularly CAS Common
                                            Chemistry</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>While useful for chemical databases, this number might be
                                        too specific for general datasets that do not require
                                        detailed chemical information.</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para><emphasis role="bold">PUBCHEM</emphasis></para>
                                        <para>PubChem Compound ID</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>This ID is specific to the PubChem database, which may
                                        not be necessary for datasets that do not require detailed
                                        chemical compound information.</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para><emphasis role="bold">INCHIKEY</emphasis></para>
                                        <para>A fixed-length string created from the IUPAC
                                            International Chemical Identifier (InChI)</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>This identifier is highly specific to chemical
                                        informatics and may not be relevant for datasets that do not
                                        require precise chemical structure information.</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para><emphasis role="bold">EPA_CompTox</emphasis></para>
                                        <para> EPA Substance ID</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>This ID is specific to the Environmental Protection
                                        Agency's CompTox database, which might be too specialized
                                        for datasets not focused on environmental
                                        toxicology.</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para><emphasis role="bold">CATALOGUE_OF_LIFE</emphasis></para>
                                        <para> Catalogue of Life organism ID</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>This identifier is specific to biological taxonomy and
                                        may not be relevant for datasets that do not focus on
                                        biodiversity or taxonomic classification</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para><emphasis role="bold">ITIS</emphasis></para>
                                        <para>Integrated Taxonomic Information System Taxonomic
                                            Serial Number (ITIS TSN)</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>Similar to the Catalogue of Life ID, this is specific to
                                        taxonomic classification and may not be necessary for
                                        datasets not focused on biological taxonomy.</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para><emphasis role="bold">NCBI</emphasis></para>
                                        <para>NCBI taxonomy organism ID</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>This ID is specific to the National Center for
                                        Biotechnology Information's taxonomy database and may be too
                                        specialized for datasets not focused on genetic or
                                        biological research.</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para><emphasis role="bold">PLANTS</emphasis></para>
                                        <para>USDA PLANTS organism ID</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>This identifier is specific to the USDA PLANTS database
                                        and may not be relevant for datasets that do not focus on
                                        plant taxonomy or agriculture.</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para><emphasis role="bold">GRIN</emphasis></para>
                                        <para>USDA Agricultural Research Service Germplasm Resources
                                            Information Network (GRIN) nomen ID</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>This ID is specific to the GRIN database and may be too
                                        specialized for datasets not focused on agricultural
                                        research or germplasm resources.</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para><emphasis role="bold">MPNS</emphasis></para>
                                        <para>Kew Gardens Medicinal Plants Name Service Record ID
                                            (includes source database prefix)</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>This identifier is specific to medicinal plants and may
                                        not be relevant for datasets that do not focus on medicinal
                                        botany or pharmacognosy.</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para><emphasis role="bold">INN_ID</emphasis></para>
                                        <para> Sequential number assigned by World Health
                                            Organization's International Nonproprietary Name (INN)
                                            Programme</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>This ID is specific to the WHO's INN Programme and may be
                                        too specialized for datasets not focused on pharmaceutical
                                        substances.</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para><emphasis role="bold">USAN_ID</emphasis></para>
                                        <para> Alphanumeric code used by American Medical
                                            Association’s United States Adopted Names (USAN)
                                            Council</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>This identifier is specific to the USAN Council and may
                                        not be relevant for datasets that do not focus on
                                        pharmaceutical naming conventions.</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para><emphasis role="bold">DAILYMED</emphasis></para>
                                        <para>UNIIs known to be associated with regulated product
                                            listings on DailyMed</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>This ID is specific to the DailyMed database and may be
                                        too specialized for datasets not focused on regulated
                                        pharmaceutical products.</entry>
                                </row>
                            </tbody>
                        </tgroup>
                    </table></para>
                <para>There are types of names that are not included in this starter set, but can be
                    included in the future. Systematic Name (sys), Common Name (cn), Code (cd), and
                    Brand/Trade Name (bn) can be added as identifier semantics.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>GSRS Transformation Logic</title>
                <para>The transformation logic is used to create Java code that uses raw data from
                    GSRS to generate its corresponding Tinkar representation.</para>
                <para> First, the user will select the UNII data they need from <link xlink:href="https://precision.fda.gov/uniisearch/archive">https://precision.fda.gov/uniisearch/archive</link> and download the file.
                    They will unzip the file and open UNII_Records_DATE in excel. As shown in Table
                    3, The STAMP coordinate for GSRS is based on the UNII data file used.<table frame="all">
                        <title><emphasis>Table 3: GSRS STAMP Coordinates</emphasis></title>
                        <tgroup cols="5">
                            <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1"/>
                            <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2"/>
                            <colspec colnum="3" colname="c3"/>
                            <colspec colnum="4" colname="c4"/>
                            <colspec colnum="5" colname="c5"/>
                            <thead>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Status</entry>
                                    <entry>Time</entry>
                                    <entry>Author</entry>
                                    <entry>Module</entry>
                                    <entry>Path</entry>
                                </row>
                            </thead>
                            <tbody>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Active</entry>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para>Date of File</para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>EX: the file UNII_Data_20241220 has a Time
                                                  value of 2024-12-20</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>GSRS Author Concept</entry>
                                    <entry>GSRS Module Concept</entry>
                                    <entry>Master Path</entry>
                                </row>
                            </tbody>
                        </tgroup>
                    </table></para>
                <para>Status defaults to active because the component is in use. Time is based on
                    the date written in the name of the UNII data file that was previously
                    downloaded. Author is GSRS Author Concept because it represents the author
                    responsible for authoring the change. Module is GSRS Module Concept because it
                    is an assignment based on the corresponding terminology. Path is Master Path
                    because it is currently the default branch for components.</para>
                <para>The user will begin by creating a new concept with the Name space and its
                    corresponding UNII. This single concept will have three different UUIDs: UNII,
                    RxCUI UUID, and FDA UUID. If RxCUI is not present, then the concept will not get
                    that value and will have only a UNII and an FDA UUID. Every semantic that gets
                    created has its own UUID. The description semantic that is created will have a
                    reference component to the above UNII and follow the description pattern. The
                    Language field will be the [English Language] concept. The Description Text
                    value will be the literal string provided in the display name column. The Case
                    Specificity field would be the [Case Insensitive] concept because the case
                    sensitivity does not matter. The Description Type would be the [Fully Qualified
                    Name].</para>
                <para>Next, the user will create three semantics of the identifier pattern for UNII,
                    RxCUI, and FDA UUID. Beginning with UNII, the Identifier Source will be UNII,
                    and the Identifier Value will be the literal string provided in the UNII column.
                    For RxCUI, the Identifier Source will be RxCUI, and the Identifier Value will be
                    the literal string provided in the RxCUI column. For FDA UUID, the Identifier
                    Source will be FDA UUID and the Identifier Value will be the literal string
                    provided in the UUID column.</para>
                <para>Then, the user will create a new semantics of the three patterns previously
                    discussed. Beginning with Molecular Formula, Field 1 will be the literal string
                    provided in the MF column. For SMILES, Field 1 will be the literal string
                    provided in the SMILES column. For Ingredient Type, Field 1 is a Component Field
                    of the five starter data ingredient types that have been created: Ionic Moiety,
                    Molecular Fragment, Ingredient Substance, Specified Substance, and Unspecific
                    Ingredient.</para>
                <para>Finally, the user will create a new axiom semantic for Substance Type. The
                    Substance Type concept is a subclass of UNII. The substance types are Chemicals,
                    Concepts, Mixtures, Nucleic Acids, Polymers, Proteins, and Structurally diverse
                    and are all starter data concepts that have been created.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Conclusion</title>
                <section>
                    <title>Summary of Findings</title>
                    <para>This deliverable builds upon the initial progress report by further
                        detailing the modeling and representation of the GSRS data elements in the
                        context of IKM and its respective domains. The creation of new patterns has
                        expanded the capability of Tinkar to accurately represent the complex data
                        inherent in GSRS. Additionally, the inclusion of RxCUI identifiers enhances
                        the interoperability of GSRS with other drug and ingredient information
                        systems, facilitating seamless data integration and consistency. The
                        outlined transformation logic provides a clear and systematic approach for
                        converting raw GSRS data into its corresponding Tinkar representation,
                        ensuring that the data is accurately and efficiently processed. This logic
                        not only supports the initial data elements but also lays the groundwork for
                        future expansions to include additional identifiers and semantic
                        patterns.</para>
                </section>
                <section>
                    <title>Next Steps</title>
                    <para>As we move forward, the focus will be on refining these models, addressing
                        any gaps found in the current representation, and exploring the inclusion of
                        the remaining data elements as needed. By continuing to build on this
                        foundation, we aim to enhance the quality, consistency, and interoperability
                        of GSRS data, ultimately contributing to more robust and integrated
                        knowledge management systems. The progress made thus far demonstrates the
                        potential for substantial improvements in data quality and accessibility in
                        healthcare, setting the stage for continued advancements in the
                        field.</para>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <para>This deliverable serves as the initial progress report of the GSRS system in the
            context of IKM and its respective domains. This document details the two arenas in which
            IKM expertise can improve areas of concern within GSRS. Our summary of findings
            identifies areas of focus to be addressed in subsequent reports and will require
            additional and continued efforts to improve the implementation, functionality, and
            adoption of IKM solutions into GSRS. GSRS serves as just one area of opportunity in
            which IKM can make substantive improvements to its systems and result in better quality
            of data.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>References</title>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Cholan, R. A., et al. (2022). Encoding laboratory testing data: case studies
                    of the national implementation of HHS requirements and related standards in five
                    laboratories. Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association, 29(8),
                    1372–1380. https://doi.org/10.1093/jamia/ocac072</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>(2022, September 29). FDA’s Global Substance Registration System. Food and
                    Drug Administration.
                    https://www.fda.gov/industry/fda-data-standards-advisory-board/fdas-global-substance-registration-system</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Nielsen, B., &amp; Alliance, P. (2024, August 29). GLOBAL SUBSTANCE
                    REGISTRATION SYSTEM (GSRS) CONSORTIUM ROUND TABLE MEETING, from
                    https://marketing.pistoiaalliance.org/hubfs/GSRS%20Round%20table%20discussion.pdf</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Schmuff, N. (n.d.). Standardizing Quality Submissions and Assessments: PQ/CMC
                    and KASA. Food and Drug Administration. Retrieved February 20, 2025, from
                    https://www.fda.gov/media/168947/download</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>ncats. (2022, February 28). Admin: Group or Role. GitHub.
                    https://github.com/ncats/gsrs3-main-deployment/wiki/Admin:-Group-or-Role</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>UNII - Archive. (2024). Food and Drug Administration. Retrieved February 20,
                    2025, from https://precision.fda.gov/uniisearch/archive</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>ncats. (2024, November 19). Frequently Asked Questions. GitHub.
                    https://github.com/ncats/gsrs3-main-deployment/wiki/Frequently-Asked-Questions#application-programming-interface-api</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Peryea, T., et al. (2021). Global Substance Registration System: consistent
                    scientific descriptions for substances related to health. Nucleic acids
                    research, 49(D1), D1179–D1185. https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkaa962</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>1 GSRS (n.d.). Global Substance Registration System - GSRS. Retrieved February
                    27, 2025, from https://gsrs.ncats.nih.gov/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>ncats. (2022). Instructions to Install and Configure a Single Tomcat Instance,
                    Pull and Build the Code, Deploy, Configure and Test GSRS v3.0 on Red Hat Linux
                    (RHEL) GitHub. from
                    https://github.com/ncats/gsrs3-main-deployment/blob/main/docs/public_example_instructions_to_install_%26_configure_Tomcat_pull_%26_build_the_code_deploy_configure_and_test_GSR</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Illustrated Glossary of Organic Chemistry. (n.d.). Molecular formula (chemical
                    formula). UCLA. Retrieved November 21, 2024, from
                    https://www.chem.ucla.edu/~harding/IGOC/M/molecular_formula.html#:~:text=Molecular%20formula%20(chemical%20formula)%3A%20A%20list%20of%20all,present%3B%20in%20this%20case%20no%20subscript%20is%20used.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Environmental Protection Agency. (2016). SMILES Tutorial. EPA. Retrieved
                    November 21, 2024, from
                    https://archive.epa.gov/med/med_archive_03/web/html/smiles.html</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Peryea, T., Southall, N., Miller, M., Katzel, D., Anderson, N., et al. (2021).
                    Global substance registration system: Consistent scientific descriptions for
                    substances related to health. NIH National Library of Medicine. Retrieved
                    November 26, 2024, from
                    https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7779023/</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
</chapter>
