<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>GSRS/UNII Demonstration Project Progress Report (Months 13-24)</title>
    <section>
        <title>Purpose</title>
        <para>There is an increasing need for high-quality and accurate data as healthcare
            organizations are becoming more reliant on electronic health records (EHRs), laboratory
            information systems (LISs), and other electronic information systems. A primary tool for
            many organizations, terminology standards work to improve the quality and accuracy of
            data. Terminology standards aim to ensure information is captured and represented in a
            repeatable and standardized format so that other organizations have a common
            understanding of the data. While terminology standards are a useful tool, extensive
            knowledge management (KM) is needed to identify, manage, and share the standardized data
            that these systems and standards capture. As data flows within and between healthcare
            systems, the use of different terminology standards, KM processes, and systems
            themselves can pose a threat to the integrity of data. A recent study found that only
            22-68% of data integrity is maintained in a single trip, posing challenges around
            interpretation, and resulting accuracy around patient care [1].</para>
        <para>Integrated Knowledge Management (IKM) is an approach to data management that aims to
            maintain the meaning, integrity, and quality of data as it travels within and between
            healthcare systems. IKM is an evolving approach to manage disparate terminology
            standards using a common, centralized, and repeatable representation of data. The use of
            a common model supports the interoperability of data between disparate terminology
            standards, well documented version control even when different terminology standards
            employ their own versioning practices, and the incorporation of new or emerging
            terminology standards. IKM will use an iterative approach to build upon previous work on
            Resource Description Frameworks (RDFs) and property graphs with novel ideas and
            concepts. There is no reference or best practice guide for how an IKM solution can or
            should operate and will therefore require extensive research, prototyping, and
            development.</para>
        <para>The Food and Drug Administration (FDA) created a Global Substance Registration System
            (GSRS) to facilitate the efficient and accurate information exchange on substances
            within regulated products. The creation of the GSRS knowledge base allowed for
            standardized, scientific descriptions of substances across regulatory lines, such as
            within and between countries. The collection and dependencies of knowledge within GSRS
            presents a direct use case in which IKM and its capabilities can improve GSRS.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Aims</title>
        <para>The aims of this document serve as a collection of landscape analyses of the GSRS
            system and its parts within the domains of Integrated Knowledge Management: Ecosystem
            Engagement and User Interface/User Experience (UI/UX).</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Global Substance Registration System (GSRS)/Unique Ingredient Identifier (UNII) Demonstrations</title>
        <section>
            <title>Ecosystem Engagement: GSRS/UNII Demonstration Project Progress Report [Task
                2.3.1]</title>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Progress Report Week 26</emphasis></para>
            <section>
                <title>Introduction</title>
                <para>Ecosystem engagement approach details the current state and interactions of
                    systems as well as aims to educate on benefits of solutions to the overall
                    system when IKM is utilized. This encompasses investigation of challenges,
                    authorship of materials such as whitepapers, and connecting various entities
                    across numerous fields such as federal, academia, and industry. The culmination
                    of these efforts works to advance data interoperability and integration of
                    knowledge between systems in line with IKM’s mission.</para>
                <para>This portion of the program report provides an overview of GSRS, including its
                    history and interactions with relevant parties, such as with the FDA and
                    relevant terminologies. Key findings indicate challenges around inconsistencies
                    in data quality across regulatory domains, challenges managing proprietary
                    information, and difficulties with standardizing substance identification across
                    diverse chemical structures.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Investigation of GSRS</title>
                <para>The U.S. FDA’s Informatics Team, the National Institutes of Health (NIH)
                    National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences (NCATS), and the European
                    Medicines Agency (EMA) collaborated to create the Global Substance Registration
                    System (GSRS) to meet the need for an accurate, shared substance repository [2].
                    Instead of relying on conventional names, which vary across regulatory domains,
                    the GSRS knowledge base defines substances by standardized, scientific
                    descriptions, allowing for accurate global exchange of critical ingredient
                    information.</para>
                <para>Today, few drugs are sourced within only one jurisdiction due to increasingly
                    globalized supply chains [2]. The growing number of imported FDA-regulated
                    products and ingredients spurred the need for collaboration with international
                    parties to facilitate knowledge sharing through common standards. In 2006, FDA
                    began developing the Substance Registration System (SRS) with the ability to
                    generate and record a Unique Ingredient Identifier for any substance “from an
                    atom to an organism” [4]. The FDA SRS served as the model for the Global
                    Substances Registration System now used around the world.</para>
                <para>The Unique Ingredient Identifier (UNII) was originally developed by the
                    International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry as a non-proprietary, free,
                    unique, unambiguous, non-semantic, alphanumeric identifier based on a
                    substance’s molecular structure, protein and nucleic sequences, and/or
                    descriptive information [2]. A substance may be defined as a chemical, protein,
                    nucleic acid, polymer, mixture, or structurally diverse. UNIIs can be generated
                    at any time in the regulatory life cycle of a drug, biologic, food, or
                    device.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Mandate for International Collaboration</title>
                <para>The International Organization for Standardization (ISO) is a global network
                    of 172 countries that collaborate on developing international standards [5]. ISO
                    has developed over 20,000 international standards through these members and
                    technical experts on a range of topics. The Health Informatics-Identification of
                    Medicinal Products (IDMP) is a group of 5 Health Informatics ISO standards that
                    includes Medicinal Product Identification (MPID), Pharmaceutical Product
                    Identifier (PhPID), Substance Identification (SubID), Dosage Form and Route of
                    Administration, and Units of Measurement. All 5 standards are associated with an
                    ISO code and a technical specifications-implementation guide.</para>
                <para>Implementation of the Identification of Medicinal Products (IDMP) standards is
                    up to individual international organizations who must create their own policies
                    and implementation guidelines. Correspondingly, it is FDA’s goal to harmonize
                    standards for international exchange of medicinal product data, from which it
                    has historically used ISO IDMP standards such as the National Drug Code. The FDA
                    Global Substance Registration System (GSRS) adheres to ISO standards, and
                    includes the U.S. National Drug Code, Unique Ingredient Identifier, and the
                    Unified Code for Units of Measure which conform to ISO 11615, ISO 11238, and ISO
                    11240, respectively. FDA is working with World Health Organization- Uppsala
                    Monitoring Centre (WHO-UMC), HL7, ISO, Global IDMP Working Group (GIDWG), and
                    International Conference on Harmonisation (ICH) to implement IDMP standards, and
                    are members of the GIDWG which aim to demonstrate successful implementation of
                    ISO IDMP standards and maintenance of global identifiers [6,7].</para>
                <para>The GSRS facilitates accurate exchange of substances identifying information
                    through their Unique Ingredient Identifiers (UNIIs). UNIIs are generated using
                    ISO 11238 specifications [8, 9]. ISO 11238 “provides the conceptual framework
                    for defining Substances and Specified Substances and for assigning unique
                    identifiers in the context of the ISO IDMP standards” and describes how to
                    distinguish substances based on their scientific identity [10,11]. In line with
                    international efforts to implement these IDMP standards, the European Union uses
                    GSRS software developed by the FDA.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>FDA Interactions with GSRS</title>
                <para>FDA uses GSRS to register unique substances and control substance data as it
                    pertains to FDA regulated products such as food, pharmaceuticals, and cosmetic
                    products. There are over 157,000 substance records in the most recent volume.
                    Currently, the FDA only focuses on regulated, marketed products. FDA uses UNII
                    throughout product lifecycles, including clinical trial phases, marketing, and
                    post-market surveillance. If a substance is not already registered with GSRS, a
                    submission can be made via the PrecisionFDA website, and a GSRS registrar will
                    review the substance. A UNII will be assigned if the substance is approved
                    [12].</para>
                <para>Users can filter and export GSRS public data from PrecisionFDA and create GSRS
                    JSON (JavaScript Object Notation) records in their own user space. They can also
                    use a PrecisionFDA shared space to collaborate with the FDA-SRS team [2].</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>GSRS and Other Data Standards</title>
                <para>While other standards may not always use GSRS directly, standards can instead
                    utilize UNII as identifiers. For example, the FDA Structured Product Label (SPL)
                    is one of RxNorm’s data sources and as a result, the drug is required to be
                    listed in RxNorm. According to the SPL Implementation Guide, pharmaceutical
                    companies should submit drug information, including UNIIs, to the FDA SPL
                    database. FDA will then list the record on the NIH’s National Library of
                    Medicine’s pharmaceutical product labeling database, DailyMed. All drug products
                    listed in DailyMed are automatically passed through to RxNorm and assigned an
                    RXCUI.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Assessment of Constraints within GSRS</title>
                <para>Current concerns and limitations of GSRS include inconsistencies in data
                    quality across regulatory domains, challenges managing proprietary information,
                    and difficulties with standardizing substance identification across diverse
                    chemical structures. A 2019 IDMP workshop facilitated by the World Health
                    Organization (WHO) including representatives from the U.S. FDA, EMA, Health
                    Canada, the WHO Programme for International Drug Monitoring, and other national
                    health agencies outlined some of these issues and discussed the need for
                    comprehensive solutions. [13]</para>
                <para>The IDMP workshop identified the need to access trade secrets and commercially
                    confidential information, especially for premarket products, to create global
                    substance identifiers as a potential sticking point. The workshop also
                    recognized the possibility that different regulatory standards across countries
                    could result in inconsistent granularity and quality of data included in the
                    GSRS.</para>
                <para>Furthermore, semantic redundancies and the need to identify substances across
                    diverse classes and levels of organization create added complexity. Research
                    published by the NIH NCATS found each substance record includes 6 name synonyms
                    on average, with one record having 240 different names. The study found 1,000
                    examples where the same name can refer to two different substances. Table 1
                    below shows examples of overlap from the public dataset in which common elements
                    between substances can be represented, creating spaces in ambiguity. [3]<table
                        frame="all">
                        <title><emphasis>Table 1: Homographs from Public Dataset</emphasis></title>
                        <tgroup cols="4">
                            <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1"/>
                            <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2"/>
                            <colspec colnum="3" colname="c3"/>
                            <colspec colnum="4" colname="c4"/>
                            <thead>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Substance Homonym</entry>
                                    <entry>Description A</entry>
                                    <entry>Description B</entry>
                                    <entry>Reasoning</entry>
                                </row>
                            </thead>
                            <tbody>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Alpha-Tocopherol</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para>Synthetic Vitamin E</para>
                                        <para>UNII H4N855PNZ1</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para>Natural Extract Vitamin E</para>
                                        <para>UNII N9PR3490H9</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>Stereochemical Ambiguity</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Azithromycin</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para>Azithromycin Trihydrate</para>
                                        <para>UNII 5FD1131I7S</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para>Azithromycin Anhydrous</para>
                                        <para>UNII J2KLZ20U1M</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>Implicit vs explicit hydration</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Lobelia</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para>Indian Tobacco Leaf</para>
                                        <para>UNII 7QFT17RLRG</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para>Lobelia Inflata L. Plant</para>
                                        <para>UNII 9PP1T3TC5U</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>Whole versus part of plant</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Lime</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para>Lime (calcium oxide)</para>
                                        <para>UNII C7X2M0VVNH</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para>Lime (citrus)</para>
                                        <para>UNII 8CZS546954</para>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>Ambiguity of Language</entry>
                                </row>
                            </tbody>
                        </tgroup>
                    </table></para>
                <para>This issue extends to structure-based identifiers for chemical substances.
                    Researchers found over 5,000 GSRS chemical records have two or more IUPAC
                    (International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry) International Chemical
                    Identifiers referring to the same substance, and over 1,200 InChI keys are
                    shared by two or more substances. The same is true for Chemical Abstract Service
                    and other registry numbers, often because more specific substances refer to a
                    more general concept registry number. [3]</para>
                <para>The NIH NCATS study concluded that market forces will continue to drive
                    innovation and the creation of entirely new classes of products. Thus, the GSRS
                    standard must continue to accommodate “new and unusual materials in ways that
                    have traditionally challenged other standards.” [3]</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Benefits of GSRS to IKM</title>
                <para>The ability to represent GSRS data comprehensively and accurately in IKM
                    systems adds to the functionality of IKM. In a previous report, GSRS data
                    elements were identified that could be represented by existing Terminology
                    Knowledge Architecture (Tinkar) components. TAs described previously, the
                    Knowledge Representation team expanded the Tinkar framework to accommodate new
                    patterns for GSRS data elements, allowing for even more robust data modeling as
                    part of IKM.</para>
                <para>The ability to model GSRS substance records further expands the Knowledge
                    Management Environment’s (Komet) utility. Users could include more granular
                    substance data in new and existing LIDR records, ensuring that substance
                    information is seamlessly integrated with clinical and laboratory data. This
                    integration of additional supplemental information may allow IKM to support more
                    robust research, regulation, and clinical decision-making by tying substances to
                    assays and reagents used in other laboratorial settings for example. Overall,
                    growing to accommodate GSRS data expands IKM’s strategy to improve data
                    quality.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Benefits of IKM to GSRS</title>
                <para>The Global Substance Registration System could benefit from integration with
                    IKM in two ways: first, by expanding the usability and interoperability of GSRS
                    substance records and, second, by improving the quality and maintenance of GSRS
                    data.</para>
                <para>With the ability to import GSRS records, IKM expands the usability, reach, and
                    connectedness of GSRS records to other data standards and use-cases. By bringing
                    GSRS into the Tinkar framework, GSRS data can be a part of comprehensive,
                    interoperable health records used for research, regulation, and in clinical
                    contexts. IKM helps to connect GSRS not only to existing pharmaceutical data
                    standards, such as RxNorm, but also with clinical data standards like LOINC,
                    SNOMED, and the local coding systems used by labs and health systems across the
                    country. This connects GSRS to the broader network of health informatics in
                    practice, such as to laboratory devices and any corresponding methods and
                    reference ranges.</para>
                <para>STAMP, a feature of IKM systems, will further expand the utility of GSRS by
                    providing comprehensive version history, including relevant contextual
                    information. STAMP, as shown in Figure 1, includes the status of a given
                    component (e.g., active/inactive), the common standard time a component was
                    created/modified, the author of a given version, the module, which assigns a
                    component to the appropriate terminology or terminology component, and path,
                    which enables testing for provisional content without the constraints of
                    incorporating an entire terminology library. With STAMP, the Tinkar Reference
                    Model records key information for capturing a complete record of all changes to
                    concepts. This allows users to track changes and refer to various versions of
                    semantic components used to represent data. With Tinkar, a single GSRS record
                    could be continuously built out and adapted as it moves between systems, while
                    maintaining version tracking and context. Furthermore, this feature of IKM could
                    enable GSRS administrators to reconcile knowledge surrounding standardization of
                    substances and improve the quality of data by reducing outdated information.
                    Implementing IKM would enable GSRS to continue ingesting new information and
                    adjust existing records while maintaining reliable substance registration,
                    providing a complete history and evolution of a substance and its usages.
                    Comprehensive version tracking can address two of the limitations of GSRS
                    identified previously: first, inconsistent representation and secondly,
                    redundant concepts.</para>
                <figure xml:id="STAMPDiagram"> 
                    <title>Figure 1: STAMP Diagram</title> 
                    <mediaobject> 
                        <imageobject> 
                            <imagedata fileref="../images/STAMP%20Diagram.svg" 
                                scale="35" align="center"/> 
                        </imageobject> 
                    </mediaobject> 
                </figure>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Current State Use-Case</title>
                <para>Azithromycin dihydrate is a common antibiotic used to treat bacterial
                    infections, such as bronchitis and pneumonia. Below, shown in Table 2, is an
                    excerpt of information present within GSRS from PrecisionFDA [14]:<table
                        frame="all">
                        <title><emphasis>Table 2: GSRS Excerpt of Azithromycin
                            Dihydrate</emphasis></title>
                        <tgroup cols="2">
                            <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1" colwidth="1*"/>
                            <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2" colwidth="3.5*"/>
                            <thead>
                                <row>
                                    <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2">AZITHROMYCIN DIHYDRATE
                                        (CHEMICAL)           UNII5FD1131I7S (Salt/Solvate
                                        UNII)</entry>
                                </row>
                            </thead>
                            <tbody>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Substance Hierarchy</entry>
                                    <entry>
                                        <para>Azithromycin Anhydrous (Chemical) - UNII J2KLZ20U1M
                                            (Active Form)</para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Azithromycin Hemiethanolate Monohydrate - UNII
                                                  S548K9P0TK (Active Form)</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Azithromycin Anhydrous - UNII J2KLZ20U1M
                                                  (Active Form)</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Azithromycin Hydrogencitrate - UNII T7I43X3J2A
                                                  (Active Form)</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Azithromycin Lactobionate - UNII 4G45QWD7VU
                                                  (Active Form)</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Azithromycin Sulfate - UNII FF2VAQ5BGN
                                                  (Salt/Solvate UNII)</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para><emphasis role="bold">Azithromycin
                                                  Dihydrate</emphasis> - UNII 5FD1131I7S
                                                  (Salt/Solvate UNII)</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Azithromycin Sodium Dihydrogen Phosphate -
                                                  UNII ADV7FS82PV (Salt/Solvate UNII)</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Azithromycin Fumarate - UNII 2GMV4359ZJ
                                                  (Salt/Solvate UNII)</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Azithromycin, Unspecified Form - UNII
                                                  F94OW58Y8V (Salt/Solvate UNII)</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Azithromycin - UNII F94OW58Y8V (Salt/Solvate
                                                  UNII)</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Azithromycin Maleate - UNII MB33AVA3ZK
                                                  (Salt/Solvate UNII)</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Azithromycin Dihydrochloride - UNII 4WY75EB7AG
                                                  (Salt/Solvate UNII)</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Azithromycin Monohydrate - UNII JTE4MNN1MD
                                                  (Salt/Solvate UNII)</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Azithromycin - UNII F94OW58Y8V (Salt/Solvate
                                                  UNII)</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Azithromycin Isopropanolate Monohydrate - UNII
                                                  QKX96Y66IE (Salt/Solvate UNII)</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Azithromycin Aspartate - UNII 7YDL43V3U2
                                                  (Salt/Solvate UNII)</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Azithromycin Monohydrochloride - UNII
                                                  WWL9UK9T02 (Salt/Solvate UNII)</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para><emphasis role="bold">Azithromycin
                                                  Dihydrate</emphasis> - UNII 5FD1131I7S
                                                  (Salt/Solvate UNII)</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <para>
                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>Azithromycin Isopropanolate Monohydrate -
                                                  UNII QKX96Y66IE (Salt/Solvate UNII)</para>
                                                </listitem>
                                            </itemizedlist>
                                        </para>
                                    </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Names and Synonyms</entry>
                                    <entry>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Azithromycin Dihydrate</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Azithromycin (as Dihydrate)</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Azithromycin Dihydrate [EP Monograph]</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Azithromycin Dihydrate [MI]</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Azithromycin Dihydrate [Orange Book]</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Azithromycin Dihydrate [USP Monograph]</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Azithromycin Dihydrate [VANDF]</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Azithromycin Dihydrate [WHO-DD]</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Azithromycin Hydrate</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Azithromycin Hydrate [JAN]</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Azithromycin [MART.]</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>N-METHYL-11-AZA-10-DEOXO-10-DIHYDROERYTHROMYCIN
                                                  A DIHYDRATE</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>Zithromax</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>ZMAX</para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                    </entry>
                                </row>
                            </tbody>
                        </tgroup>
                    </table></para>
                <para>The GSRS system for azithromycin dihydrate contains information such as the
                    UNII, substance hierarchy, chemical structure, classification codes and
                    identifier codes, names and synonyms, and more. For this substance, there are 14
                    names and synonyms from various sources, with many being the same. Additionally,
                    the substance hierarchy nests azithromycin dihydrate under azithromycin
                    anhydrous, yet is also listed separately twice with the same UNII. There are
                    other duplicate entries presents within the substance hierarchy besides
                    azithromycin dihydrate, such as azithromycin isopropanolate monohydrate and
                    unspecified azithromycin.</para>
                <para>Assessment of azithromycin dihydrate on the GSRS system showcases partial
                    implementation of STAMP methodology. Audit information present on the GSRS
                    system provides the Validated Record Status (Status), Creation and Last Edit
                    Date (Time), and Created By Admin (Author). There are also forms of Module such
                    as through connections to 15 differing systems through codes, such as to RxCUI.
                    The aiding in the implementation of Path through IKM would additionally improve
                    the quality and usability of GSRS data. For example, separate research data can
                    be aggregated from various sources over multiple years, with differing names and
                    local codes are used to represent azithromycin dihydrate. Without version
                    tracking and integration of GSRS and IKM, a researcher must manually clean and
                    process data, and potentially some records created using the unspecified parent
                    concept ‘azithromycin’ could have been lost upon data transfer. The researcher
                    is not able to analyze useful information included in the substances GSRS
                    record, such as RxNorm Concept Unique Identifier (RxCUI) or molecular
                    formula.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Conclusion</title>
                <section>
                    <title>Summary of Findings</title>
                    <para>The GSRS system is a diverse resource for substance registration and
                        management. Challenges persist around difficulties with standardizing substance
                        identification across multiple chemical structures, challenges managing
                        proprietary information, and inconsistencies in data quality across regulatory
                        domains. Adapting the Tinkar Model to accommodate more knowledge in the GSRS
                        expands IKM’s functionality to users for research, regulation, and clinical
                        decision making. Conversely, IKM adds value to GSRS by expands the usability,
                        reach, and connectedness of GSRS records to other data standards and use-cases.
                        The use of a Tinkar feature, STAMP, will ensure IKM-integrated GSRS concepts
                        have comprehensive version tracking and will help GSRS administrators improve
                        quality and cut back on redundancies.</para>
                </section>
                <section>
                    <title>Recommendation</title>
                    <para>Implementation of IKM can allow GSRS to reconcile knowledge surrounding
                        standardization and lead to improvements in data quality. Through this, the
                        GSRS system can continue to ingest added information as well as adjust
                        existing contributions to meet the increasingly interconnected nature of
                        health systems, working to maintain accurate and reliable substance
                        registration. Additionally, crossover between GSRS and IKM will require
                        coordination between relevant parties to successfully implement and build
                        upon existing knowledge.</para>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>UI/UX: GSRS/UNII Demonstration Project Progress Report [Task 1.3.2]</title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Progress Report Week 26</emphasis></para>
        <section>
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <para>The GSRS provides a system that offers a comprehensive framework for the
                definition and identification of substances used in medicinal products, dietary
                supplements, foods, and cosmetics; capturing relationships between substances and
                references, referencing data to their respective authoritative sources [15].</para>
            <para>While comprehensive, the GSRS has limitations as it functions as a static database
                with limited real-time collaboration and lacks multitasking abilities compared to
                Komet. This analysis compares the user experience of the Global Substance
                Registration System (GSRS) with that of the Next-Gen Komet Platform; specifically
                focusing on the enhanced authoring experience Komet provides that the GSRS does not.
                The enhanced authoring experience can be broken down into the below key
                areas.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Unified Knowledge Framework Enhancing Data Reliability</title>
            <para>he GSRS is designed specifically for tracking substances in regulatory approvals,
                safety monitoring, and pharmacovigilance. In contrast, Komet serves as a general
                authoring platform, enabling interoperability across regulatory and healthcare
                organizations.</para>
            <para><emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Knowledge Framework Features of
                    Komet</emphasis></emphasis></para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Multipurpose Support</emphasis>: As shown in Figure 2 Komet
                employs an open knowledge graph methodology, interconnecting substances,
                medications, laboratory tests, and diseases within a cohesive framework. This
                approach facilitates seamless access and utilization of knowledge for researchers,
                regulators, and clinicians. By integrating these diverse domains, Komet reduces the
                reliance on multiple knowledge tools, thereby streamlining learning, adoption, and
                system maintenance for organizations.</para>
            <figure xml:id="KometGeneralDiGraphEditing"> 
                <title>Figure 2: Komet General DiGraph Editing</title> 
                <mediaobject> 
                    <imageobject> 
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/Komet%20General%20DiGraph%20Editing.svg" 
                            scale="25" align="center"/> 
                    </imageobject> 
                </mediaobject> 
            </figure>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Breaking Down Silos</emphasis>: Komet’s integrated knowledge
                framework effectively eliminates traditional healthcare data silos, facilitating
                direct connections between regulators and real-world clinical practice. This
                integration streamlines the monitoring of substance usage in treatments and reduces
                redundant efforts across various healthcare and regulatory systems.</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Improved Data Quality</emphasis>: By harmonizing healthcare
                knowledge, Komet significantly enhances data accuracy and consistency; leading to a
                superior safety monitoring, improved insights into real-world clinical effects, and
                greater efficiency compared to the GSRS system.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Modern User Experience Focused on Personalized Multitasking</title>
            <para>The GSRS functions as a basic substance search and submission platform but
                provides limited support for personalized workflows and collaboration. Although the
                GSRS is user-friendly, it does not offer the productivity and efficiency tools
                available within Komet. Komet introduces a modern user experience to healthcare
                knowledge management, aligning with the advanced usability standards prevalent in
                other industries in several ways.</para>
            <para><emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Multitasking Features of Komet compared to
                        GSRS</emphasis></emphasis></para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Project Journals</emphasis>: GSRS has limited
                functionalities for organizing and tracking work. As illustrated in Figure 3,
                Komet’s Knowledge Journals offer a robust solution, enabling users to document,
                track, and share projects within a structured framework. These journals maintain a
                comprehensive history of completed work, track status updates, and provide real-time
                alerts, thereby ensuring seamless workflow management.</para>
            <figure xml:id="KometLandingPageProjectJournals"> 
                <title>Figure 3: Komet Landing Page – Project Journals</title> 
                <mediaobject> 
                    <imageobject> 
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/Komet%20Landing%20Page%20–%20Project%20Journals.svg" 
                            scale="25" align="center"/> 
                    </imageobject> 
                </mediaobject> 
            </figure>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Infinite Workspace</emphasis>: GSRS requires users to work
                in a linear, sequential manner, thereby limiting multitasking and flexible authoring
                processes. In contrast, Komet provides an expansive, panel-based workspace, as shown
                in Figure 4, that enables users to personalize their workflows, seamlessly switch
                between related tasks, and optimize productivity.</para>
            <figure xml:id="InfiniteWorkspaceOpenConcepts"> 
                <title>Figure 4: Infinite Workspace – Open Concepts</title> 
                <mediaobject> 
                    <imageobject> 
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/Infinite%20Workspace%20–%20Open%20Concepts.svg" 
                            scale="50" align="center"/> 
                    </imageobject> 
                </mediaobject> 
            </figure>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Extension and Development Path Management:</emphasis> GSRS
                lacks robust extension and development features, limiting its adaptability in
                collaborative environments. Komet empowers users with customizable development
                paths, ranging from personal sandboxes to production environments, enabling version
                control, seamless knowledge sharing, and structured contributions.</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Robust Comparison Tools</emphasis>: GSRS offers basic search
                and browsing capabilities but lacks advanced comparison tools essential for
                effective healthcare knowledge management. In contrast, Komet’s panel-based
                information design and detailed knowledge history tracking allows users to compare
                knowledge across different healthcare concepts, hierarchical structures, and system
                extensions. These advanced tools help identify and prevent inaccuracies,
                duplications, and errors from propagating within the knowledge base.</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Duplicate &amp; Favorite Functionality:</emphasis> Komet
                introduces efficient duplication and favoriting tools to streamline repetitive tasks
                and workflows. These features allow users to reuse existing knowledge assets created
                by others, thereby significantly enhancing speed, collaboration, and knowledge
                dissemination.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Enhanced Collaboration for More Accurate and Up-to-Date Knowledge</title>
            <para>GSRS primarily functions as a static database with limited real-time collaboration
                between researchers, regulators, and industry experts. Updates require formal
                submissions and reviews, resulting in a slow reflection of new discoveries. Whereas
                Komet is designed as an open framework that actively encourages cross-disciplinary
                collaboration to enhance the acquisition and accuracy of healthcare
                knowledge.</para>
            <para><emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Collaboration Features of
                    Komet</emphasis></emphasis></para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Open-Source Integrated Knowledge Foundation</emphasis>: GSRS
                lacks an open framework that would enable dynamic, real-time contributions to
                maintain and expand healthcare knowledge. Komet’s open-source approach fosters
                greater flexibility, broader adoption, and increased momentum, ensuring that
                healthcare knowledge remains current and continuously evolving.</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Multi-User Collaboration, Sharing, and Real-Time
                    Feedback</emphasis>: GSRS does not provide an intuitive mechanism for
                collaboration or feedback on substance information. Komet introduces multi-user
                capabilities, allowing multiple contributors to work on the same task
                simultaneously. Additionally, as shown below in Figure 5, Komet provides built-in
                tools for users to share content, leave notes, add comments, and offer feedback
                throughout the knowledge creation and validation process. Flexible sharing controls
                also allow users to personalize collaboration settings to engage with others in a
                meaningful way.</para>
            <figure xml:id="KometReal-timeReasoner"> 
                <title>Figure 5: Komet Real-time Reasoner</title> 
                <mediaobject> 
                    <imageobject> 
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/Komet%20Real-time%20Reasoner.svg" 
                            scale="35" align="center"/> 
                    </imageobject> 
                </mediaobject> 
            </figure>
            <para>Transparent Knowledge History &amp; Version Tracking: GSRS lacks a detailed
                version history, making it challenging to track changes, provide feedback, and
                collaborate effectively. Komet’s framework ensures full transparency by maintaining
                a comprehensive, and accessible record of knowledge updates. As depicted in Figure 6
                &amp; 7, this enables users to review, build upon, improve, or correct previous
                work, ensuring that knowledge remains accurate and continuously refined.</para>
            <figure xml:id="KometConceptHistoryandTimeTravelOne"> 
                <title>Figure 6: Komet Concept History &amp; Time Travel 1</title> 
                <mediaobject> 
                    <imageobject> 
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/Komet%20Concept%20History%20and%20Time%20Travel%20One.svg" 
                            scale="35" align="center"/> 
                    </imageobject> 
                </mediaobject> 
            </figure> 
            <figure xml:id="KometConceptHistoryandTimeTravelTwo"> 
                <title>Figure 7: Komet Concept History &amp; Time Travel 2</title> 
                <mediaobject> 
                    <imageobject> 
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/Komet%20Concept%20History%20and%20Time%20Travel%20Two.svg" 
                            scale="35" align="center"/> 
                    </imageobject> 
                </mediaobject> 
            </figure>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Customization Features to Support Unique Information Needs</title>
            <para>GSRS operates as a one-size-fits-all application with limited customization
                options. In contrast, Komet offers a range of customization features, allowing
                organizations and users to tailor the platform to fit their specific workflows and
                processes. This enhances adoption rates and enables Komet to serve as a flexible
                solution for breaking down healthcare knowledge silos.</para>
            <para><emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Customization Features of
                    Komet</emphasis></emphasis></para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Customizable Data Views</emphasis>: GSRS offers only
                pre-defined views of its substance data, restricting users' ability to adjust the
                display to their specific needs. Komet, on the other hand, empowers organizations
                and users with tools to create customized information panels, as shown in Figure 8
                &amp; 9, ensuring they can adapt the platform to support knowledge authors,
                researchers, regulators, and clinicians in a manner that best fits their
                workflow.</para>
            <figure xml:id="KometMasterViewEditor-CustomizedInformationTemplates"> 
                <title>Figure 8: Komet Master View Editor - Customized Information Templates</title> 
                <mediaobject> 
                    <imageobject> 
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/Komet Master%20View%20Editor%20-%20Customized%20Information%20Templates.svg" 
                            scale="35" align="center"/> 
                    </imageobject> 
                </mediaobject> 
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="KometLIDRRecord-CustomInformationPanel"> 
                <title>Figure 9: Komet LIDR Record - Custom Information Panel</title> 
                <mediaobject> 
                    <imageobject> 
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/Komet%20LIDR%20Record%20-%20Custom%20Information%20Panel.svg" 
                            scale="35" align="center"/> 
                    </imageobject> 
                </mediaobject> 
            </figure>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Plug-In Support for Extended Functionality</emphasis>: Komet
                features a plug-in framework, akin to modern open-source platforms, allowing users
                and third-party providers to contribute new features and enhancements. This
                decentralized approach expands Komet’s authoring capabilities, encouraging broader
                adoption, and increasing the overall usefulness of its integrated knowledge
                foundation.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Conclusion</title>
            <para>In conclusion, while the GSRS remains a useful tool for exploring definitions and
                identifications of substances, Komet offers an enhanced alternative with its
                integrated and clinical context, advanced visualization, search and filtering, and
                user-friendly interface. Komet is designed to facilitate a more comprehensive
                understanding of clinical concepts and foster a community-driven approach to
                refining these concepts. Its interactive comments section allows users to share
                observations, insights, and resolve queries, thereby enhancing the overall
                efficiency and efficacy of healthcare professionals.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <para>This deliverable serves as an updated progress report of the GSRS system in the
            context of IKM and its respective domains. This document details the arenas in which IKM
            expertise can improve areas of concern within GSRS. Our summary of findings identifies
            areas of focus to be addressed in subsequent reports and will require additional and
            continued efforts to improve the implementation, functionality, and adoption of IKM
            solutions into GSRS. GSRS serves as just one area of opportunity in which IKM can make
            substantive improvements to its systems and result in better quality of data.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>References</title>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Cholan, R. A., et al. (2022). Encoding laboratory testing data: case studies
                    of the national implementation of HHS requirements and related standards in five
                    laboratories. Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association, 29(8),
                    1372–1380. https://doi.org/10.1093/jamia/ocac072</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>(2022, September 29). FDA’s Global Substance Registration System. FDA.
                    https://www.fda.gov/industry/fda-data-standards-advisory-board/fdas-global-substance-registration-system</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Peryea, T., et al (2020). Global Substance Registration System: consistent
                    scientific descriptions for substances related to health. Nucleic Acids
                    Research, 49(D1), D1179–D1185. https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkaa962</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Unique Ingredient Identifier (UNII). (2019). Va.gov.
                    https://www.oit.va.gov/Services/TRM/StandardPage.aspx?tid=5227</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>(2016). What we do. ISO. https://www.iso.org/what-we-do.html</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Fitzmartin, R., Chen, T.-J., &amp; Perkins, V. (2022). Toward Global
                    Identification of Medicinal Products (IDMP) Implementation: A Focus on Biologics
                    1. https://sbiaevents.com/files2022/IDMP-Webinar-2022-10-27.pdf</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Toward Global IDMP Implementation: A Focus on Global Use Cases. (2023). U.S.
                    Food and Drug Administration.
                    https://www.fda.gov/drugs/news-events-human-drugs/toward-global-idmp-implementation-focus-global-use-cases-11282023</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>FDA’s Global Substance Registration System. (n.d.). Precision.fda.gov.
                    https://precision.fda.gov/uniisearch</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>(2022). Identification of Medicinal Products (IDMP). FDA.
                    https://www.fda.gov/industry/fda-data-standards-advisory-board/identification-medicinal-products-idmp</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>(2018). Health informatics — Identification of medicinal products — Data
                    elements and structures for the unique identification and exchange of regulated
                    information on substances [Review of Health informatics — Identification of
                    medicinal products — Data elements and structures for the unique identification
                    and exchange of regulated information on substances].
                    https://www.iso.org/obp/ui/en/#iso:std:iso:11238:ed-2:v1:en</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>(2018). Health informatics — Identification of medicinal products (IDMP) —
                    Implementation guidelines for ISO 11238 for data elements and structures for the
                    unique identification and exchange of regulated information on substances
                    [Review of Health informatics — Identification of medicinal products (IDMP) —
                    Implementation guidelines for ISO 11238 for data elements and structures for the
                    unique identification and exchange of regulated information on substances].
                    https://www.iso.org/obp/ui/en/#iso:std:iso:ts:19844:ed-3:v1:en</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>(2024, March 18). Registering chemicals or proteins in FDA’s Global Substance
                    Registration System within precisionFDA [Review of Registering chemicals or
                    proteins in FDA’s Global Substance Registration System within precisionFDA].
                    Food and Drug Administration.
                    https://www.fda.gov/media/169513/download?attachment</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>NOTES FROM A WORKSHOP ON THE IDENTIFICATION OF MEDICINAL PRODUCTS (IDMP).
                    (2019).
                    https://admin.iprp.global/sites/default/files/2020-04/IPRP_IDMPWG_Minutes_11-12Sep2019Workshop_2020_0310.pdf</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>GSRS. (2025). Fda.gov.
                    https://precision.fda.gov/ginas/app/ui/substances/f7e56a5b-ae71-4663-bda9-29d291956e26</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Peryea, T., Southall, N., Miller, M., Katzel, D. A., Anderson, N., Neyra, J.,
                    Stemann, S., Nguyen, D.-T., Dammika Amugoda, Archana Newatia, Ramez Ghazzaoui,
                    Johanson, E., Diederik, H., Callahan, L., &amp; Switzer, F. (2020). Global
                    Substance Registration System: consistent scientific descriptions for substances
                    related to health. Nucleic Acids Research, 49(D1), D1179–D1185.
                    https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkaa962</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
</chapter>
