<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Status Definitions</title>
    <section>
        <title>Active</title>
        <para>An active component is one that is fully committed, currently in use, and visible
            throughout the application. This status represents the default “live” state for any
            concept or semantic, meaning the component is displayed across all panels and is
            accessible to users. On the backend, active components are fully committed, included in
            all indexes, and exported as part of the system’s data outputs.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Inactive</title>
        <para>An inactive component is one that has been explicitly marked as no longer active but
            is retained within the system for historical and traceability purposes. This status is
            used when a component is superseded, deprecated, or needs to be hidden from active use
            while still remaining viewable for reference. Inactive components are shown with an
            inactive status and are visible in history views and filters. On the backend, they are
            retained with all historical versions and are included in exports and audit logs.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Withdrawn</title>
        <para>A withdrawn component is one that was released by mistake and must be treated as if it
            never existed, such as in cases of copyright violation, data breach, or legal removal.
            This is a rare status, typically invoked under legal or policy mandates. Withdrawn
            components are hidden from normal views and do not appear in searches or history unless
            specifically surfaced. Although they still exist in the database, they are treated as
            “voided” and do not appear in exports, indexes, or history trails. Importantly, a
            withdrawn status is permanent and should never be recovered to active or inactive; it is
            distinct from inactive because it fully suppresses visibility and treats the component
            as retracted from the system.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Canceled</title>
        <para>A canceled component refers to a temporary or uncommitted component or version that
            was abandoned before being committed to the system. This occurs when a user cancels a
            creation or exits the application without saving changes. Canceled components are never
            visible in the application and are filtered from all user-facing views. On the backend,
            they exist only in a transient state, marked with a “canceled” stamp, and are subject to
            garbage collection and cleanup. They are not included in exports.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Retired (Deprecated Term)</title>
        <para>The term “retired” was previously used informally or in reference to external
            standards, such as SNOMED or LOINC, but it is not a valid or supported status in Komet.
            It is recommended to avoid using “retired” to describe a component’s state and to use
            “inactive” instead. There is no user interface or backend recognition of “retired” as a
            formal status.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>

