<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Summary of Findings – Safety Systems Impact for Knowledge Management and Advanced
        Analytics Constructs (Months 13-24)</title>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>Integrated Knowledge Exchange (IKE) is a set of principles, tools and methods that are
            designed to make doing the right thing easier. One of those “right things” is patient
            safety. First and foremost, our health information must do no harm to the patient. IKE
            enables more accurate, complete, precise, and higher-quality health data that is safer
            to use for clinical decision-making as low-quality health data management practices can
            lead to under treatment, over treatment, or delayed treatment resulting in preventable
            patient harm [1].</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Patient Safety – Then and Now</title>
        <para>Patient safety has been defined as the “prevention of harm to patients” [2]. To
            achieve patient safety, the whole healthcare system must work collaboratively to prevent
            errors, learn from the errors that occur, and develop a culture of safety similar to
            other high-risk industries, such as aviation.</para>
        <para>Previously, patient safety efforts have primarily focused on investigating adverse
            events after they have occurred. This is known as reactive safety and, while important
            for learning from errors, is insufficient in reducing common adverse events. such as
            medication errors, surgical complications, or diagnostic errors [2]. Alternatively,
            proactive safety attempts to design or redesign systems, processes, and methods based on
            leading indicators of increased risk, poor quality, or identified flaws before an
            adverse event occurs. Examples of proactive safety practices include hazard analysis,
            safety reporting, audits, tracers, training, testing, and surveys to measure the culture
            of safety.</para>
        <para>Properly implementing both reactive and proactive safety requires organizations and
            systems to develop a culture of safety that establishes a non-punitive response to
            error, also known as a “just culture". Just culture is a balance between learning from
            error and accountability that encourages practitioners to be transparent with the
            self-reporting of errors by reducing or eliminating the fear of retribution, loss of
            employment, or legal action [3]. Blaming an individual or team for system errors
            prevents learning from errors, impedes continuous improvement, and reinforces silence
            when system vulnerabilities are discovered. Unfortunately, many current healthcare
            professionals continue to be hesitant when reporting errors due to medical malpractice
            litigation concerns and threat of employment termination.</para>
        <para>Since the 1999 report, To Err is Human, was published by the Institute of Medicine,
            patient safety has received more attention across the healthcare ecosystem due to the
            prevalence of preventable patient harm. A short review of these important patient safety
            publications documents key milestones for system improvement opportunities and required
            changes to improve patient care and safety:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>To Err is Human (1999) – described the breadth and depth of preventable harm
                    that estimated nearly 100,000 Americans died because of preventable patient harm
                    and the challenge of improving patient safety [4]. In 2016, a study from Johns
                    Hopkins researchers estimated annual patient deaths at more than 250,000
                    Americans making preventable patient harm the third leading cause of death in
                    the United States of America (USA) behind cardiac disease and cancer [5].</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Crossing the Quality Chasm (2001) – described major healthcare quality gaps,
                    how current practices degrade the quality of healthcare in America, and how to
                    take systems approaches to improve the quality of care delivered to patients.
                    The paper outlines goals for healthcare quality improvements, including
                    redesigning safety as system property, improving effectiveness, focusing on
                    patient-centered approaches, timeliness and efficiency, and more. The report
                    also furthered the need for digitized health information systems [6].</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Health IT and Patient Safety (2012) – described both the promise of health
                    information technology (HIT) and the potential patient safety risks of poorly
                    designed, improperly configured, and mismanaged electronic patient data and HIT
                    systems. The report further highlighted the importance of the human-machine
                    (including software) interfaces to prevent diagnostic errors and improve
                    clinical decision making. HIT vendors, regulators, and health systems were
                    encouraged to find ways to mitigate identified HIT risks and the unintended
                    consequences of the Meaningful Use criteria as part of the Health Information
                    Technology for Economic and Clinical Health (HITECH) Act of 2009 [7].</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Improving Diagnosis in Health Care (2015) – described the importance of
                    reducing the prevalence of diagnostic errors across the healthcare system
                    including missed diagnoses, delayed diagnoses, and incorrect diagnoses resulting
                    in undertreatment, overtreatment, suboptimal standard of care, and preventable
                    patient harm. It is estimated that every American will experience at least one
                    diagnostic error during their lifetime. High quality health information is
                    critical for improving diagnostic decision making and clinicians and patients
                    must be able to trust the underlying health data and HIT systems being used for
                    diagnostic decision making [8].</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Safety of Inpatient Care in Surgical Settings: cohort study - described the
                    state of adverse patient events today for patients admitted to 11 U.S. hospitals
                    for surgical procedures. The authors identified that more than one third (38%)
                    of surgical patients admitted as inpatients to the hospitals being studied
                    suffered an adverse event. Nearly half of the adverse events were identified as
                    major (serious harm resulting in substantial intervention or prolonged recovery,
                    life threatening event, or death) and likely preventable [9].</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <section>
            <title>High Reliability Organizations (HROs)</title>
            <para>High reliability organization (HRO) principles from other safety critical
                industries such as commercial aviation and nuclear power began to be adopted as a
                patient safety framework in some healthcare settings (See Table 1) [10]. These
                principles originated from social science as behaviors present in organizations that
                operate in extremely complex, high-risk environments with high levels of system
                reliability believed to produce safer outcomes. Reliability is the probability that
                a component or system will perform as designed under certain conditions over time
                (i.e., checklists). <table frame="all">
                    <title><emphasis>Table 1: HRO Principles for Health
                        Information</emphasis></title>
                    <tgroup cols="3">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1" colwidth="1*"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2" colwidth="1*"/>
                        <colspec colnum="3" colname="c3" colwidth="1*"/>
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry>HRO Principle</entry>
                                <entry>HRO Response</entry>
                                <entry>IKE Application</entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Preoccupation with
                                    Failure</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Develop leading safety indicators</entry>
                                <entry>Measure &amp; monitor data quality</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Reluctance to
                                    Simplify</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Awareness of active &amp; latent failures</entry>
                                <entry>Identify known &amp; unknown defects</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Sensitivity to
                                    Operations</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Promote reporting of defects</entry>
                                <entry>Speak up &amp; report errors/defects</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Commitment to
                                    Resilience</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Manage errors before losses occur</entry>
                                <entry>Perform rigorous testing/monitoring</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Deference to
                                    Expertise</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Engage experts in decision making</entry>
                                <entry>Use informatics experts in HIT</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table></para>
            <para>While leaders and managers can foster a culture supported by HRO principles, HRO
                methods rely on decomposition or breaking complex systems down into single
                components to analyze. If they primarily focus on reducing errors at a single
                component level, also known as component failures (human or machine), they can be
                erroneously made to believe that worse case scenarios (losses, adverse events, and
                accidents) have linear causality with the human as a possible weak link in the
                system.</para>
            <para>Traditional safety approaches are inadequate when it comes to addressing the
                increasing complexity in the healthcare ecosystem. Methodologies, like root cause
                analysis (RCA) and Failure Modes and Effects Analysis (FMEA), focus on failures at a
                component level or as over-simplified human error and were developed before work
                systems incorporated software, computers, and other sophisticated technology such as
                artificial intelligence (AI). The healthcare ecosystem is complex, multifaceted, and
                highly coupled across various systems, such as healthcare data information systems,
                and requires a more complex and comprehensive approach to safety that employs
                systems theory, systems thinking, and a systems approach to safety [11,12].</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>System Safety</title>
            <para>System Safety is rooted in systems theory where the whole system is more than the
                sum of the parts. System Safety addresses the whole using a combination of systems
                and safety engineering approaches and views patient safety as a control
                problem.</para>
            <para>Engineering models can be developed and analyzed for safety and quality purposes
                throughout the system’s lifecycle from design through adoption. These system models
                are not schematics or flow charts; instead, they serve as abstract representations
                of highly complex sociotechnical relationships between a controller and the process
                being controlled. These relationships are known as control loops (Figure 1)
                [13].</para>
            <figure xml:id="Provider-PatientControlLoop"> 
                <title>Figure 1: Provider/Patient Control Loop </title> 
                <mediaobject> 
                    <imageobject> 
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/Provider-Patient%20Control%20Loop.svg" 
                            scale="50" align="center"/> 
                    </imageobject> 
                </mediaobject> 
            </figure>
            <para>Control loops are hierarchal with the Provider as a controller above the Patient,
                the controlled process in this example. The downward arrows represent the control
                actions that the controller uses to control the patient care process including
                assessments, exams, tests, imaging, treatments, and therapies. The upward arrows are
                feedback mechanisms the provider receives from the patient such as their medical
                history, symptoms, and health trends.</para>
            <para>Without adequate feedback, the provider would not be able to make safe, high
                quality clinical decisions that meet the standard of care. The Provider controller
                develops a process model or belief system about each individual patient before
                making treatment decisions. Other information may be accessible through the
                patient’s electronic health record (EHR), a family member, or another patient
                advocate. Modelling the patient care system of interest builds on this control loop
                to include other essential control loops forming what’s known as a control structure
                [14].</para>
            <para>Once the control structure is fully modelled, either in the design or redesign
                phases of the system lifecycle, teams can conduct proactive and retrospective safety
                analyses to identify new requirements, system hazards, unsafe control actions, and
                missing feedback loops. The System Theoretic Process Analysis (STPA) method is most
                effective when used early in the design or redesign phase as a prospective safety
                analysis while the Causal Analysis based on Systems Theory (CAST) is used
                retrospectively to determine causal factors of adverse events such as preventable
                patient harm [15].</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Safety Management Systems (SMS)</title>
            <para>Safety Management Systems (SMS) are used by high-risk industries such as aviation,
                military commands, health care, and nuclear power to reduce or eliminate hazards for
                safer outcomes. SMS is a formalized approach to safety decision-making, proactive
                safety management, safety culture promotion, and quality assurance. An effective SMS
                relies on a comprehensive safety information system that has leading indicators of
                safe performance, feedback from voluntary reporting, and passive data collection
                using software applications that monitor system control actions.</para>
            <para>Safety data trends are reported to responsible parties including operators,
                supervisors, management, regulators, and other industry stakeholders. An SMS is an
                enabler for learning including knowledge sharing, policy effectiveness, and
                innovation and drives key processes like safety risk management and safety assurance
                [16]. SMS design is enhanced when system control structures are modelled, monitored,
                and audited using system safety engineering principles such as STPA to support
                continual process improvement.</para>
            <para>Safety in a health data context includes clinical decision support, safe data
                exchange, and safe use of health data for regulatory oversight, health equity,
                research, and population health decision-making. Furthermore, poor data quality
                degrades patient safety especially among disparate health populations when using low
                quality data to train Artificial Intelligence (AI) models for patient care
                [17].</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Spotlight Case Study #1: System-Theoretic Process Analysis (STPA) of the U.S.
                Diagnostic Laboratory Data Ecosystem</title>
            <para>The STPA of the U.S. Diagnostic Laboratory Data Ecosystem, was a proactive
                analysis that sought to detail the operations of the complex, interdependent system
                both as a whole and of its respective components and identify where – or where not –
                diagnostic laboratory data was fulfilling its goals of higher quality care.</para>
            <para>Using STPA with interviews from 50 stakeholders, the research team developed a
                model of the ecosystem (control structure) and analyzed it to identify the causal
                factors in common types of adverse events related to diagnostic laboratory data and
                provided recommendations for improvement and system redesign. This analysis
                identified over 200 Unsafe Control Actions (UCAs) and six main causal factors that
                contribute to two main recurring hazards: (1) patients receiving less than adequate
                care and (2) diminishing trust and/or reputation within the laboratory data
                ecosystem.</para>
            <para>These six causal factors with their associated recommendation were:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Decentralized and missing oversight</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Recommendation 1: Assign responsibility for addressing gaps in the
                                regulatory oversight of laboratory data exchanges between system
                                components that are regulated by different agencies.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Recommendation 2: Identify the data and standards needs of
                                regulatory agencies and ensure they have the ability to use them
                                appropriately.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Recommendation 3: Encourage the identification of regulatory gaps
                                in other areas of the laboratory ecosystem through additional
                                systems-theory-based analyses.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Inadequacies and gaps in laboratory data standards, including standards
                        that are loosely constrained, ambiguous, and outdated</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Recommendation 4: Reference libraries must develop a knowledge
                                base that establishes a ground truth for naming, coding, and mapping
                                of reference terminologies to particular laboratory tests, and
                                stakeholders must be incentivized to use it.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Recommendation 5: Appropriate groups must be assigned
                                responsibility for identifying gaps and weaknesses in laboratory
                                data standards and for establishing a reporting channel for problems
                                related to them.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Recommendation 6: Standards Development Organizations (Logical
                                Observation Identifiers Names and Codes [LOINC®], Systematized
                                Nomenclature of Medicine Clinical Terms (SNOMED CT®, RxNorm, etc.)
                                must continuously support users by identifying and eliminating
                                ambiguities in implementation guides for HIT standards.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Inaccurate perceptions of risks with respect to both laboratory data and
                        the use of HIT</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Recommendation 7: Proactively and retroactively investigate
                                systemic sources of diagnostic error.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Recommendation 8: Create a consolidated national database for HIT
                                safety reporting that can be used to identify trends and
                                opportunities for improving patient safety outcomes. It should
                                include information about HIT not behaving as users intended and
                                detail how features of HIT design may have contributed to “user
                                errors.”</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Lack of a systems view by participants in the system</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Recommendation 9: Educate the healthcare community on systems
                                engineering and systemic approaches for solving problems, including
                                tools to accomplish this goal.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Recommendation 10: Establish appropriate control loops for updates
                                to standards and HIT.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Inadequate regulatory emphasis on the safety involved in health system
                        information technology</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Recommendation 11: Assign regulatory oversight of HIT safety to
                                The Assistant Secretary of Technology/Office of the National
                                Coordinator for HIT (ASTP/ONC) or another appropriate group. Include
                                the explicit directive to develop and include safety-related
                                certification criteria for HIT and the ability to limit the
                                inclusion of “hold harmless” clauses in HIT contracts.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Recommendation 12: Establish incentives for using certified HIT
                                throughout the entire healthcare ecosystem</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Flawed communication and coordination</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Recommendation 13: Develop formal processes for inclusion of
                                laboratorians in the multidisciplinary teams responsible for
                                decisions about laboratory data needs, representations, and
                                interfaces at care facilities.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>UCAs Scenario – Defining the Need for IKE</title>
            <para>This following UCA scenario identifies an area within the Spotlight Case Study #1
                where IKE solutioning would strengthen knowledge representation, improve data
                quality, and reduce patient risk.</para>
            <para>UCA scenario: A medical practitioner may provide treatment that does not match the
                patient’s condition. One contributing factor may be that the practitioner did not
                have the diagnostic information to inform their mental model of the patient’s
                condition. The diagnostic information may not be observed by the medical
                practitioner because they may be accustomed to using their routine process to access
                results in the EHR, which only displays laboratory data that has been previously
                mapped to the care facility’s EHR system (e.g., mapped to a LOINC® code or local
                code representation). In some cases, additional unmapped test results are shared by
                the laboratory as a Portable Document Format (PDF) and the physician may not notice
                the PDF due to its lack of salience in the EHR process flow. Physicians who are not
                expecting and looking for the test results may not be prompted to look for
                additional, unmapped information in a patient profile, particularly if the unmapped
                results were ordered by another physician or a long time ago. The results may have
                been shared as a PDF because they pertained to a new or uncommon test whose format
                could not be represented in the messaging standard available to that laboratory-care
                facility pair. Standards for new and complex tests (e.g., genomics) are not yet
                tightly constrained, which means the results can be shared as PDFs because Clinical
                Laboratory Improvement Amendments (CLIA) only requires that the data that is sent
                gets received and does not specify the method of transmission nor impose any
                requirement or confirmation that the information is observed by the medical
                practitioner. CLIA was drafted and approved in 1988, before EHRs were widely adopted
                and modifications to CLIA require Congressional approval. The following is a
                visualization of this scenario using system safety principles (Figure 2).</para>
            <figure xml:id="VisualizationofUCALaboratoryDataScenario "> 
                <title>Figure 2: Visualization of UCA Laboratory Data Scenario </title> 
                <mediaobject> 
                    <imageobject> 
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/Visualization%20of%20UCA%20Laboratory%20Data%20Scenario.svg" 
                            scale="50" align="center"/> 
                    </imageobject> 
                </mediaobject> 
            </figure>
            <para>For the full report, click <link
                    xlink:href="https://synensysglobal.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/System-Safety-within-Laboratory-Data-Exchanges-Report.pdf"
                    >here</link>.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>The Promise and Challenges of Digital Health Information and Patient Safety</title>
        <para>Moving from paper charts to EHR systems is mostly complete (96%) in hospitals in the
            U.S., while 22% of office-based physician practices remain paper-based [18]. Incentive
            programs such as the Meaningful Use (MU) program provided government funding through the
            U.S. Center for Medicare and Medicaid Services (CMS) for health systems and provider
            organizations to digitize their health information systems. From 2010-2020, MU program
            goals included digital data collection, data sharing, advanced clinical processes, and
            improved outcomes. Studies have shown that HIT has improved patient safety by reducing
            medication errors, avoiding adverse drug reactions, and increasing adherence to
            evidence-based medicine protocols [19].</para>
        <para>While HIT has improved some clinical outcomes, the adoption, configuration,
            implementation, and maintenance of HIT has increased patient risk in other parts of the
            health delivery system due to unintended consequences of poorly managed systems [20].
            First-generation HIT configurations have mostly been managed by HIT vendors who mainly
            focused on billing data and other administrative and operational data management
            functions (e.g., reimbursement, mandatory reporting, etc.). HIT adoption radically
            changed historic clinical workflows in an effort to standardize data inputs and system
            outputs, but this “one size fits all” approach was resisted by clinicians creating
            configuration trade-offs, workarounds, and increased system complexity.</para>
        <para>Local configurations and local coding created unique HIT features and functionality,
            which may have been needed based on hospital location or patient population, also
            created variability from hospital to hospital even within the same health network. For
            the most part, these local variations had few visible negative consequences for patients
            and health practitioners. Unfortunately, most HIT configurations did not optimize for
            patient mobility – patients who received care in non-affiliated systems or for the need
            to share precise data with other health systems, health registries, and public health
            agencies.</para>
        <para>Without new incentives, many organizations are unable to fully maintain their HIT as
            vendor maintenance contract costs continue to increase. Experienced HIT personnel have
            also become more expensive as technology companies search for qualified staff in a
            decreasing talent pool, which has led Health systems to be more dependent on vendors to
            fill the talent gap. Some under-resourced hospitals may be forced to delay system
            upgrades and updates – even important changes in terminology, clinical workflows, naming
            and coding, or other critical data quality enhancements due to concerns over system
            failures, outages, or unexpected consequences from system updates. These are real
            concerns and may lead to patient safety implications. The recent CrowdStrike
            cybersecurity update failure in 2024 caused many health systems to cancel surgeries and
            other non-critical services leading to over $2 billion in losses to healthcare
            organizations [21].</para>
        <section>
            <title>Addressing Patient Safety Gaps in the Current Health Data Ecosystem</title>
            <para>Health data is a critical component of health care decisions and can directly
                impact the treatment that patients receive, and the quality of care delivered.
                Clinical decision support systems (CDSS) depend on accurate and precise data to
                ensure decision “triggers” fire when appropriate to prevent delays in treatment or
                diagnostic errors. If important clinical information is missing sufficient context,
                decision-making can be incorrect, insufficient, or incomplete. A laboratory test
                result that is missing units of measure, reference range, or unique device
                identification may be excluded from a providers decision-making process for a
                patient, which may then prompt further testing, additional costs, and unnecessary
                patient suffering through intrusive tests. Patient history may not always be
                accurate or complete – especially when limiting data migration to a patient’s recent
                history or when sharing data from one EHR to another.</para>
            <para>Many of the errors related to encoding, sharing, and exchanging health data remain
                difficult to manage safely since institutions are mostly interested in the quality
                of the data received rather than the data sent. ASTP/ONC has developed the Trusted
                Exchange Framework and Common Agreement (TEFCA) to enhance data sharing and data
                exchange by establishing policies, governance practices, and standards aimed at
                making health data more accessible for payers, public health agencies, provider
                organizations, and patients. TEFCA will likely enhance the data sharing
                infrastructure, but it still does not currently address the quality of data being
                shared [22].</para>
            <para>Data intended to be used for research needs to possess the attributes summarized
                in the Findability, Accessibility, Interoperability, and Reusability (FAIR) Guiding
                Principles, which provide guidelines to make data findable (F), accessible (A),
                interoperable (I), and reusable (R) to the research community and machines.
                Unfortunately, a large portion of health data does not meet the FAIR Guiding
                Principles as it is often hidden in isolated data silos or incompatible systems and
                difficult to exchange, process, and interpret [23,24]. During the COVID-19 pandemic,
                leaders were unable to make informed decisions related to public health because of
                incomplete data, unstructured data, and missing data leading to preventable patient
                deaths, pandemic response delays, and unnecessary lockdowns [25].</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Spotlight Case Study #2: Interoperability and Patient Safety – A Case for a Source of Truth</title>
            <para>A source of truth, or definitive knowledge source, is needed to ensure data is
                accurate and trustworthy from the time it is encoded at the source, during
                validation, and as it is transmitted within and between HIT systems. Trustworthy
                data in turn ensures that safety management systems can operate properly and
                accurately, and governing bodies are able to rely on data and audits of appropriate
                controls to provide real time feedback.</para>
            <para>While there are multiple health data standards development and oversight
                organizations that look to act as a source of truth, each of these organizations
                have their own “standards” and lack a unifying knowledge source. Simply put, one
                patient safety use case for IKE, is the ability to identify a singular source of
                data truth that can branch across multiple organizational standards and can be
                edited or updated by a unified governing entity as new testing, devices, patient
                conditions or disease codes are discovered. Thus, as changes occur the uniform
                dictionary is updated and rapidly distributed across the healthcare ecosystem before
                preventable patient harm occurs due to missed, delayed, or incorrect
                diagnoses.</para>
            <para>Having an independent governance process and entity provides a singular,
                collaborative voice for data dictionary maintenance and development that represents
                input from not only healthcare providers, but laboratories, regulatory bodies, and
                device manufactures. In addition to defining and codifying health care information
                in an objective manner, this governing body would allow for auditing of current
                dictionary definitions to assure accuracy and consistency across the ecosystem and
                improve the safety and interoperability of data. The use of this dictionary must be
                mandatory to prevent variation and allow for concurrent audit tools that can be used
                to drive continuous process improvement. Another benefit of a rigorous governing
                body is that institutional history is maintained through a transparent manner (e.g.,
                data provenance) for future use and reference as changes need to be made or new
                definitions are required, even as potential turnover within the governance body
                occurs.</para>
            <para>Using IKE as a source of truth for health care data within the healthcare
                ecosystem will provide uniformity, consistency, and accuracy in a standardized
                format that will reduce patient harm and enhance the accuracy of clinical
                decision-making.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Spotlight Case Study #3: Data Standards and Data Quality – What Are the Patient Safety Implications?</title>
            <para>In this case, a patient is transferred from one hospital (Hospital 1), where an
                initial work-up for a potentially life-threatening condition and diagnostic testing
                was performed, to another hospital (Hospital 2) for treatment at a higher level of
                care. The subsequent treating provider at the receiving hospital reviewing the data
                contained within the patient’s EHR from the sending hospital noted a test result
                that was “out-of-range” indicating a life-threatening condition. Based upon the test
                results noted in the medical record, appropriate clinical judgement was exercised,
                and the patient was treated appropriately while further definitive imaging was being
                performed. Unbeknownst to the provider responsible for initiating orders at the
                receiving hospital (Hospital 2), the reference range for the test used at the
                hospital where the test was run (Hospital 1) was different from the one used at the
                hospital where the treatment was initiated (Hospital 2). Further, there was no flag
                to alert the treating providers at the receiving hospital to the discrepancy in
                ranges used. While a subsequent review of the patient’s initial labs from Hospital 1
                displayed as normal, those results were not immediately available or displayed in
                Hospital 2 for comparison upon initial review. Despite the use of a common EHR to
                make patient information readily accessible across care sites, different reference
                ranges for the same test resulted in incorrect provider decision making and patient
                harm. The patient experienced significant harm, resulting in prolonged
                hospitalization, additional testing, and delayed recovery from the iatrogenic error
                resulting from unnecessary treatment.</para>
            <para>Patient safety can be compromised by a lack of standard laboratory reporting
                nomenclature and interoperability. This is especially important given current
                healthcare delivery practices in which patients are frequently transferred from one
                care site to another or from one care team to another. Clinical decision making
                based on laboratory results relies on the trust that the information is complete and
                accurate, however, there is variability in laboratory test results and reference
                ranges depending upon which test is performed, on which testing device, within which
                hospital, thus posing a serious and ongoing patient safety risk. When test results
                are transmitted from one system to another, all the pertinent testing information
                (i.e., test name, standard coding, results, reference range, test type, device name,
                manufacturer, and unique device identifier) must be communicated.</para>
            <para>Using IKE for laboratory test coding creates a source of truth for HIT and
                informatics professionals to increase data accuracy, quality, and precision without
                increasing unnecessary organizational burden. Furthermore, patients would receive
                safer and higher quality care no matter where care occurs.</para>
            <para>Watch the full case study <link
                    xlink:href="https://documentsuat-cloud.cap.org/fda-shield/CAP%20video%20v18%20with%20cc.mp4?_gl=1*qerztx*_ga*MTYyNjY4NDcwNi4xNzQwNTE3Njcw*_ga_97ZFJSQQ0X*MTc0MDUxNzY3MC4xLjEuMTc0MDUxNzgzMC4wLjAuMA.."
                    >here</link>.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Spotlight Case Study #4: Analysis of Laboratory Data Transmission Between Two Healthcare Institutions Using a Widely Used Point-to-Point Health Information Exchange Platform: a Case Report</title>
            <para>The objective of this analysis was to identify information loss that could affect
                clinical care in laboratory data transmission between two health care institutions
                via a Health Information Exchange (HIE) platform. To accomplish this, data
                transmission results of 9 laboratory tests of a simulated patient, including LOINC®
                codes, were compared in the following: between sending and receiving EHR systems,
                the individual Health Level Seven International (HL7) Version 2 messages across the
                instrument, laboratory information system, and the sending EHR. The analysis found
                that the loss of information for this and similar tests indicated the following
                potential patient safety issues:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Consistently missing specimen source</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Lack of reporting of analytical technique or instrument platform</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Inconsistent units of measure and reference ranges</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Discordant LOINC® code use</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Increased data messaging complexity with multiple HL7 versions </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>This analysis showcased the challenges surrounding the completeness and accuracy
                of laboratory data exchanges in terms of the data elements required by law and the
                needed details to correctly interpret the results of the test. Additionally, this
                analysis highlighted the differences of manufacturers’ equipment (specifically in
                vitro devices) performing the same test on the same sample and the production of
                differing results. Furthermore, despite being essential for correct interpretation,
                information on the equipment manufacturer that produced the result, and the type of
                sample tested was never included in the exchange results. The study concluded that
                while the Systemic Harmonization and Interoperability Enhancement for Laboratory
                Data (SHIELD) collaborative community recommendations can be helpful − such as
                consistently including encodement information (SNOMED CT® and LOINC®), UCUM (Unified
                Codes for Units of Measure), and Unique Device Identifier (UDI) – these are partial
                steps to improving laboratory data interoperability. In tandem, EHR and Laboratory
                Information System (LIS) functionality must be standardized to allow for the
                consistent capture and transmission of relevant data elements. Usage of a HIE with
                standard messaging, SHIELD recommendations, and enhanced EHR data encoding
                functionality can yield consistent test identification and result value
                transmission.</para>
            <para>For the full study, click <link
                    xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/jamiaopen/article/7/2/ooae032/7657767"
                    >here</link>.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Spotlight Case Study #5: Establishing Trust in Pharmaceutical Data with an
                Independent Verification and Validation (IV&amp;V) Methodology</title>
            <para>In this study, researchers demonstrated a general-purpose IV&amp;V approach for
                information models, instance data, and knowledge that will enable reproducible
                metrics for data quality and patient safety. This IV&amp;V approach uses established
                statistical process control methods for inter-rater and intra-rater reliability and
                agreement metrics with Cohen’s Kappa to evaluate pharmacy prescription data being
                migrated between a legacy EHR and commercial-off-the-shelf (COTS) EHR. These methods
                are widely accepted in other industries where quality and safety are closely
                monitored, but the methods are under-utilized within the HIT industry. The research
                team demonstrated that these methods can be applied to electronic health data and
                knowledge management tasks. Researchers recommended that HIT practitioners routinely
                use bivariate comparison of reviewer agreement over an appropriately sized
                statistical sample to develop standard benchmarks for health data and knowledge
                quality and safety. A detailed description of the method is provided in this study
                along with summarized analysis findings from the application of IV&amp;V methods to
                pharmacy prescription data being migrated between EHRs.</para>
            <para>For the full study, click <link
                    xlink:href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC10148340/"
                >here</link>.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Summary</title>
        <para>Many other safety-critical industries are addressing the data quality of their safety
            information to improve safety management of their aircraft, automobiles, power plants,
            and search engines. In today’s digital healthcare ecosystem and with patients receiving
            care in diverse health settings, even at home, patient safety does not just depend upon
            highly skilled clinicians. Now, more than ever, patient safety depends on high quality
            data. Producing high quality data depends on ensuring data is accurately encoded at the
            source and exchanged or migrated without losing meaningful context for clinical decision
            making no matter where a patient receives treatment. Health informaticists and HIT
            professionals need tooling and support to ensure their organizations are producing high
            data quality. IKE can provide this tooling and support to improve health data quality so
            providers, leaders, and patients can trust their health data is safe to use.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>References</title>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Department of Veteran Affairs, Office of Inspector General. The New Electronic
                    Health </para>
                <para>Record’s Unknown Queue Caused Multiple Events of Patient Harm July 14, 2022, </para>
                <para>Report #22-01137-204</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Mitchell PH. Defining Patient Safety and Quality Care. In: Hughes RG, editor.
                    Patient </para>
                <para>Safety and Quality: An Evidence-Based Handbook for Nurses. Rockville (MD):
                    Agency </para>
                <para>for Healthcare Research and Quality (US); 2008 Apr. Chapter 1. Available from: </para>
                <para>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK2681/ </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Plebani, M. (2015). Diagnostic errors and laboratory medicine–causes and
                    strategies. </para>
                <para>JIFCCLM, 26(1), 7.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Dekker, S. (2016). Just culture: Balancing safety and accountability. CRC
                    Press.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Donaldson, M. S., Corrigan, J. M., &amp; Kohn, L. T. (Eds.). (2000). To err is
                    human: building </para>
                <para>a safer health system.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Makary, M. A., &amp; Daniel, M. (2016). Medical error—the third leading cause
                    of death in </para>
                <para>the US. BMJ, 353.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Institute of Medicine (US) Committee on Quality of Health Care in America.
                    Crossing the </para>
                <para>Quality Chasm: A New Health System for the 21st Century. Washington (DC):
                    National </para>
                <para>Academies Press (US); 2001. Available from: </para>
                <para>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK222274/ doi: 10.17226/10027</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Committee on Patient Safety and Health Information Technology; Institute of
                    Medicine. </para>
                <para>Health IT and Patient Safety: Building Safer Systems for Better Care.
                    Washington (DC): </para>
                <para>National Academies Press (US); 2011 Nov 10. PMID: 24600741.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Committee on Diagnostic Error in Health Care; Board on Health Care Services;
                    Institute </para>
                <para>of Medicine; The National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine;
                    Balogh </para>
                <para>EP, Miller BT, Ball JR, editors. Improving Diagnosis in Health Care.
                    Washington (DC): </para>
                <para>National Academies Press (US); 2015 Dec 29. Preface. Available from: </para>
                <para>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK338585/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>. Duclos, A., Frits, M. L., Iannaccone, C., Lipsitz, S. R., Cooper, Z.,
                    Weissman, J. S., &amp;</para>
                <para> Bates, D. W. (2024). Safety of inpatient care in surgical settings: cohort
                    study. BMJ, 387.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Chassin, M. R., &amp; Loeb, J. M. (2013). High‐reliability health care:
                    getting there from here. </para>
                <para>The Milbank Quarterly, 91(3), 459-490.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Weick, K. E., &amp; Sutcliffe, K. M. (2001). Managing the unexpected (Vol. 9).
                    San </para>
                <para>Francisco: Jossey-Bass.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Leveson, N., Dulac, N., Marais, K., &amp; Carroll, J. (2009). Moving beyond
                    normal accidents </para>
                <para>and high reliability organizations: A systems approach to safety in complex
                    systems. </para>
                <para>Organization studies, 30(2-3), 227-249.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Leveson, N. G. (2016). Engineering a safer world: Systems thinking applied to
                    safety (p. </para>
                <para>560). The MIT Press.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Leveson, N. G., &amp; Stephanopoulos, G. (2013). A system-theoretic,
                    control-inspired view </para>
                <para>and approach to process safety.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>. Leveson, N. G. (2023). An Introduction to System Safety Engineering. The MIT
                    Press.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Li, Y., &amp; Guldenmund, F. W. (2018). Safety management systems: A broad
                    overview of </para>
                <para>the literature. Safety science, 103, 94-123.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Kristiansen, T. B., Kristensen, K., Uffelmann, J., &amp; Brandslund, I.
                    (2022). Erroneous</para>
                <para> data: The Achilles' heel of AI and personalized medicine. Frontiers in
                    Digital Health, 4,</para>
                <para> 862095.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Office of the National Coordinator for Health Information Technology.
                    ‘National Trends in</para>
                <para> Hospital and Physician Adoption of Electronic Health Records,’ Health IT
                    Quick-Stat</para>
                <para> #61.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Alotaibi, Y. K., &amp; Federico, F. (2017). The impact of health information
                    technology on </para>
                <para>patient safety. Saudi medical journal, 38(12), 1173.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Singh, H., &amp; Sittig, D. F. (2016). Measuring and improving patient safety
                    through health </para>
                <para>information technology: The Health IT Safety Framework. BMJ quality &amp;
                    safety, 25(4), </para>
                <para>226-232.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Alder, S. (July, 2024). July 26, 2024: CrowdStrike Issues Update on Outage
                    Cause; </para>
                <para>Healthcare Hit Hardest with Estimated $1.94B in Losses. HIPAA Journal.
                    Accessed at </para>
                <para>https://www.hipaajournal.com/crowdstrike-issues-update-on-outage-cause-healthcare\u0002hit-hardest-with-estimated-1-94b-in-losses/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Mijic, M., &amp; Tripathi, M. (2024). Accelerating The Exchange Of Health And
                    Human </para>
                <para>Services Data To Improve Outcomes And Disrupt Inequities. Health Affairs
                    Forefront. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Lehne, M., Sass, J., Essenwanger, A., Schepers, J., &amp; Thun, S. (2019). Why
                    digital </para>
                <para>medicine depends on interoperability. NPJ digital medicine, 2(1), 79.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Wilkinson, M. D., Dumontier, M., Aalbersberg, I. J., Appleton, G., Axton, M.,
                    Baak, A., ... </para>
                <para>&amp; Mons, B. (2016). The FAIR Guiding Principles for scientific data
                    management and </para>
                <para>stewardship. Scientific data, 3(1), 1-9.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Fahey, R. A., &amp; Hino, A. (2020). COVID-19, digital privacy, and the social
                    limits on data\u0002focused public health responses. International Journal of
                    Information Management, 55, </para>
                <para>102181.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
</chapter>
