<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Summary of Findings – Data Collection and Transmission for FDA Medical Device Development
        Tools</title>
    <section>
        <title>Purpose</title>
        <para>Integrated Knowledge Management (IKM) is a multi-faceted approach to managing data and
            industry-wide knowledge. The primary goal of IKM in the healthcare sector is to advance
            patient health outcomes and organizational operations by improving the accuracy,
            quality, and interoperability of healthcare data. While a well-structured and
            comprehensive approach to IKM has the potential to positively impact the entire
            healthcare field, this deliverable will more specifically explore how IKM, Terminology
            Knowledge Architecture (Tinkar), and Komet can support the U.S. Food and Drug
            Administration’s (FDA’s) Medical Device Development Tools (MDDT) program and future
            submitters achieve their goals.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Background</title>
        <para>Over the last two years, our team has been working to develop an IKM reference
            implementation in the form of Komet. Komet is an application that supports comprehensive
            IKM of various healthcare terminology standards, like Logical Observation Identifiers
            Names and Codes (LOINC®), Systematized Nomenclature of Medicine Clinical Terms (SNOMED
            CT®), and RxNorm. Komet employs Terminology Knowledge Architecture (Tinkar), a
            self-describing data structure and logical model, to provide a standardized and
            repeatable way of representing these various clinical terminology standards. Tinkar can
            transform data into both Protocol Buffers (Protobuf) and the Fast Healthcare
            Interoperability Resources (FHIR) data exchange standard to export and transmit data to
            other system. To demonstrate the real-world applicability of Komet and IKM, our team
            explored how it could contribute to FDA goals. </para>
        <para>The MDDT program is an FDA initiative that aims to improve the process for device
            development, evaluation, and innovation by providing a standardized way to qualify the
            tools that medical devices use, including biomarker tests, various outcome measures,
            sensors, and more. The FDA medical device review and approval process has a variety of
            submission pathways, with a high-level overview of the overarching process outline
            below. <figure xml:id="FDADeviceSubmissionProcess">
                <title>FDA Device Submission Process</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/FDA%20Device%20Submission%20Process.svg"
                            scale="25" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>If a device uses a qualified MDDT tool, the device sponsor can ensure FDA
            approval of that specific tool without needing to undergo additional, duplicative review
            [1], IKM and Tinkar have the potential to support the MDDT program in two key
            ways:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Submitting Komet, Tinkar, and our overall IKM approach to the MDDT program as
                    a tool for review and approval to help FDA improve the predictability and
                    efficiency of medical device development and review.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Using Komet, Tinkar, and our overall IKM approach as a standardized and
                    repeatable way to represent the various qualified tools, devices, and tests
                    approved through the initiative and map them to disparate terminology
                    standards.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section> 
        <title>Komet as a Tool</title>
        <para>The MDDT program identifies four categories for submitted tools, including an “Other”
            category that assess (or supports assessment of) safety, effectiveness, or performance
            for a medical device [2]. Komet and our work could fall within this category as an
            open-source database and validation tool that ensures medical devices represent data,
            results, analytes, codes, and other critical information associated with devices in a
            standardized and accurate way. Komet could serve as a tool for a wide range of devices
            submitted to FDA via established pathways that would facilitate their review and
            approval:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="underline">501(K) submissions</emphasis>: Devices in the
                    501(k) premarket submission process argue that their device is as safe and
                    effective as an existing and equivalent device that is already on the market.
                    Using Komet and Tinkar as a database could be used to demonstrate how both
                    devices use the same, or equivalent, codes to represent the various tests,
                    analytes, results, and values being captured [3].</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="underline">FDA Premarket Approval (PMA)
                    Submissions</emphasis>: Devices in the PMA approval process possess substantial
                    risks, support human life, and/or are significantly involved in the prevention
                    of negative health outcomes in humans. Given this risk to human health and
                    safety, Komet, Tinkar, and our standardized representation of data across
                    terminology standards could validate that these devices can accurately transmit
                    encoded information to a variety of health information systems – including
                    Electronic Health Records (EHRs), Laboratory information Systems (LISs), and
                    more – without the loss of structure, meaning, or critical associated concepts.
                    Komet can be used to ensure these devices can not only capture this information
                    in their local systems but can also transmit the information to other systems
                    involved in the delivery of patient care to demonstrate their ability to meet
                    their intended purpose of protecting human life [4].</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="underline">De Novo Submissions</emphasis>: Devices in the De
                    Novo approval process represent novel medical devices that lack a comparable
                    existing device to use as a point of comparison. These devices may not have
                    existing ways to be represented using terminology standards. Komet can support
                    the creation of a novel concept that can be used to reference the device
                    submission while collecting data and performing tests. The versioning features
                    within Komet can then be used to retire the temporary concept and update it to
                    the official concepts once they have been created. Using our Status, Time,
                    Author, Module, Path (STAMP) feature, the information associated with the
                    temporary concept, the date the concept was updated, the specific information
                    that was changed when it was updated to the official concept, and more would be
                    stored and could be easily visualized in the timeline feature. As these concepts
                    continue to evolve, Komet would continue to tie critical information to the most
                    recent versions so that historical context and data is not lost [5]. </para>
            </listitem>  
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>As an MDDT, Komet could streamline the device review and approval process, reducing
            the time and resources needed to evaluate products accurately and efficiently. Komet
            would support a consistent and reliable assessment of other devices that reduces the
            time it takes to approve products. Once products have been approved, Komet could also
            continue to support standardized assessments of their safety with high-quality data
            collection and post-market surveillance that expedites 501(K) submissions, additional
            continued evaluation of devices, and more.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Standardized Representation and Transmission of Device Data</title>
        <section>
            <title>Discussion</title>
            <para>Our team explored the possibility and accuracy of end-users using Komet to author or
                edit an MDDT-related concept in Tinkar, transforming that representation into FHIR, and
                then transmitting that data to the various terminology standards to provide a way to
                represent these new tools when there is no formal or standardized concept [6]. We used
                IKM and Komet to develop Tinkar Terminology Change Sets and versioned knowledge graphs
                to provide Description Logic for terminology concept definitions. Even when there isn’t
                an official term or concept code, our Tinkar Change Sets provided an avenue to represent
                the MDDT tests, tools, and devices in a standardized way. This could serve as both a
                temporary solution, that could then be identified and mapped as an equivalent concept
                once Standards Developing Organizations (SDOs) release a formal term, or a permanent
                solution that could be submitted, validated, and released by SDOs. This document
                explores how IKM and Tinkar could support the lossless transmission of MDDT data between
                these devices and health systems, like EHRs and LISs, by normalizing the representation
                of devices, results, properties, and other pertinent information.</para>         
                <figure xml:id="FHIRTransmissionPathway">
                    <title>FHIR Transmission Pathway</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="../images/FHIR%20Transmission%20Pathway.svg" scale="25"
                                align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Results</title>
                <section>
                    <title>Performance &amp; Efficiency</title>
            <para>An implementation of the Tinkar data model includes rich semantic details for
                representing knowledge sources including but not limited to individual concepts,
                synonyms and descriptions, relationships between terms, language and dialect
                information, and description logic axioms and robust version history. This rich
                verbose data set contains complex and highly granular information. Converting this
                data into a structured format like JavaScript Object Notation (JSON) or Health Level
                Seven (HL7) FHIR can be challenging due to the intricacy and depth of the data.
                Finding equivalence between source data elements and Tinkar data elements correctly
                is crucial when converting Tinkar data into a structured format. However, this
                process can be difficult and time-consuming, particularly when dealing with complex
                data sets. Both JSON and HL7 FHIR have their own limitations. For instance, JSON
                itself isn’t as performant as alternative binary-JSON format representations and HL7
                FHIR may not cover all possible healthcare data exchange use cases and scenarios.
                These limitations can pose challenges when trying to represent a rich verbose data
                set like a Tinkar database. Our team also found variation between different
                operating systems when transforming Tinkar data to HL7 FHIR and JSON exports. </para>
                </section>
            <section>
                <title>Lossy Representation</title>
                <para>Transforming Tinkar data into JSON or HL7 FHIR risks loss of information or
                    distortion of original data. Thus, maintaining data integrity during this
                    conversion process is a challenge. One significant challenge we faced in
                    implementation of the transform to FHIR is JSON does not support all data types
                    and structures that Tinkar and the source terminologies native formats
                    represent. Therefore, when transforming data from a Tinkar data representation
                    to JSON, there is a risk of losing information that does not fit into the JSON
                    structure. While JSON can handle some complex data structures, it can struggle
                    with deeply nested structures such as description logic axiom definitions for
                    concepts. Furthermore, during the transformation process, valuable metadata
                    (such as timestamps, authorship, or source information) may be lost. This can
                    reduce the utility and context of the transformed data, especially in the
                    context of the STAMP (status, time, author, module, and path) information in
                    Tinkar at the concept-level rather than at the code system level. </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Version History Over Time</title>
                <para>Data standards are constantly evolving. The Tinkar data representation is
                    designed to retain each version of objects persisted as the object changes over
                    time, along with metadata indicating its version identifier, time of creation,
                    creating author, and branch of the version control system on which it was
                    created. Every version of each object must remain available for retrieval and
                    inspection. Keeping up with these changes and ensuring the converted data
                    remains compliant with the updated standards can be challenging, especially with
                    the lossy challenges as described above in the HL7 FHIR format. FHIR terminology
                    resources do not have a clean way of representing rich version history and
                    metadata; we are currently employing a strategy of combining together a HL7 Code
                    System FHIR Resource and HL7 Provenance FHIR Resource but there are details lost
                    such as the Module and Path and can only be exported at the Code System level
                    and not at the individual concept-level. </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Reasoning</title>
                <para>Lossy representation can lead to inefficient querying. If data is not
                    accurately represented, it can be more challenging to perform queries and gain
                    insights from the JSON data. If many concepts are updated in a Tinkar editing
                    environment, then the description logic reasoning can take a long time to
                    execute and have unintended consequences on the results. To mitigate these
                    challenges, it's crucial to plan and execute the transformation process
                    carefully, taking into consideration the data types, structures, and other
                    specific characteristics of the Tinkar database.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Future Considerations</title>
        <para>As FDA continues to mature the MDDT program, Komet and IKM could support integration
            with the Laboratory Interoperability Device Reference (LIDR), a centralized repository
            of standardized codes for laboratory tests, devices, and analyzers. Incorporating LIDR
            into the MDDT process and requiring participants to transmit their LIDR record, using
            Komet and IKM, as part of the evaluation process could support further standardization
            of laboratory device representation [7]. </para>
        <para>In the coming months, our team plans to unequivocally demonstrate that IKM, and more
            specifically Komet, provides the general authoring capabilities and features necessary
            to support LIDR and improve the quality of healthcare data. Komet will provide an
            authoring environment that can represent a wide range of healthcare systems and
            terminology standards that also supports exporting data in a FHIR format to map
            laboratory devices, tools, and results to LOINC® and other standards that LISs can use
            to represent new concepts. As part of this initiative, our team plans to perform
            extensive validation exercises at all stages of the workflow to ensure key functionality
            and data quality. This effort aligns with one of LIDR’s goals to reduce the variance in
            device representation across laboratories by automating the mapping process or placing
            the onus of device mapping on the In Vitro Diagnostic (IVD) manufacturer, including
            reference and tooling. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>References</title>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Medical Device Development Tools (MDDT) [Internet]. FDA; [cited 2024 May 17].
                    Available from: <link
                      xlink:href="https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/medical-device-development-tools-mddt"
                        >https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/medical-device-development-tools-mddt</link></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Center for Devices and Radiological Health. Medical Device Development Tools
                    (MDDT) [Internet]. FDA; [cited 2025 Apr 14]. Available from: <link
                        xlink:href="https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/medical-device-development-tools-mddt"
                        >https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/medical-device-development-tools-mddt</link></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Center for Devices and Radiological Health. Premarket notification 510(K)
                    [Internet]. FDA; [cited 2025 Apr 14]. Available from: <link
                        xlink:href="https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/premarket-submissions-selecting-and-preparing-correct-submission/premarket-notification-510k"
                        >https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/premarket-submissions-selecting-and-preparing-correct-submission/premarket-notification-510k</link></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Center for Devices and Radiological Health. Premarket approval (PMA)
                    [Internet]. FDA; [cited 2025 Apr 14]. Available from: <link
                        xlink:href="https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/premarket-submissions-selecting-and-preparing-correct-submission/premarket-approval-pma"
                        >https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/premarket-submissions-selecting-and-preparing-correct-submission/premarket-approval-pma</link></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Center for Devices and Radiological Health. De Novo Classification Request
                    [Internet]. FDA; [cited 2025 Apr 14]. Available from: <link
                        xlink:href="https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/premarket-submissions-selecting-and-preparing-correct-submission/de-novo-classification-request"
                        >https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/premarket-submissions-selecting-and-preparing-correct-submission/de-novo-classification-request</link></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>HL7 International - Terminology Infrastructure Work Group. HL7 Terminology
                    Change Set Exchange [Internet]. HL7 International; [cited 2024 May 17].
                    Available from: <link
                        xlink:href="https://build.fhir.org/ig/HL7/tinkar-ig/index.html"
                        >https://build.fhir.org/ig/HL7/tinkar-ig/index.html</link></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Merrick R. LIDR White Paper [Internet]. [cited 2024 May 17]. Available from:
                        <link
                        xlink:href="https://aphlinformatics.atlassian.net/wiki/spaces/SC/pages/2020966449/LIDR+White+Paper"
                        >https://aphlinformatics.atlassian.net/wiki/spaces/SC/pages/2020966449/LIDR+White+Paper</link></para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
</chapter>
