<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Summary of Findings - Stakeholder Feedback on Kowledge Management Use Cases (Months
        13-24)</title>
    <section>
        <title>Purpose</title>
        <para>Health Information Technology (IT) is pivotal for organizing, analyzing, and
            exchanging patient health information. Despite its potential to ease provider workload
            and enhance patient care, current clinical decision support systems exhibit
            inconsistencies that can adversely impact both patients and providers. A significant
            challenge lies in the lack of uniform encoding standards, which impedes lab data
            interoperability due to errors and inconsistencies in data transfers. The use of varying
            health data standards across different stages of the patient care lifecycle further
            complicates the delivery of care, as providers struggle with transitioning information
            between systems. This complexity is exacerbated by the diverse ways in which healthcare
            information is collected, stored, and exchanged, making it difficult to maintain data
            consistency as it moves between care providers. </para>
        <para>Thus, an integrated knowledge management framework is needed to unify all knowledge
            resources under a common representation. This framework facilitates version control,
            standardized viewing, collaborative editing, and extension development, enabling the
            creation of shared knowledge bases. These knowledge bases not only streamline laboratory
            data but also simplify the relationships across disparate knowledge standards by
            extracting and representing common elements uniformly.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Objective</title>
        <para>This document is intended to serve as a summary of major feedback received from key
            relevant parties on the prototype Integrated Knowledge Management (IKM) framework. This
            feedback was collected and synthesized from a variety of interviews conducted over the
            previous period aimed at the comprehension and digestibility of IKM.</para>
        <para>To gauge current opinions, receptivity, and general understanding of the IKM framework
            and use-cases developed, the team compiled feedback from a number of relevant parties in
            a variety of forums, most notably:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">University of Nebraska Medical Center</emphasis></para>
                <para>The relevant party interview provided valuable insights into the concept
                    authoring process and user interface of a tool. The interviewee demonstrated a
                    clear understanding of the tool's functionalities but noted confusion with
                    certain manual selections and complex features, suggesting potential cognitive
                    load issues. They emphasized the importance of a structured workflow and
                    collaboration, preferring to complete tasks in one sitting to maintain focus.
                    Challenges were identified in the validation and classification processes, as
                    well as difficulties with editing due to non-intuitive interface elements.
                    Although the tool's design and familiar interactions were appreciated,
                    significant issues with terminology, icon usability, and navigation were
                    highlighted.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Clinical Informaticist</emphasis></para>
                <para>The relevant party interviews with clinical informaticists provided valuable
                    feedback on the Knowledge Management Environment (Komet) tool's interface and
                    functionality. They appreciated the improved design and usability over previous
                    versions but stressed the need for clearer terminology and contextual guidance,
                    particularly for new users. The informaticists emphasized the importance of
                    intuitive search features, module awareness, and efficient navigation and
                    editing of concepts. They also noted the complexity of certain features, such as
                    the "patterns" concept, and called for better visual hierarchy and tooltips.
                    Overall, while the enhancements were positively received, the feedback
                    highlighted the need for continued improvements in user guidance and interface
                    clarity to better support clinical informatics workflows.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Methodology</title>
        <para>To assess the Next Gen Komet Authoring Environment, we conducted two rounds of remote,
            individual interviews with expert users. Each session, lasting between 60 and 75
            minutes, were structured around task-based evaluations, where participants engaged with
            an interactive Figma prototype. They were encouraged to verbalize their thoughts as they
            navigated the interface, providing insights into their mental models and identifying
            usability challenges. The facilitator monitored their interactions, offering guidance
            when necessary and demonstrating features when the prototype's limitations restricted
            direct engagement.</para>
        <para>During these sessions, we collected a wide array of feedback, including areas of
            confusion, initial impressions, and responses to terminology and workflows. Participants
            also provided spontaneous suggestions and ideas, enriching the feedback. The research
            was supported by tools such as Figma for the prototype experience, Zoom for facilitation
            and screen sharing, and live notetaking alongside session recordings (with participant
            consent) to ensure comprehensive documentation of insights. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Common Feedback Themes</title>
        <para>To create actionable insights from the questions, comments, and concerns that were
            brought up during these engagements, the team has categorized them into the following
            themes: ‘Workspace Interaction and Usability’, ‘Search and Navigation Functionalities’,
            and ‘Concepts’.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Workspace Interaction and Usability</title>
            <para>Workspace Interaction and Usability is the initial touchpoint for users engaging
                with Komet, playing a crucial role in shaping their first impressions and overall
                experience. It encompasses design, module and path selection, application
                navigation, and concept management. Effective usability ensures that users can
                navigate the system intuitively, enhancing satisfaction and productivity. Below is
                the feedback from relevant parties following a recent demonstration.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Module and Path Selection</title>
                <para><emphasis>Direct Feedback</emphasis></para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Module nd Path Importance:</emphasis> The
                            importance of module and path selection in setting up authoring work was
                            emphasized, with appreciation for interface improvements like clearer
                            module dropdowns.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Tooltip and Icon Clarity:</emphasis> The
                            addition of hover tooltips was appreciated, but some icons (e.g.,
                            Validator or Coordinate) were found to be non-intuitive or
                            unclear.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Notes vs. Comments:</emphasis> There was a
                            suggestion to merge or clarify Notes and Comments and improve visual
                            hierarchy for better clarity.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Module Switching Clarity</emphasis>: Users
                            demonstrated a mental model for Sandbox → Development → Production but
                            wanted more clarity on module switching and indicators for the current
                            module.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Workspace Interaction and Usability</title>
                <para><emphasis>Direct Feedback</emphasis></para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Lucidchart Comparison: </emphasis>The workspace
                            view reminded users of Lucidchart, leading to expectations for zooming,
                            panning, dragging, and visual canvas interactions.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Navigation Intuitiveness:</emphasis> While
                            navigation gestures like zoom and list toggling were intuitive, some
                            buttons (e.g., top-right arrow) were unclear due to small size or
                            missing labels. The prototype lacked full interactivity, but users
                            assumed the intended behavior correctly, indicating sound design but
                            weak User Interface (UI) cues.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Concept Management:</emphasis> Users questioned
                            whether having many concepts open was beneficial or distracting, seeking
                            clarity on what’s “active” versus “in progress.” This raises design
                            questions worth exploring for workspace management.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Key Takeaways</title>
                <para>Based on the feedback received from relevant parties regarding Concept, the
                    team has compiled key takeaways: </para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Module and Path Selection Enhancements:
                            </emphasis>The improvements in module and path selection, such as
                            clearer dropdowns and hover tooltips, were well-received. However, there
                            is a need for better clarity and intuitiveness in icon design,
                            particularly for icons like Validator and Coordinate. Additionally,
                            users suggested merging or clarifying the distinction between Notes and
                            Comments to improve visual hierarchy and understanding. There is also a
                            desire for clearer indicators and understanding of module switching,
                            especially in the context of transitioning from Sandbox to Development
                            and Production environments. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Workspace Interaction and Concept
                                Management:</emphasis> Users appreciated the intuitive navigation
                            gestures reminiscent of Lucidchart, such as zooming and panning, but
                            noted that some UI elements, like small or unlabeled buttons, could be
                            improved for better usability. The feedback highlighted a need to
                            explore the design of workspace management, particularly regarding the
                            handling of multiple open concepts and distinguishing between "active"
                            and "in progress" states. This indicates an opportunity to refine
                            workspace interactions to enhance user satisfaction and
                            productivity.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Search and Navigation Functionalities</title>
            <para>The "Search and Navigation Functionalities" section is pivotal in ensuring users
                can efficiently locate and access the information they need within Komet. By
                providing intuitive search options and seamless navigation paths, this area enhances
                user experience, reduces time spent on tasks, and boosts overall productivity. Below
                is the feedback from relevant parties regarding these functionalities following a
                recent demonstration.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Filter and Sorting</title>
                <para><emphasis>Direct Feedback</emphasis></para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Real Estate Concerns: </emphasis>Users found the
                            duplicated listing of display names and fully qualified names in search
                            results to be space-consuming without providing additional value.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Sorting Confusion: </emphasis>The distinction
                            between “Top Component” and “Matched Description Semantic” was unclear,
                            with alphabetical sorting being the only consistently useful
                            option.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Workflow Importance:</emphasis> Search is
                            central to users' workflows, primarily used to determine if a new
                            concept is needed or if an existing one can be extended.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Exact Match Issues:</emphasis> There was
                            criticism that exact matches do not always appear at the top of search
                            results.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Active vs. Retired Concepts:</emphasis> Users
                            want the default search results to show only active concepts, with an
                            option to toggle and review retired concepts for historical
                            insight.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Terminology Confusion: </emphasis>Terms like
                            “top component,” “matched description,” and “semantic” were confusing,
                            leading users to experiment by clicking around to understand sorting
                            methods.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Discoverability Issues:</emphasis> Users found
                            the module filter only through a process of elimination, suggesting a
                            need for clearer labels or inline guidance.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Hierarchy Presentation Issues</title>
                <para><emphasis>Direct Feedback</emphasis></para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Visual Confusion: </emphasis>The visual
                            representation of hierarchy was unclear, with questions about the
                            meaning behind the angles of lines and the presence of circles. There
                            was difficulty in understanding how polyhierarchy and multi-parenting
                            were depicted.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Polyhierarchial Expections:</emphasis> There was
                            an expectation for polyhierarchy to display all parent paths, but it
                            seemed that only one path was shown, leading to confusion.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Navigation Needs: </emphasis>There is a desire
                            for a visual Systematized Nomenclature of Medicine
                                (SNOMED<superscript>®</superscript>) hierarchy that allows users to
                            easily navigate parent-child relationships without needing to know exact
                            terms.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Logical Subdivisions: </emphasis>Chapters are
                            seen as logical subdivisions within a project, organizing content into
                            categories like Obstetrics and Gynecology (OB-GYN) or cardiology.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Hierarchy Interpretation:</emphasis> Users
                            accurately interpreted Project Journals as large workspaces or
                            initiatives, with Chapters as sub-tasks or topic-specific
                            workstreams.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Additional Features</title>
                <para><emphasis>Direct Feedback</emphasis></para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Completion Matching:</emphasis> Users strongly
                            recommended implementing completion matching, such as typing "tet fal"
                            to return "Tetralogy of Fallot."</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Favorites Feature:</emphasis> The idea of
                            marking frequently used concepts as favorites was well-received.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Screen Space Concerns:</emphasis> The
                            "description semantics" panel in search results was seen as taking up
                            too much screen space, distracting from important tasks like reviewing
                            axiom relationships.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Key Takeaways</title>
                <para>Based on the feedback received from relevant parties regarding Search and
                    Navigation Functionalities, the team has compiled key takeaways: </para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Search and Sorting Challenges: </emphasis>Users
                            face confusion and inefficiencies with the current search and sorting
                            functionalities. Issues include the unclear distinction between sorting
                            options like "Top Component" and "Matched Description Semantic," and the
                            lack of prioritization for exact matches in search results.
                            Additionally, the duplicated display of names and fully qualified names
                            is seen as unnecessary and space-consuming. Users also expressed a need
                            for the default search to focus on active concepts, with an option to
                            view retired ones.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Hierarchy and Navigation improvements:
                            </emphasis>The visual representation of hierarchies is unclear, causing
                            confusion about polyhierarchical structures and navigation paths. Users
                            expect a more intuitive display of parent-child relationships and
                            logical subdivisions within projects. The current system's inability to
                            clearly show all parent paths in polyhierarchies and the lack of a
                            user-friendly visual SNOMED<superscript>®</superscript> hierarchy are
                            significant areas for improvement. Additionally, clearer labels or
                            inline guidance for filters and navigation tools are needed to enhance
                            discoverability and user experience.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Concepts</title>
            <para>The "Concepts" section is integral to managing and understanding the complex data
                structures within Komet. It includes Change History/Version Control, Axiom
                Visibility and Concept Management, Relationship Modeling, and Terminology. These
                functionalities ensure accurate tracking of changes, clear visibility into data
                structures, and effective management of relationships and terminology. Together,
                they enhance data integrity and facilitate informed decision-making. Below is the
                feedback from relevant parties regarding these functionalities following a recent
                demonstration.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Change History "Time Travel Feature"</title>
                <para><emphasis>Direct Feedback</emphasis></para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Version Tracking Appeal:</emphasis> Users
                            appreciated the concept of version tracking across time and extensions,
                            noting it as superior to current tools.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Timeline Clarity:</emphasis> Users struggled to
                            understand changes in the timeline and how to interpret green dots and
                            labels.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Comparison Needs:</emphasis> There is a desire
                            for side-by-side comparisons and clearer visual cues to highlight
                            differences.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Appreciation for Functionality:</emphasis> The
                            feature was described as "slick" for comparing changes, especially for
                            evolving concepts.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Collaboration Use Case:</emphasis> It is
                            particularly useful when multiple people are collaborating or editing a
                            term, such as when a graduate student makes changes.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Color Coding: </emphasis>Users liked the ability
                            to see edits across different extensions, such as
                                SNOMED<superscript>®</superscript> Clinical Terminology (CT), US
                            Extension, and Primordial Path, through color coding.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Content Specificity: </emphasis>The feature is
                            seen as clever and potentially useful, particularly for user-authored
                            content rather than standardized terms.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Screen Real Estate:</emphasis> It was suggested
                            that the feature should collapse by default to avoid occupying too much
                            screen space.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Overuse Concers:</emphasis> For long-established
                                SNOMED<superscript>®</superscript> content, the feature may not
                            always be necessary, but it is potentially more beneficial for
                            user-created content.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Intuitive Navigation:</emphasis> While users
                            appreciated the potential to compare across extensions like
                                SNOMED<superscript>®</superscript> and Logical Observation
                            Identifiers, Names, and Codes (LOINC<superscript>®</superscript>), the
                            process was not intuitive.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Axiom Visibility and Concept Management</title>
                <para><emphasis>Direct Feedback</emphasis></para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Axiom Display: </emphasis>Users appreciated the
                            prominent and clean display of axioms, considering it a significant
                            improvement in the interface.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Duplication Feature: </emphasis>The ability to
                            duplicate a concept was valued as a shortcut for authoring related
                            content efficiently.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Concept Editing:</emphasis> Users believe that
                            editing a Fully Qualified Name should be restricted to user-authored
                            content, not SNOMED<superscript>®</superscript> originals. The
                            interaction of clicking directly into the name field was seen as
                            innovative but not immediately obvious.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Children Concepts View:</emphasis> There was an
                            expectation to view children of a concept within the same interface or
                            have easy navigation options to access them.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Relationship Modeling and Terminology</title>
                <para><emphasis>Direct Feedback</emphasis></para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">"Is-a" Relationship:</emphasis> Establishing an
                            “Is-a” relationship early in the modeling process was deemed crucial,
                            with users typically starting by defining a parent relationship before
                            adding more complex logic or attributes.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Necessary vs. Sufficient Sets:</emphasis> Users
                            generally do not distinguish between necessary and sufficient sets,
                            preferring to focus on what is both necessary and sufficient. The UI's
                            requirement for explicit axiom type selection was questioned, as
                                SNOMED<superscript>®</superscript> determines whether a concept is
                            primitive or fully defined by logic.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Advanced User Needs:</emphasis> While separating
                            necessary and sufficient sets might benefit advanced users, most
                            modelers do not require this complexity.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Property Set Unfamiliarity:</emphasis> The term
                            “property set” was unfamiliar, with speculation that it might refer to a
                            template or reusable pattern for defining concepts.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Parent Concept Selection: </emphasis>Users
                            emphasized the need for clearer cues and better semantic context when
                            selecting parent concepts, especially in distinguishing between similar
                            categories like congenital diseases or anomalies.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Key Takeaways</title>
                <para>Based on the feedback received from relevant parties regarding Concept, the
                    team has compiled key takeaways: </para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Change History and Version Control
                                Enhancements:</emphasis> The "Time Travel Feature" for version
                            tracking is highly appreciated for its ability to track changes across
                            time and extensions, offering superior functionality compared to
                            existing tools. However, users face challenges with timeline clarity and
                            interpreting visual cues like green dots and labels. There is a strong
                            desire for side-by-side comparisons and clearer visual indicators to
                            highlight differences. While the feature is beneficial for collaborative
                            editing and user-authored content, concerns about screen space and
                            intuitive navigation remain, suggesting areas for improvement.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Axiom Visibilty and Relatinship Modeling Needs:
                            </emphasis>Users value the clean display of axioms and the ability to
                            duplicate concepts for efficient authoring. However, there is a need for
                            clearer interaction cues, especially for editing Fully Qualified Names,
                            which should be restricted to user-authored content. In relationship
                            modeling, establishing an “Is-a” relationship early is crucial, but the
                            distinction between necessary and sufficient sets is not commonly made
                            by users, indicating a potential simplification of the UI. Additionally,
                            clearer semantic cues are needed for parent concept selection to aid
                            users in distinguishing between similar categories.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <para>The feedback gathered from key relevant parties on the IKM framework provides valuable
            insight for refining future iterations of the prototype. Relevant parties, including
            representatives from the University of Nebraska Medical Center and clinical
            informaticists, highlighted both strengths and areas for improvement in the framework.
            The feedback underscored the need for a more intuitive user interface and clearer
            terminology to reduce cognitive load and enhance user experience. The reviewers praised
            the framework's design and usability improvements but emphasized the necessity of
            structured workflows and collaborative features to facilitate efficient task completion.
            The identification of challenges in validation and classification processes, as well as
            navigation difficulties, illuminate the need for ongoing enhancements to support
            seamless user interaction.</para>
        <para> This feedback is instrumental in driving the iterative development process of the IKM
            framework. By addressing the highlighted issues, such as the complexity of certain
            features and the need for better visual hierarchy and tooltips, the development team can
            enhance the framework's usability and functionality. Ultimately, feedback gathered will
            lead to a more robust and user-friendly IKM framework that effectively unifies knowledge
            resources, streamlines laboratory data, and simplifies the integration of disparate
            knowledge standards, thereby improving data consistency and interoperability in
            healthcare settings.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
