<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Tinkar Modeling Guide </title>
    <section>
        <title><anchor xml:id="Toc196843725"/>Introduction</title>
        <para>Biomedical terminologies are increasingly important resources for knowledge
            management, data integration, and decision support across healthcare contexts. The
            growing use of digital health data is accelerating the adoption of standard
            terminologies such as SNOMED CT®, LOINC®, and RxNorm. The interoperability of digital
            health data requires that healthcare organizations integrate subsets and modules of
            various reference terminologies and manage dependencies, versions, and new releases. As
            a result, there is a need for standardized representation of concepts that includes
            change management capabilities.</para>
        <para>This section focuses on how the Terminology Knowledge Architecture (Tinkar) addresses
            the need for standardized semantics with versioning. The modeling guide establishes the
            processes and outputs for modeling domain Concepts in the Tinkar specification. The
            guide explains the data interoperability requirements Tinkar is intended to address,
            provides an overview of the Tinkar Modeling Process, and describes how the model can be
            applied to a unique data set. The Tinkar Modeling Guide does not encompass all the
            information regarding the Tinkar Reference Model. Therefore, it is encouraged to review
            the <link
                xlink:href="https://www.hl7.org/documentcenter/private/standards/HL7_LM_TERM_KB_R1_INFORM_2021AUG_FINAL.pdf"
                xml:id="menurafr">HL7 informative ballot</link> to supplement this guide.</para>
        <section>
        <title><anchor xml:id="Toc196843726"/>What is Tinkar?</title>
        <para>Tinkar is a logical model designed to establish a robust knowledge architecture. Its
            primary goal is to integrate local systems with medical and laboratory terminologies
            like SNOMED CT®, LOINC®, RxNorm, etc., facilitating effective communication of clinical
            information across multiple systems. Tinkar is intended to support health care
            organizations’ standard terminology modules, value sets, and coding systems, as well as
            local terms and equivalence mappings. This allows organizations to tailor their
            terminology standards to specific needs. Enterprises can extend their terminology
            standards and rapidly implement extensions, enabling swift adaptation to evolving
            healthcare requirements.</para></section>
        <section>
            <title><anchor xml:id="Toc196843727"/>Why Tinkar</title>
            <para>Information systems across healthcare record and manage clinical data using
                clinical statements and clinical terminologies in non-standardized ways.
                Interoperability specifications aim to require terminology bindings to Concepts,
                code systems, and reusable value sets. There is currently variation in clinical data
                exchange across the enterprise as existing payloads and clinical statements use
                inconsistent and highly variable enterprise terminologies. Managing the Concepts,
                code systems, and value sets is complex because developers, implementers, and end
                users are forced to handle unnecessary complexity. For example:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>In the representation of medication, RxNorm codes overlap with CVX codes.
                        Investigational vaccines from the FDA are not represented in RxNorm, CVX, or
                        SNOMED CT®.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>In the representation of COVID-19, result codes are inconsistent and are
                        not equivalent (e.g., detected, undetected, positive, negative,
                        etc.).</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        </section>
    <section>
        <title><anchor xml:id="Toc196843728"/>Tinkar Logical Model</title>
        <para>Before representing a data set using the Tinkar Logical Model, it is essential to
            understand the Tinkar starter data of Concepts, Patterns, and Semantics. The goal is to
            use what already exists in Tinkar and only create new Components when needed. This
            section provides a basic overview of the Tinkar Logical Model. The full description of
            the logical model is in the HL7 ballot, linked in the Introduction of this
            document.</para>
        <para>
            <figure xml:id="TinkarLogicalModelExample">
                <title>Tinkar Logical Model</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata
                            fileref="../images/Tinkar%20Logical%20Model%20Example.svg"
                            scale="25" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </para>
        <para>The Tinkar Logical Model consists of three main Components: a Concept, a Pattern, and
            a Semantic. These Components ensure that data is consistently processed across different
            systems by defining the context and relationships of the data elements. This helps
            maintain uniformity in data interpretation, which is crucial for effective
            interoperability. The model can represent any knowledge standard, while still allowing
            for traceability and transparency of the data.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Components</title>
            <para>The main objects in Tinkar are called Components. There are three distinct types:
                Concepts, Patterns, and Semantics. Every Component in Tinkar is represented by an
                array of at least one Universally Unique Identifier (UUID). A Component can be
                represented by multiple UUIDs if derived from multiple sources. For example, the
                Concept Acetaminophen, which exists in SNOMED CT®, LOINC®, and RxNorm, could have a
                UUID from each terminology and be represented as an array of UUIDs for this single
                Concept within a Tinkar implementation.</para>
            <para>Every Component consists of a set of change records called Component Versions.
                Each version has an associated STAMP (Status, Time, Author, Module, Path).</para>
            <section>
                <title>Concepts</title>
                <para>A Concept in Tinkar is a Component identified using Universally Unique
                    Identifiers (UUIDs) and a STAMP. It contains only the information within the
                    STAMP. Concepts have no emergent meaning. For example, Acetaminophen can be
                    represented by attaching the description ‘Acetaminophen’ to a Concept with a
                    UUID and no other additional information. Additional information is provided by
                    Semantics. The specific meaning, purpose, and data elements of a Semantic are
                    defined by a Pattern. </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title><anchor xml:id="Toc196843731"/>Patterns</title>
                <para>A Pattern is created to make a new table and describes the fields and field
                    types for the table, similar to a database. A Pattern is a Component that
                    contains a Semantic Meaning, Semantic Purpose, and possibly a set of field
                    definitions. A field definition has its own purpose, meaning, and datatype.
                    These field types describe what type of information and what format the data in
                    a Semantic following in this Pattern will be. The field definitions are
                    equivalent to defining the columns in a database table. Using the Pattern,
                    Semantics with varying fields and field types can be specified to represent any
                    structure needed to provide meaning to a Component. There are three key Patterns
                    used to represent terminologies via Tinkar: the Description Pattern, the
                    Identifier Pattern, and the Stated Definition Pattern. The table below
                    illustrates the Description Pattern as an example. The Description Pattern is
                    one of the three key Tinkar Patterns. It has four different fields, each with
                    associated field definitions. </para>
                <table>
                    <title>Description Pattern</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Description Pattern</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Semantic Meaning</entry>
                                <entry>Description Semantic</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Semantic Purpose</entry>
                                <entry>Description Semantic</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Field 1: Language</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Meaning</entry>
                                <entry>Language for Description</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Purpose</entry>
                                <entry>Language</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Field Type</entry>
                                <entry>Component Field</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Field 2: Description</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Meaning</entry>
                                <entry>Text for Description</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Purpose</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Field Type</entry>
                                <entry>String</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Field 3: Description Case
                                    Significance</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Meaning</entry>
                                <entry>Description Case Significance</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Purpose</entry>
                                <entry>Description Case Significance</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Field Type</entry>
                                <entry>Component Field</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Field 4: Description
                                    Type</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Meaning</entry>
                                <entry>Description Type</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Purpose</entry>
                                <entry>Description Type</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Field Type</entry>
                                <entry>Component Field</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <para>The meaning and purpose Concepts shown in the above table for the Description
                    Pattern are also types of Concepts in Tinkar, each with its own definitions. The
                    table below shows the definition for the meaning and purpose Concepts from the
                    Description Pattern table. Note how sometimes the meaning and the purpose is the
                    same.</para>
                <table>
                    <title>Description Pattern Meaning and Purpose Concepts</title>
                    <tgroup cols="4">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                        <colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Pattern Field</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Concept </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition </emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry morerows="1"><emphasis role="bold"
                                        >Description</emphasis><emphasis role="bold">
                                        Semantic</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Semantic Meaning</entry>
                                <entry>Description Semantic </entry>
                                <entry>Purpose and meaning for the description Pattern and dialect
                                    Patterns</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Semantic Purpose</entry>
                                <entry>Description Semantic </entry>
                                <entry>Purpose and meaning for the description Pattern and dialect
                                    Patterns</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry morerows="1"><emphasis role="bold">Field 1:
                                        Language</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Meaning</entry>
                                <entry>Language for Description </entry>
                                <entry>The Semantic value indicating which language is used in the
                                    description text</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Purpose</entry>
                                <entry>Language </entry>
                                <entry>Specifies the language of the description text.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry morerows="1"><emphasis role="bold">Field 2:
                                        Description</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Meaning</entry>
                                <entry>Text for Description</entry>
                                <entry>Captures the human readable text for a description in
                                    Komet</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Purpose</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Human readable text for a Concept</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry morerows="1"><emphasis role="bold">Field 3: Description Case
                                        Significance</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>Meaning</para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>Description Case Significance </entry>
                                <entry>Specifies how to handle the description text in terms of case
                                    sensitivity</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Purpose</entry>
                                <entry>Description Case Significance </entry>
                                <entry>Specifies how to handle the description text in terms of case
                                    sensitivity</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry morerows="1"><emphasis role="bold">Field 4: Description
                                        Type</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Meaning</entry>
                                <entry>Description Type </entry>
                                <entry>Specifying what type of description, e.g., fully qualified,
                                    or regular, etc.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Purpose</entry>
                                <entry>Description Type </entry>
                                <entry>Specifying what type of description, e.g., fully qualified,
                                    or regular, etc. </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title><anchor xml:id="Toc196843732"/>Semantics</title>
                <para>To give machine-readable meaning to Components, Tinkar uses Semantics. A
                    Semantic is a Component that contains a set of fields about the subject (the
                    meaning and purpose defined by its Pattern). A Semantic provides meaning to the
                    Components it references through its fields. A Semantic supports the
                    specification of value sets, compositional definitions, and other Components
                    requiring internal structure, and it specifies the nature of the compositional
                    relationship explicitly. </para>
                <para>A Semantic contains the data values, the referenced Pattern, and potentially
                    multiple fields depending on the referenced Pattern. The referenced Component is
                    the Component that is getting assigned the values in the fields. If table 1
                    represents the Pattern, the records inside that table are the Semantics. The
                    referenced Pattern defines exactly how many fields a Semantic must have and
                    their data type. The values in a field must match the corresponding field type
                    defined in the field definition from the Pattern. If a Pattern has no field
                    definitions, then a Semantic of that Pattern will have no fields. These are
                    referred to as Membership Patterns and Semantics.</para>
                <para>For example, the Concept of Acute Pelvic Pain requires additional information
                    to accurately describe it. This information is all asserted by one or more
                    Semantics of one or more Patterns (possibly multiple descriptions, a logical
                    definition, etc.). Examples of such assertions include descriptions of the
                    Concept, its fully qualified name, and unique relationships associated with the
                    Concept.</para>
                <para>
                    <figure xml:id="TinkarArchitectureModel">
                        <title>Tinkar Architecture Model</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata
                                    fileref="../images/Tinkar%20Architecture%20Model.svg"
                                    scale="75" align="center"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>STAMP</title>
            <para>The STAMP in the Tinkar Reference Model allows for capturing a complete change
                record of all changes to a Component. It includes the Status, Time, Author, Module,
                and Path. As a model changes and evolves, changes are made in Components. With each
                change, a new change record and a new STAMP Coordinate are created. To track
                information like when and who made the changes, a STAMP is assigned to each version
                to record and preserve the history.</para>
            <para>The following describes each of these attributes:</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis> – A status is identified by a Concept and
                may be annotated with additional information. For example, inactive or active. The
                tables below show the parent and children Concepts aligned to Status.</para>
            <table>
                <title>Status Parent Concept</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Parent Concept </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Status Value </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>The status represented by the STAMP (Active, Cancelled, Inactive,
                                Premundane, Withdrawn)</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <table>
                <title>Status Children Concepts</title>
                <tgroup cols="4">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                    <colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Children Concept </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Business Rules</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Use Case Example</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Premundane Status</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Concept used to represent the original default status when
                                creating a Concept that has not transitioned to a different
                                status.</entry>
                            <entry>In the Premundane status, Components can move to the Active or
                                Cancelled statuses. Since primordial Components were never committed
                                to a database, they cannot be move to the Inactive or Withdrawn
                                statuses.</entry>
                            <entry>When a new Component has been created but nothing is assigned nor
                                has it been approved, it would have a Premundane status.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Canceled Status</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Concept used to represent a status for Components that are
                                canceled. This means it was never successfully committed to the
                                database. This state would be local only, and transient. It will
                                eventually be removed from memory and will not propagate from one
                                database to another.</entry>
                            <entry>The Cancelled status is a terminal status, meaning it cannot be
                                moved from the Cancelled status back to a different status.</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>If a new Component is:</para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Created accidentally</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Created initially in the Premundane status but is
                                            deemed unnecessary </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                                <para>It would be moved to Cancelled status. </para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Active Status</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Concept used to represent a status for Components that are
                                active.</entry>
                            <entry>In the Active status, Components can move to the Inactive status
                                if a Component is no longer active, or it can move to the Withdraw
                                status if the Component is realized to be a mistake.</entry>
                            <entry>A Component that was in Premundane status that has been fully
                                reviewed and vetted will move to the Active status.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Inactive Status</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Concept used to represent a status for Components that are no
                                longer active. This can be due to many reasons including the model
                                changing or the Component was made obsolete by a new one.</entry>
                            <entry>In the Inactive status, Components can move to the Withdrawn
                                status, if the Component is realized to be a mistake. In special
                                circumstances with a good business reason, Components may be moved
                                from Inactive back to Active.</entry>
                            <entry>If a Component committed to the Active status is no longer
                                needed, it would be moved to the Inactive Status. </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Withdrawn Status </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Concept used to represent a status for Components that are
                                withdrawn. This indicates that a Component was successfully
                                released, but that the Component’s release was a mistake, and all
                                references to a withdrawn Component should be reassigned. </entry>
                            <entry>The Withdrawn status is a terminal status. </entry>
                            <entry>If a Component was accidentally created and committed to the
                                Active status, it would be moved to the Withdrawn status.</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>When representing a new data set using the Tinkar Reference Model, only the status
                values above are allowed and must follow the business rules defined. The business
                rules do not account for the accidental moving of a Component. The diagram below
                shows the mapping between each status.</para>
            <para>
                <figure xml:id="StatusDiagram">
                    <title>Status Diagram</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata
                                fileref="../images/Status%20Diagram.svg"
                                scale="100" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </para>
            <para> </para>
            <para>If the data set has additional status values beyond these five, such as the LOINC®
                Discouraged Status, they should be represented using an additional Pattern and
                Semantic. The STAMP status values must not be extended beyond the provided starter
                set. For example, using the LOINC® Discouraged Status, the status would be Active
                since it is in use. However, a Semantic would also be assigned to indicate it was
                Discouraged, capturing that additional information.</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Time </emphasis>– The timestamp is captured with precision
                and a time zone. The table below shows the parent Concept aligned to Time.</para>
            <table>
                <title>Time Parent Concept</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Parent Concept </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Time </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>The timestamp is capture with precision and a time zone</para>
                                <para> </para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Author – </emphasis>The author represents the author
                responsible for authoring the change. An author is identified by a Concept and may
                be annotated with additional information. The tables below show the parent Concept
                aligned to Author.</para>
            <table>
                <title>Author Parent Concept</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Parent Concept </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Author </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>The author represents the author responsible for authoring the
                                change. An author is identified by a Concept and may be annotated
                                with additional information. </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Module </emphasis>– The module assigns the appropriate
                terminology (e.g., LOINC®) or terminology Component (SNOMED CT®). A module is
                identified by a Concept and may be annotated with additional information. The tables
                below show the parent and children Concepts aligned to Module.</para>
            <table>
                <title>Module Parent Concept</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Parent Concept </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Module</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>The module assigns the appropriate terminology (e.g., LOINC®) or
                                terminology Component (SNOMED CT®). A module is identified by a
                                Concept and may be annotated with additional information, such as
                                organizing content for maintenance and publication purposes.</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <table>
                <title>Module Child Concept</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Child Concept </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Primordial Module</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>The default module assigned prior to creating other module
                                Concepts. The primordial module is reserved for the starter set
                                information that all Tinkar Reference Models require. Information
                                that is specific to a particular data set (i.e., SNOMED CT®) should
                                be contained in a module specific to that data set (i.e., a SNOMED
                                CT® module)</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Path –</emphasis> The path specifies version control within
                a development lifecycle, such as development, testing, staging, or production. A
                path is identified by a Concept and may be annotated with additional information.
                The tables below show the parent and children Concepts aligned to Path. <anchor
                    xml:id="Ref168991129"/></para>
            <table>
                <title>Path Parent Concept</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Parent Concept </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Path</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A set of assets under version control that can be managed
                                distinctly from other assets. Paths branch from other paths when
                                established and can also be merged with other paths. <anchor
                                    xml:id="Ref168991135"/></entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <table>
                <title>Path Children Concepts in the starter set. Additional paths may be created as
                    need to organize development activities appropriately for a particular purpose
                    (sandbox paths, feature paths, …)</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Children Concept </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Prerequisite Path</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A path that contains Components that are shared across all paths
                                and includes infrastructure Components.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Master Path</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A default path branch for Components. This path represents the
                                published Components in production.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Release</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A path branch for Components under release. Once in this path,
                                only minor changes such as bug fixes, documentation generation, and
                                other release-oriented tasks can be added.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Development Path</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A path branch that specifies that the Components are currently
                                under development.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Sandbox Path</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A path branch for Components under testing.</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>
                <figure xml:id="PathDiagram">
                    <title>Path Diagram</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata
                                fileref="../images/Path%20Diagram.svg"
                                scale="100" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </para>
            <para>Figure 3 illustrates the relationship between the five main paths detailed in
                Table 10 through which the project flows. The project begins in the Prerequisite
                Path, incorporating essential infrastructure Components shared across all paths. The
                established Components of the Prerequisite Path then move into the Master Path to
                create the first version of the project, known as Master 1. Rather than using a
                single path to showcase project flow, the Master and Development Paths record the
                project's history. The Master Path stores the official release history, while the
                Development Path serves as an integration branch for developing changes or features.
                Features are tested in the Sandbox Path, and approved Components are integrated into
                new project developments. Once a development has acquired sufficient Components for
                a new release, the project merges into the Release Path, signifying a release cycle
                where only minor changes, such as bug fixes, documentation generation, and other
                release-oriented tasks, can be added. When ready for official release, the project
                merges with the Master Path, creating a new version known as Master 2. This released
                Master 2 merges back into the Development Path, allowing the project to progress
                into the next phase of development.</para>
            <section>
                <title><anchor xml:id="Toc196843734"/>STAMP Progression Examples in Component
                    Versions</title>
                <para>To understand how STAMPs are assigned to Component versions, the examples
                    below illustrate STAMP functions and the design process behind them. </para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Example 1: Proposing a new
                            SNOMED CT® Regular Name (Synonym) locally</emphasis></emphasis></para>
                <para>In this example, a new Regular Name description for a SNOMED CT® Concept as a
                    local extension is proposed. Since a new Semantic is being created, the new
                    Component version requires a STAMP. In this example, the following parts are
                    assigned:</para>
                <table>
                    <title>STAMP Example 1</title>
                    <tgroup cols="3">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">STAMP</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field Value</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field Reasoning</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Active</entry>
                                <entry>Status is set to Active since the Semantic should be active
                                    and visible.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Time</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Current Date Time</entry>
                                <entry>The date and time when the Semantic was created.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Author</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>User Account</entry>
                                <entry>The specific user account as a Tinkar Concept should be
                                    assigned.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Module</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Local Extension Module to SNOMED CT®</entry>
                                <entry>This is a local extension, not any official SNOMED CT®
                                    release.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Path</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Development Path</entry>
                                <entry>This is a proposal for the new Semantic and not an officially
                                    reviewed Semantic.</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Example 2: Testing different
                            Pattern designs for approval and moving forward with
                        one</emphasis></emphasis></para>
                <para>In this example, three different Patterns to simulate storing experimental
                    data in various ways are tested. These can be sent to another user who decides
                    which Pattern they prefer and proposes to keep it while discarding the
                    others.</para>
                <para>Initially, all three Patterns have similar STAMP assignments:</para>
                <table>
                    <title>STAMP Example 2</title>
                    <tgroup cols="3">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">STAMP</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field Value</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field Reasoning</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Active</entry>
                                <entry>Status is set to Active since the Semantic should be active
                                    and visible.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Time</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Current Date Time</entry>
                                <entry>The date and time when the Semantic was created.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Author</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>User Account</entry>
                                <entry>The specific user account as a Tinkar Concept should be
                                    assigned. For this example, ‘Author 1’ is used.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Module</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Experimental Data Module</entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>The Unique Module to specify the domain or data set that
                                        is being used.</para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Path</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Sandbox Path</entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>The proposed Patterns are made for testing the data. They
                                        are not official or in development yet.</para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <para>A second person may review these testing Patterns and, upon selecting a
                    preferred design, update the Patterns to new versions, reflecting their decision
                    in the STAMP for those Pattern versions.</para>
                <para>The Pattern selected for retention:</para>
                <table>
                    <title>Example STAMP Pattern to Keep</title>
                    <tgroup cols="3">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">STAMP</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field Value</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field Reasoning</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Active</entry>
                                <entry>Status is set to Active since the Semantic should be active
                                    and visible.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Time</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Current Date Time</entry>
                                <entry>The date and time when the Semantic was created.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Author</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>User Account</entry>
                                <entry>The second person who chose the Pattern or ‘Author
                                    2’.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Module</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Experimental Data Module</entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>The Unique Module to specify the domain or data set that
                                        is being used.</para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Path</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Development Path</entry>
                                <entry>The proposed Pattern has moved into development and is
                                    waiting for official approval before it can be moved to the
                                    ‘Master Path.’</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <para>The Pattern selected for removal:</para>
                <table>
                    <title>Example STAMP Pattern to Remove</title>
                    <tgroup cols="3">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">STAMP</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field Value</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field Reasoning</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Inactive</entry>
                                <entry>The status is changed to inactive since the users will no
                                    longer use these Patterns.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Time</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Current Date Time</entry>
                                <entry>The date and time when the Semantic was created.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Author</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>User Account</entry>
                                <entry>The second person who chose the Pattern or ‘Author
                                    2’.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Module</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Experimental Data Module</entry>
                                <entry>The Unique Module to specify the domain or data set that is
                                    being used.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Path</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Sandbox Path</entry>
                                <entry>The proposed Patterns are still testing Patterns and not
                                    official or in development.</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title><anchor xml:id="Toc196843735"/>Tinkar Representation Examples</title>
            <para>This section highlights examples of how common medical tests can be represented in
                Tinkar. The examples demonstrate how tests currently represented in both SNOMED CT®
                and LOINC® terminologies can be modeled in the Tinkar Logical Model.</para>
            <section>
                <title><anchor xml:id="Toc196843736"/>Ex. 1 Urine Homocysteine</title>
                <para>Figure 4 illustrates a Urine Homocysteine Test represented in the Tinkar
                    Logical Model. The Concept contains both the description for the test as well as
                    its corresponding UUID. This Concept serves as the subject for further
                    classification. The Pattern uses field definitions to explain and categorize the
                    corresponding Semantic fields. For example, LOINC® records the interval of time
                    over which an observation is made. The time to conduct a Urine Homocysteine Test
                    is 24 hours. Therefore, under the Time Field Definition within the LOINC®
                    Pattern, the corresponding Semantic field would be 24H. While there are separate
                    Patterns and Semantics for both SNOMED CT® and LOINC® terminologies, they are
                    both connected to the original Concept. </para>
                <para><figure xml:id="UrineHomocysteineRepresentationinTinkar">
                        <title>Urine Homocysteine Representation in Tinkar</title>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata fileref="../images/Urine%20Homocysteine%20Representation%20in%20Tinkar.svg"
                                        scale="100" align="center"/> 
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title><anchor xml:id="Toc196843737"/>Ex. 2 Substance concentration of glucose in
                    specimen at point in time</title>
                <para>Figure 5 illustrates a Substance Concentration of Glucose in Specimen Test
                    represented in the Tinkar Logical Model. The Concept contains both the
                    description for the test as well as its corresponding UUID. This Concept serves
                    as the subject for further classification. The Pattern uses field definitions to
                    explain and categorize the corresponding Semantic fields. For example, this test
                    involves measuring the concentration of glucose in a given specimen. Therefore,
                    under the Method field definition within the SNOMED CT® Pattern, the
                    corresponding Semantic field would be Measurement – action. While there are
                    separate Patterns and Semantics for both SNOMED CT® and LOINC® terminologies,
                    they are both connected to the original Concept.</para>
                <figure xml:id="SubstanceConcentrationofGlucoseinSpecimeninTinkar">
                    <title>Substance Concentration of Glucose in Specimen in Tinkar</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="../images/Substance%20Concentration%20of%20Glucose%20in%20Specimen%20in%20Tinkar.svg"
                                scale="100" align="center"/> 
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title><anchor xml:id="Toc196843738"/>Creating a Representative Tinkar Reference Model for a
            Data set</title>
        <para>Creating a representative Tinkar Reference Model for a domain data set involves
            several key steps. The sections below detail the current Tinkar starter data and outline
            the steps for translating a data set into the Tinkar Logical Model.</para><figure xml:id="KeyStepstoRepresentaDataSetinTinkar">
            <title>Key Steps to Represent a Data Set in Tinkar</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/Key%20Steps%20to%20Represent%20a%20Data%20Set%20in%20Tinkar.svg"
                        scale="100" align="center"/> 
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <section>
            <title>Modeling Principles</title>
            <para>There are specific principles to try and follow while executing the modeling
                process. These principles are detailed below. </para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Encapsulate rather than
                                specialize.</emphasis></emphasis></para>                 
                    <para>For example, if a device identifier is sourced from a database like the
                        Global Unique Device Identification Database (GUDID), you would not create a
                        new Pattern to handle it. You should continue to use the Identifier Pattern
                        already created in GUDID, but instead create a new Pattern to add any
                        additional information needed (i.e., Is it a Primary DI or a Secondary DI?
                        etc.) This new Pattern could then have Semantics referencing the identifier
                        Semantic Components to give meaning.</para></listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">A Pattern/Field Definition
                                cannot have the same purpose as its
                                meaning.</emphasis></emphasis></para>
                    <para>In cases where a Pattern has more than one field definition, we want the
                        purpose and meaning to be unique for each field definition. If there is only
                        one field definition it is okay if the meaning and purpose are the same but
                        in general, we want to be as specific here as possible since the reasoner
                        looks at these purpose and meaning Concepts to determine equivalence in
                        Patterns.</para></listitem>

            </orderedlist>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Defining The Data Element</title>
        <para>To represent a new standard in the Tinkar Logical Model, it is essential to determine
            the Patterns of the data set. Some Patterns will originate from the current Tinkar
            starter set, while others may be created specifically for the data set’s unique
            properties or reused from systems such as SNOMED CT®, LOINC®, or RxNorm.</para>
        <para>In preparation for modeling in Tinkar, there are two approaches:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Starting from an existing system’s data set like SNOMED CT®, LOINC®, or
                    RxNorm</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Developing a new model using elements that might already exist and/or
                    introducing brand new elements that need representation (e.g., LIDR). </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>The differences between predefined and new data sets are minimal. The main difference
            is that with a predefined data set, information about the model is usually
            well-documented, making it easier to identify a unique list of data elements and
            definitions. With a new data set, validating unique data elements and definitions may
            take more time.</para>
        <para>To determine a data set’s Patterns, it is recommended to start by identifying all
            unique fields in the data set and assigning them a meaning, purpose, and definition. The
            term meaning refers to the Concept or idea that a word, phrase, symbol, or other form of
            communication represents. Within the Tinkar Reference Model, a meaning is applied to a
            field within a Semantic, indicating the type of information or data the field is
            designed to hold. For example, a field used to describe an SDO’s website would have the
            meaning 'URL,' implying that the field is meant to contain a URL. This is the specific
            type of data representing a web address.</para>
        <para>The term ‘purpose’ refers to the specific role or function that a field within a
            Semantic is intended to serve. It provides broader context for why the field and its
            data exist within the model. For example, in the field describing an SDO’s website, the
            purpose is 'Website,' indicating that the field's role is to provide the website
            address, adding context to the meaning 'URL.'</para>
        <para>For a data set that is part of a well-established source such as RxNorm and SNOMED
            CT®, field definitions can typically be found in online documentation of the
            terminology. For a data set that is not well-established, definitions may need to be
            created.</para>
        <para>To illustrate a practical example of a predefined data set, the image below shows a
            snippet of the LOINC® transformation. LOINC® is a predefined data set with definitions
            and fields listed in its source file. In this snippet, some unique LOINC® fields
            provided in the data set are added to an Excel sheet in preparation. The purpose,
            meaning, and definitions are included to exemplify what these definitions should
            be.</para><figure xml:id="ExampleofLOINCDataElements">
            <title>Example of LOINC Data Elements</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/Example%20of%20LOINC%20Data%20Elements.svg"
                        scale="100" align="center"/> 
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>Once unique data elements are recorded, they can be assessed to determine how they can
            be represented using current Tinkar Semantics, Concepts, and Patterns.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Determine Description Semantics</title>
        <para>Since the goal is to reuse Tinkar Components as often as possible, the current Tinkar
            Patterns are reviewed first to determine where the new data set can be represented using
            those Patterns. It is advised to start with the Description Semantics. Description
            Semantics define how names and definitions are assigned to Components. Table 1 should be
            reviewed to determine what Concepts to use in the analyzed data set or if something new
            needs to be created. To understand how this has been done before, examples of
            terminology snippets from SNOMED CT®, LOINC®, RxNorm, and LIDR are provided below. As
            the following sections walk through modeling the Description Semantic, these snippets
            will be referred to as examples of how to model certain fields.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Example 1: SNOMED CT® Regular Name
                </emphasis></emphasis></para>
        <para>The example in the screenshot below, shows a row of SNOMED CT® data that will be used
            to demonstrate how the data set was represented using the Description Semantics.</para>
        <para>Source: <link
                xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCRELFMT/4.2.2.+Description+File+Specification"
                >https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCRELFMT/4.2.2.+Description+File+Specification</link>.</para>
        <para/><figure xml:id="SNOMEDCTDescriptionDataExample">
            <title>SNOMED CT® Description Data Example</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/SNOMED%20CT®%20Description%20Data%20Example.svg"
                        scale="100" align="center"/> 
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Example 2: LOINC® Long Common
                    Name</emphasis></emphasis></para>
        <para>The example in the screenshot below shows a row of LOINC® data that will be used to
            demonstrate how the data set was represented using the Description Semantics.</para>
        <para>Source: <link xlink:href="https://loinc.org/search/?t=1&amp;s=7364-3"
                >https://LOINC®.org/search/?t=1&amp;s=7364-3</link>. </para><figure xml:id="LOINCDescriptionDataExample">
                    <title>LOINC® Description Data Example</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="../images/LOINC®%20Description%20Data%20Example.svg"
                                scale="30" align="center"/> 
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
        <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Example 3: RxNorm
                Name</emphasis></emphasis></para>
        <para>The example in the screenshot below shows a row of RxNorm data that will be used to
            demonstrate how the data set was represented using the Description Semantics.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Source File: </emphasis><link
                xlink:href="https://lhncbc.nlm.nih.gov/RxNav/news/RxNorm-in-OWL.html"><emphasis
                    role="bold"
                    >https://lhncbc.nlm.nih.gov/RxNav/news/RxNorm-in-OWL.html</emphasis></link></para><figure xml:id="RxNormOWLFileExample">
                    <title>RxNorm OWL File Example</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="../images/RxNorm%20OWL%20File%20Example.svg"
                                scale="100" align="center"/> 
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
        <section>
            <title><anchor xml:id="Toc196843742"/>Field 1: Language</title>
            <para>The first field value for the Description Semantic is assigned as a Language
                Concept. The purpose of the language field is to identify the Concept's language and
                description. The table below outlines the currently available languages to select
                from. If a specific language Concept does not exist in Tinkar, a new Concept to
                represent that language will need to be created.</para>
            <table>
                <title>Language Concepts</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Concept </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">English Language </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A Concept representing the English Language</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Spanish Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A Concept representing the Spanish Language</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Chinese Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A Concept representing the Chinese Language</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Czech Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A Concept representing the Czech Language</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Danish Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A Concept representing the Danish Language</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Dutch Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A Concept representing the Dutch Language</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">French Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A Concept representing the French Language</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">German Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A Concept representing the German Language</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Irish Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A Concept representing the Irish Language</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Italian Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A Concept representing the Italian Language</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Korean Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A Concept representing the Korean Language</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Lithuanian Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A Concept representing the Lithuanian Language</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Polish Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A Concept representing the Polish Language</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Russian Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A Concept representing the Russian Language</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Swedish Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A Concept representing the Swedish Language</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>Upon revisiting the examples provided in section 3.2, the following
                representations and/or gaps were identified:</para>
            <table>
                <title>Language Examples</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 1: SNOMED CT®</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>From the SNOMED CT® export file, the language Concept can
                                represent language Code. In this case, <emphasis role="bold"
                                        ><emphasis role="italic">'en'</emphasis></emphasis> would be
                                used for English.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 2: LOINC®</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>From the LOINC® export file, the English version has been
                                obtained, so all descriptions can be represented by the language
                                Concept and English can be. There was no explicit language field
                                like there was in SNOMED CT, but since LOINC is primarily an
                                American terminology we can assume we will use the English language
                                to represent the Concept.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 3: RxNorm</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>From the RxNorm export file, the English version has been
                                obtained, so all descriptions can be represented by the language
                                Concept and English can be used.</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>No new Concepts need to be created since the Languages above can be represented
                with existing Concepts in Tinkar. </para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">To add a language Concept:</emphasis></para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Create a new Concept.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Give the Concept a Fully Qualified Name of the specific language it is
                        representing.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>In the Stated Definition, add an is-A relationship to language under the
                        necessary set.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title><anchor xml:id="Toc196843743"/>Field 2: Description String</title>
            <para>The Description String field is the literal string representation of the data,
                typically just the name of the element. </para>
            <table>
                <title>Description String</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Concept </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description String </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>The string value that represents the data.</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>Upon revisiting the examples provided in section 3.2, the following
                representations were identified:</para>
            <table>
                <title>Description String Examples</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 1: SNOMED CT®</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>From the SNOMED CT® export file, the string value of the Term
                                field <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">‘Chronic lung
                                        disease’</emphasis></emphasis> represents the Tinkar
                                Description String value in the Description Semantic.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 2: LOINC®</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>From the LOINC® export file, the string value of the Long Common
                                Name <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">‘Meadow Fescue
                                        IgG Ab [Units/volume] in Serum’</emphasis></emphasis>
                                represents the Tinkar Description String value in the Description
                                Semantic.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 3: RxNorm</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>From the RxNorm export file, the string value of the text inside
                                the quotations <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic"
                                        >‘amlodipine 5 MG / hydrochlorothiazide 25 MG / olmesartan
                                        medoxomil 40 MG Oral Tablet’</emphasis></emphasis>
                                represents the Tinkar Description String value in the Description
                                Semantic.</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>No new Concepts need to be created since the above Description Strings can be
                represented with existing Concepts in Tinkar.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title><anchor xml:id="Toc196843744"/>Field 3: Description Case Significance</title>
            <para>Description case significance specifies how the capitalization of the string value
                should be handled, such as whether it is case sensitive or case insensitive. If the
                data has specific capitalization rules beyond existing Concepts, a new Concept will
                need to be created to represent it.</para>
            <table>
                <title>Description Case Significance</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Concept </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description Case
                                Sensitive</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Assumes the description is dependent on capitalization</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description Not Case Sensitive
                                </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Value which designates character as not sensitive for a given
                                description</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>Upon revisiting the examples provided in section 3.2, the following
                representations and/or gaps were identified:</para>
            <table>
                <title>Description Case Significance Examples</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 1: SNOMED CT®</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>From the SNOMED CT® export, the caseSignificanceID can be
                                represented using the Case Significance child Concept. Therefore,
                                    <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Description Not
                                        Case Sensitive</emphasis></emphasis> would be used to
                                represent its case significance.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 2: LOINC®</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>In the LOINC® export file, there is no requirement to enforce
                                case sensitivity on the long common name during a search. Therefore,
                                    <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Description Not
                                        Case Sensitive</emphasis></emphasis> would be used to
                                represent its case significance.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 3: RxNorm</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>In the RxNorm export file, the RxNorm Name specifically
                                incorporates certain capital letters with a particular purpose.
                                Therefore, <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Description
                                        Not Case Sensitive</emphasis></emphasis> would be used to
                                represent its case significance.</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>No new Concepts need to be created since the above Description Case Significance
                can be represented with existing Concepts in Tinkar.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title><anchor xml:id="Toc196843745"/>Field 4: Description Type</title>
            <para>The description type field is used to determine the type of description the string
                represents for a Component. For example, the Fully Qualified Name is the primary way
                a Component is referred to. The Regular Name is any other common name or synonym
                referring to that Concept. The Definition description type can be used to provide a
                definition for any Concept. If none of the description types below represent the
                description specific to the data set, a new Concept would need to be created under
                Description Type to represent the new type of data.</para>
            <table>
                <title>Description Type</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Concept </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description Type</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Specifying what type of description, it is i.e., is it fully
                                qualified or regular and etc.</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <table>
                <title>Description Type Children</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Children Concept</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition Description Type
                                </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Semantic value indicating that the description type for the
                                Description Pattern is a definition</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Fully Qualified Name Description
                                    Type</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Semantic value indicating that the description type for the
                                Description Pattern is a fully qualified name. The fully qualified
                                name is a unique description that differentiates a Concept from
                                other similar Concepts.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Regular Name Description Type
                                </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Semantic value indicating that the description type for
                                Description Patter is a regular name. This includes names that are
                                not the fully qualified name, such as synonyms or other descriptions
                                of a Concept.</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>Revisiting the examples provided in section 2.3, the following representations
                and/or gaps were identified:</para>
            <table>
                <title>Description Type Examples</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 1: SNOMED CT®</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>From the SNOMED CT® export file, typeId is represented using one
                                of the Description Types. Specifically, <emphasis role="bold"
                                        ><emphasis role="italic">Synonym</emphasis></emphasis> is
                                represented using the Tinkar Regular Name Description Type.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 2: LOINC®</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>From the LOINC® export file, the long common name can be
                                represented using the <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic"
                                        >Fully Qualified Name Description
                                Type</emphasis></emphasis>.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 3: RxNorm</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>From the RxNorm export file, the RxNorm Name can be represented
                                using the <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Fully
                                        Qualified Name Description
                                Type</emphasis></emphasis>.</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>No new Concepts need to be created since the above Description Types can be
                represented with existing Concepts in Tinkar.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Determine Identifier Semantics</title>
        <para>Identifier Semantics are used to assign unique identifiers to Components that link to
            external data sources where the identifier is utilized. Although each Component in
            Tinkar is assigned a UUID, the original source and identifier of the data must be
            captured to reference back to the original source. For example, SNOMED CT® Identifiers
            and LOINC® IDs are stored and assigned to the Concepts they describe. Specific examples
            are detailed further in this section. The Identifier Pattern and its child Concepts are
            shown below.</para>
        <table>
            <title>Identifier Pattern</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2"><anchor xml:id="Hlk196842095"
                            />Identifier Pattern</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Semantic Meaning</entry>
                        <entry>Identifier Source</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Semantic Purpose</entry>
                        <entry>Identifier Source</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Field 1: Identifier Source </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Meaning</entry>
                        <entry>Identifier Source</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Purpose</entry>
                        <entry>Identifier Source</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Field Type</entry>
                        <entry>Component Field</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Field 2: Identifier Value</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Meaning</entry>
                        <entry>Identifier Value</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Purpose</entry>
                        <entry>Identifier Value</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Field Type</entry>
                        <entry>String</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
        <table>
            <title>Identifier Pattern Concept</title>
            <tgroup cols="4">
                <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                <colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Pattern Field</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Concept </emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition </emphasis></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry morerows="1"><emphasis role="bold">Identifier Semantic/Field 1:
                                Identifier Source</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Meaning</entry>
                        <entry>Identifier Source</entry>
                        <entry>An identifier used to label the identity of a unique
                            Component.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Purpose</entry>
                        <entry>Identifier Source</entry>
                        <entry>An identifier used to label the identity of a unique
                            Component.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry morerows="1"><emphasis role="bold">Field 2: Identifier
                                Value</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Meaning</entry>
                        <entry>Identifier Value </entry>
                        <entry>The literal string value associated as the ID</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Purpose</entry>
                        <entry>Identifier Value </entry>
                        <entry>The literal string value associated as the ID</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
        <para>To understand how this has been done before, examples of terminology snippets from
            SNOMED CT®, LOINC®, RxNorm, and LIDR are provided below. As the following sections walk
            through modeling the Identifier Semantic, these snippets will be referred to as examples
            for how to model certain fields.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Example 1: SNOMED
                CT®</emphasis></emphasis></para>
        <para>The example in the screenshot below shows a row of SNOMED CT® data used to illustrate
            how the data set was represented using the Identifier Semantics.</para>
        <para>Source: <link
                xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCRELFMT/4.2.1+Concept+File+Specification"
                >https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCRELFMT/4.2.1+Concept+File+Specification</link></para>
        <figure xml:id="SNOMEDCTUUIDExample">
            <title>SNOMED CT® UUID Example</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="../images/SNOMED%20CT®%20UUID%20Example.svg"
                                scale="100" align="center"/> 
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Example 2:
            LOINC®</emphasis></emphasis></para>
        <para>The example in the screenshot below shows a row of LOINC® data used to illustrate how
            the data set was represented using the Identifier Semantics.</para>
        <para>Source: <link xlink:href="https://loinc.org/search/?t=1&amp;s=7364-3"
                >https://LOINC®.org/search/?t=1&amp;s=7364-3</link>. </para><figure xml:id="LOINCUUIDExample">
            <title>LOINC® UUID Example</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/LOINC®%20UUID%20Example.svg"
                        scale="70" align="center"/> 
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Example 3:
            RxNorm</emphasis></emphasis></para>
        <para>The example in the screenshot below shows a row of RxNorm data used to illustrate how
            the data set was represented using the Identifier Semantics.</para>
        <figure xml:id="RxNormOWLFileIdentifier">
            <title>RxNorm OWL File Identifier</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/RxNorm%20OWL%20File%20Identifier.svg"
                        scale="100" align="center"/> 
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <section>
            <title><anchor xml:id="Toc196843747"/>Field 1: Identifier Source</title>
            <para>The Identifier Source is a unique identifier representing the data source from
                which it originates, such as SNOMED CT® or LOINC®. In cases where a data set is
                represented for the first time in Tinkar, the source may not yet exist,
                necessitating the creation of a new Concept.</para>
            <table>
                <title>UUID Concept</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Children Concept </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Universally Unique Identifier
                                </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>An identifier that uniquely represents a Concept in
                                Tinkar</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>Upon revisiting the examples outlined in section 3.3, the following
                representations and/or gaps were identified:</para>
            <table>
                <title>Identifier Source Examples</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 1: SNOMED CT®</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>From the SNOMED CT® export file, since the ID is not a UUID, a
                                new Concept is required. This Concept, referred to as ‘SNOMED CT®
                                Identifier Source’, becomes a child Concept of Identifier Source,
                                and the Semantic Field Value references this newly created
                                Concept.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 2: LOINC®</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>From the LOINC® export file, the absence of an Identifier Source
                                like in Example 1 necessitates the creation of a new ‘LOINC® Number’
                                Concept under Identifier Source, which is used for the Semantic
                                Field Value.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 3: RxNorm</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>From the RxNorm export file, the assignment of two different
                                    Identifiers to the Concept results in two separate Identifier
                                    Semantics: one references the RxNorm CUI, while the other
                                    references the SNOMED CT® ID. </para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>RxNorm CUI: a new Concept under Identifier Source,
                                            named ‘RxNorm CUI’, is required. This is the Semantic
                                            Field Value for the first Identifier Semantic.</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>SNOMED CT® ID: a new Concept needs to be created, or
                                            the Concept from Example 1 can be utilized if it was
                                            previously created in the model.</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>In these examples, each case needed a new Concept to represent the Unique
                Identifier.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title><anchor xml:id="Toc196843748"/>Field 2: Identifier Value</title>
            <para>The identifier value is the string representation of the Identifier, typically a
                random integer. Upon revisiting the examples provided in section 3.3, the following
                representations and/or gaps were identified:</para>
            <table>
                <title>Identifier Value Examples</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 1: SNOMED CT®</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>From the SNOMED CT® export file, the literal string value
                                ‘413839001’ from the ID column is used for the field value.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 2: LOINC®</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>From the LOINC® export file, the literal string value '7364-3'
                                from the LOINC®_NUM column is used for the field value.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 3: RxNorm</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>From the RxNorm export file, as described in the previous
                                    example, two fields were created using two Semantics. The string
                                    value representing each ID is used for the field value: </para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>'1000001' for RxNorm CUI</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>'447089002' for SNOMED CT®</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title><anchor xml:id="Toc196843749"/>Determine Stated Definition Semantics</title>
            <para>The Stated Definition Semantic captures the unique relationships that define a
                Concept. This can be challenging to model because it requires determining which data
                elements fit into the existing stated definition versus those that need new Patterns
                and Semantics. In this step, it is essential to identify the properties of Concepts
                that make them unique, i.e., the underlying properties that differentiate one
                Concept from another in the model. The Stated Definition Pattern is depicted below,
                along with the meaning and purpose Concepts.</para>
            <table>
                <title>Stated Definition Pattern</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Stated Definition Pattern</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Semantic Meaning</entry>
                            <entry>Stated Definition</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Semantic Purpose</entry>
                            <entry>Logical Definition</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Field 1: Logical Definition</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Meaning</entry>
                            <entry>EL++ Terminological Axioms</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Purpose</entry>
                            <entry>Logical Definition</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Field Type</entry>
                            <entry>DiTree</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <table>
                <title>Stated Definition Meaning and Purpose Concepts</title>
                <tgroup cols="4">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                    <colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Pattern Field</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Concept </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition </emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry morerows="1"><emphasis role="bold">Stated Definition
                                    Semantic</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Meaning</entry>
                            <entry>Stated Definition</entry>
                            <entry>Relationships/Axioms of a Concept that have been explicitly
                                stated and defined</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Purpose</entry>
                            <entry>Logical Definition</entry>
                            <entry>The Semantic value describing the purpose of the stated and
                                inferred terminological axioms.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry morerows="1"><emphasis role="bold">Field 1: Logical
                                    Definition</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Meaning</entry>
                            <entry>EL++ Terminological Axioms </entry>
                            <entry>The relationships that uniquely define a Concept in EL++
                                description logic.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Purpose</entry>
                            <entry>Logical Definition </entry>
                            <entry>The Semantic value describing the purpose of the stated and
                                inferred terminological axioms.</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>In cases where the data set is predefined, such as SNOMED CT® or RxNORM, the OWL
                Description Logic String is provided and transformed into the EL++ Stated
                Terminological Axioms. When creating a new model, the properties of EL++
                Terminological Axioms must be examined to determine how to describe the uniqueness
                of the Concepts being modeled. The stated definition child Concepts are outlined
                below.</para>
            <table>
                <title>Stated Definition Children Concepts</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Children Concept </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2"><emphasis role="bold">Implication
                                    Set</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Implication Set </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A set of relationships that indicate something has an
                                implication. Not necessary or sufficient, but implicated.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Necessary Set </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A set of relationships that is always true of a Concept.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Property Set</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A set of relationships that are non-defining and are not used by
                                a description logic classifier.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Sufficient Set </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A set of relationships that differentiate a Concept and its
                                subtypes from all other Concepts. A Concept that contains at least
                                one set of necessary and sufficient conditions is considered
                                defined.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2"><emphasis role="bold"
                                    >Roles</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Role group </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>An association between a set of attribute or axiom value pairs
                                that causes them to be considered together within a Concept
                                definition or post-coordinated expression.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Role</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>An abstract representation of a high-level role for a therapeutic
                                medicinal product; these Concepts are not intended to describe
                                detailed indications for therapeutic use or imply appropriateness in
                                all clinical situations.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Role Type</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A Concept representing a particular kind of relationship between
                                two entities, defining the specific function or responsibility one
                                entity plays in relation to another.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Concept Reference</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>The Concept referred to by the is_a axiom relationship or the
                                axiom role relationship.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Is a </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Designates the parent child relationship</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>To understand how the Stated Definitions Semantic has been modeled, examples of
                terminology snippets from SNOMED CT®, LOINC®, RxNorm, and LIDR are provided below.
                As the following sections walk through modeling the Stated Definitions Semantic,
                these snippets will be referred to as examples for how to model certain
                fields.</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Example 1: SNOMED
                    CT®</emphasis></emphasis></para>
            <para>The example in the screenshots below shows a SNOMED CT® Axiom example and its
                Axiom expression, illustrating how the data set was represented using the Stated
                Definitions Semantics.</para>
            <para>Source: <link
                    xlink:href="https://browser.loincsnomed.org/?perspective=full&amp;conceptId1=413839001&amp;edition=MAIN/LOINC/2023-10-15&amp;release=&amp;languages=en"
                    >https://browser.LOINC®snomed.org/?perspective=full&amp;ConceptId1=413839001&amp;edition=MAIN/LOINC®/2023-10-15&amp;release=&amp;languages=en</link></para>
            <figure xml:id="SNOMEDCTExampleOWLExpression">
                <title>SNOMED CT® Example OWL Expression</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/SNOMED%20CT®%20Example%20OWL%20Expression.svg"
                            scale="75" align="center"/> 
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="SNOMEDCTExampleOWLExpression2">
                <title>SNOMED CT® Example OWL Expression</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/SNOMED%20CT®%20Example%20OWL%20Expression2.svg"
                            scale="75" align="center"/> 
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Example 2:
                    LOINC®</emphasis></emphasis></para>
            <para>LOINC® does not have an OWL String representation. However, the information below
                shows the data from LOINC® used to represent LOINC® using the Tinkar Stated
                Definitions Semantics.</para>
            <para>Source: <link xlink:href="https://loinc.org/search/?t=1&amp;s=7364-3"
                    >https://LOINC®.org/search/?t=1&amp;s=7364-3</link></para>
            <figure xml:id="LOINCExampleOWLExpression">
                <title>LOINC® Example OWL Expression</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/LOINC®%20Example%20OWL%20Expression.svg"
                            scale="50" align="center"/> 
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic"> Example 3:
                    RxNorm</emphasis></emphasis></para>
            <para>The example in the screenshot below shows the RxNorm OWL file, illustrating how
                the data was represented using the Stated Definitions Semantics.</para>
            <para>Source File: <link
                    xlink:href="https://lhncbc.nlm.nih.gov/RxNav/news/RxNorm-in-OWL.html"
                    >https://lhncbc.nlm.nih.gov/RxNav/news/RxNorm-in-OWL.html</link></para>
            <figure xml:id="RxNormExampleOWLExpression">
                <title>RxNorm Example OWL Expression</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/RxNorm%20Example%20OWL%20Expression.svg"
                            scale="100" align="center"/> 
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Determine Description Logic</title>
            <para>Description logic aims to represent and characterize classes of objects and their
                relationships. SNOMED CT®, for example, uses description logic that corresponds to
                the EL++ language to define Stated and Inferred relationships and axioms. Given that
                all source files differ, not all contain OWL Description Logic. If they do contain
                an OWL Description Logic String, it should be utilized to avoid manually creating
                another string.</para>
            <para>Upon revisiting the examples provided in section 3.4, the following
                representations and/or gaps were identified:</para>
            <table>
                <title>Stated Definition Examples</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 1: SNOMED CT®</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Utilizing the owlExpression column allows for the representation
                                of the field using the Tinkar description logic. This string can be
                                imported using EL++ Description Logic, leading to the generation of
                                Stated Axioms.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 2: LOINC®</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>LOINC® lacks an OWL String representation unless SNOMED
                                    CT®-LOINC® collaboration files are used, but these files are
                                    incomplete. Documentation reveals six main parts comprising a
                                    LOINC® Code:</para>
                                <orderedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Component</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Property</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Time</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>System</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Scale</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Method</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </orderedlist>
                                <para>Part definitions from LOINC® are treated as ‘Roles’ in the
                                    stated definition. ‘Role Type’ corresponds to one of the six
                                    parts above, and ‘Role Value’ corresponds to the Concept
                                    representation of the value. </para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>To represent the data in the Stated Definitions
                                            Semantics, create a new Concept for each main LOINC®
                                            Part and a new Concept for each unique value for each of
                                            the six parts so they can be assigned in the LOINC® Code
                                            Role.</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>In addition to these six parts, there needs to be an
                                            ‘Is A’ relationship to designate the parent Concept. In
                                            the SNOMED CT®-LOINC® Collaboration, all LOINC® Concepts
                                            are listed as a child of ‘Observable Entity.’ Therefore,
                                            all LOINC® Codes will have an ‘Is A -> Observable
                                            Entity’ relationship.</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 3: RxNorm</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>In the RxNorm OWL release file, the OWL Syntax literal string
                                    row can be used to represent the Tinkar description logic field
                                    in the Stated Definitions Semantics.</para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>‘EquivalentClasses(:90708001
                                            ObjectIntersectionOf(:64572001
                                            ObjectSomeValuesFrom(:609096000
                                            ObjectSomeValuesFrom(:363698007 :64033007))))’</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Create New Patterns</title>
        <para>Once the current Patterns are analyzed and representation using Tinkar is determined,
            some outlying data may still need to be extended into new Patterns using the Tinkar
            Reference Model. This section reviews the steps for creating new Patterns.</para>
        <section>
            <title><anchor xml:id="Toc196843752"/>Filter for Data Elements associated to
                Concepts</title>
            <para>Start by filtering data elements associated with the Concept being modeled. Focus
                on these elements rather than those describing other data elements in the file.
                Since Semantics refer to any Component (any Concept, Pattern, or Semantic), begin
                with the Patterns that refer to the Concepts being modeled.</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Example 1: SNOMED CT® </emphasis></para>
            <para>In SNOMED CT®, there are descriptions and dialects. Descriptions are modeled first
                since they reference actual Concepts (Semantic referring to a Concept), while
                Dialects refer to those Descriptions (Semantic referring to a Semantic).</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Example 2: LOINC® </emphasis></para>
            <para>In LOINC®, there is a data element for STATUS. This directly describes an
                attribute of a LOINC® Concept. However, there are additional data elements such as
                STATUS_REASON, STATUS_TEXT, and CHANGE_REASON_PUBLIC. These additional data elements
                do not directly describe attributes of the LOINC® Concept itself but are descriptive
                attributes of the STATUS.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Group by similar data elements </title>
            <para>Group data fields with similar elements together. Elements with similar purposes
                and occurrences should be grouped together in a Pattern. These elements do not
                always need to have the same values across Concepts. Once the related Concepts are
                represented, these groupings will become new Patterns.</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Example 1: RxNorm</emphasis></para>
            <para>In RxNorm, HUMAN_DRUG and PRESCRIBABLE are two data elements that are closely
                related and often seen together, but it is not expected for them to occur with a
                field like VET_DRUG. In this case, to add these three data elements, two different
                Patterns are needed:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>HUMAN_DRUG + PRESCRIBABLE</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>VET_DRUG</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title><anchor xml:id="Toc196843754"/>Determine Field Types</title>
            <para>After grouping the new properties into the new Patterns that need to be modeled,
                each data element will be treated as a field type. For each field, determine how to
                represent it in the model. Below is a list of field types, with the official list
                available in Tinkar core.</para>
            <table>
                <title>Field Types</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Concept </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Component Field </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A display field type that references a Concept ID.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Component ID List </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A display field that references an ordered list of Concept
                                IDs.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Component ID Set Field </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A display field that references an unordered list of Concept
                                IDs.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Directed Graph (DiGraph) Filed
                                </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A display field that references a di-graph whose edges are
                                ordered pairs of vertices. Each edge can be followed from one vertex
                                to another vertex.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Directed Tree (DiTree) Field
                                </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A display field that references a graph obtained from an
                                undirected tree by replacing each undirected edge by two directed
                                edges with opposite directions.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Float Field </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A data type that represents values as high-precision fractional
                                values.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Integer Field </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A data type that represents some range of mathematical
                                integers</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">String </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A sequence of characters, either as a literal constant or as a
                                variable. Strings could be used to represent terms from code systems
                                or URLs, textual definitions, etc.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Boolean</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A data type that represents one of two possible values, typically
                                true or false.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Image</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A data type that represents a visual representation, such as a
                                photo or graphic.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Instant</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A data type that represents a specific point in time, often with
                                high precision.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Big Decimal</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A data type that represents very large or very precise decimal
                                numbers.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Byte Array</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A data type that represents a sequence of bytes, often used for
                                binary data.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">UUID</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A universally unique identifier, a 128-bit number used to
                                uniquely identify information in computer systems.</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>The most common field types are the Component Field, Component Set Field, and
                String Field. Things to consider:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If it is a unique element that can vary significantly between Concepts and
                        rarely has a chance of two Concepts having the same value, it should be
                        treated as a String or something similar.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If the value for the data element might be common across different
                        Concepts being modeled, consider making that value its own Concept and treat
                        this field as a Component Field with the value of that Concept.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If there could be multiple values for the data element that can be
                            shared or common across different Concepts, a Component Set Field can be
                            used, and all the values can be modeled as different Concepts within the
                            ‘set’.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Example 1: LOINC®
                        ClassType</emphasis></emphasis></para>
            <para>To represent the LOINC® ClassType, a new Pattern must be created. The LOINC®
                ClassType can be defined using a semantic of this new pattern on a LOINC® Code. When
                creating a new pattern for a Semantic, there are two different choices to make. The
                first decision is how many field definitions the Pattern should have. The second
                decision is what data type should use for the field definitions. Patterns specify
                what type of data are in the Semantic fields. However, the number of fields can vary
                depending on what type of data you are trying to represent. </para>
            <para>Patterns do not have to have field definitions. These types of patterns are called
                Membership Patterns. The purpose and meaning of the Pattern specify the Semantic
                value themselves, so a field is not needed. Using LOINC ClassType, four new patterns
                can be created. The purpose of the Patterns would be similar and have the same
                ClassType concept value, but their meaning would be different and dependent on the
                actual value. The result would be each LOINC Code having a semantic of one of the
                four corresponding patterns. </para>
            <table>
                <title>LOINC® ClassType Patterns with No Field Definitions</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Laboratory ClassType Pattern</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Semantic Meaning</entry>
                            <entry>Laboratory Class</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Semantic Purpose</entry>
                            <entry>LOINC® ClassType</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Clinical ClassType Pattern</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Semantic Meaning</entry>
                            <entry>Clinical Class</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Semantic Purpose</entry>
                            <entry>LOINC® ClassType</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Claims Attachment Type
                                Pattern</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Semantic Meaning</entry>
                            <entry>Claims Attachment</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Semantic Purpose</entry>
                            <entry>LOINC® ClassType</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Survey Type Pattern</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Semantic Meaning</entry>
                            <entry>Survey</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Semantic Purpose</entry>
                            <entry>LOINC® ClassType</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>Using No Field Definitions only works with properties that have a small set of
                possible values. If there are a significant number of possible values, it is better
                to use a field definition as shown below. </para>
            <para>To display the ClassType in a field definition for a Pattern, determine if any
                other Data Elements should be captured. For example, both the LOINC Class and
                ClassType can be captured in a single pattern using separate Field Definitions for
                each as shown below. </para>
            <table>
                <title>LOINC® Class Pattern with Field Definitions</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2"><anchor xml:id="Hlk196842781"
                                />LOINC® Class Pattern</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Semantic Meaning</entry>
                            <entry>LOINC® Class</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Semantic Purpose</entry>
                            <entry>LOINC® Class</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Field 1:</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Meaning</entry>
                            <entry>LOINC® Class</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Purpose</entry>
                            <entry>LOINC® Class</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Field Type</entry>
                            <entry>Concept Field</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2"><anchor xml:id="Hlk196842307"/>Field
                                2:</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Meaning</entry>
                            <entry>LOINC® ClassType</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Purpose</entry>
                            <entry>LOINC® ClassType</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Field Type</entry>
                            <entry>Concept Field</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para> </para>
            <para>In this example, the Class and ClassType are captured in a single pattern since
                they are closely related. The Field Type is assigned as a Concept Field. A good
                indication to use a Concept Field is if the Value itself has properties that should
                be modeled. </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Build Data Model and Starter Data</title>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The Data Model is created using a modeling tool, mapping out the Patterns,
                        Semantics, and Concepts</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Examples of current data models will be added here with
                        descriptions.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <figure xml:id="BuildDataModelandStarterData">
            <title>Build Data Model and Starter Data</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata
                        fileref="../images/Build%20Data%20Model%20and%20Starter%20Data.svg"
                        scale="100" align="center"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Validating Models</title>
        <para>To create a stable and reliable model, each must undergo a validation process. The
            validation process involves two key roles:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Domain Subject Matter Experts (SMEs) provide critical feedback based on their
                    specialized knowledge.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Tinkar Reference Modelers, who initially build and document the model, and
                    additional modelers provide insights on reusing current Tinkar Components,
                    ensuring correct reuse.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>The goal of this validation process is to achieve consensus on a stable model agreed
            upon by all relevant parties, providing a solid foundation that ensures the model's
            accuracy and reliability for future developments. The validation process involves three
            key steps: conducting peer review sessions, reviewing the model with domain SMEs, and
            having review cycles, and reaching a group consensus on the model's final state.</para>
        <figure xml:id="ValidatingModelsProcessFlowDiagram">
            <title>Validating Models Process Flow Diagram</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata
                        fileref="../images/Validating%20Models%20Process%20Flow%20Diagram.svg"
                        scale="75" align="center"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>When the initial model is complete, modelers should collect and create documentation
            of the model. This documentation should include the logical data model drawing and all
            modeling decisions, including reused Tinkar Patterns, Concepts, and Semantics, as well
            as new Concepts, Patterns, and/or Semantics created. The rationale behind the decisions
            made should also be included. Modelers should also work with other modelers to conduct
            peer review sessions to discuss the modeling decisions and rationale, and to reach
            agreed-upon decisions about the model.</para>
        <para>Once the initial model is complete, documentation is gathered, and the model has been
            peer-reviewed, the modelers should review it with the domain SME(s). The domain SME(s)
            should ensure the information requirements are met and the information is modeled in an
            agreed-upon way. All rationale for decisions, any questions the modelers may have, and
            any viable options for modeling certain aspects should be given to the domain SME(s) for
            review.</para>
        <para>Feedback gathered from the domain SME(s) should be captured and incorporated into the
            model. The modelers should then review the model again with the SMEs. The feedback
            process may continue for some time, but eventually, when all feedback has been discussed
            and implemented where applicable, the model should be finalized, and all documentation
            of the changes and history of the model should be shared.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Model Documentation</title>
        <para>Throughout the modeling process, modelers should capture documentation describing the
            rationale for decisions made, create the starter data set, and develop the logical data
            model. The table below describes the different types of artifacts modelers should
            provide once the modeling is complete. It is recommended to upload documentation to be
            stored on Confluence. </para>
        <table>
            <title>Common Tinkar Documents</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Artifact</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Model Rationale</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Documentation captured during the modeling process that explains the
                            reasoning behind modeling decisions, any assumptions made, and the
                            decisions for fields in the data set represented using Tinkar.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Starter Data Set</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>A list of any new Tinkar Components that should be created to
                            represent the data set.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Data Model</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>A logical model representation of any new Patterns, Semantics, and
                            Concepts.</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        <section>
            <title>Glossary</title>
            <para>
                <informaltable>
                    <tgroup cols="3">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Term</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Reference</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Component</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>A fundamental part of the Tinkar model, which can be a
                                    Concept, Pattern, or Semantic, each represented by
                                    UUIDs.</entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Concept</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>A Component in Tinkar identified by UUIDs and a STAMP,
                                    containing only information within the STAMP.</entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">CVX</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Codes for vaccines administered, which may overlap with
                                    RxNorm codes.</entry>
                                <entry><link
                                        xlink:href="https://www2a.cdc.gov/vaccines/iis/iisstandards/vaccines.asp?rpt=cvx"
                                        >IIS | Code Sets | CVX | Vaccines | CDC</link></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">LOINC®</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Logical Observation Identifiers, Names, and Codes</entry>
                                <entry><link xlink:href="https://loinc.org/">Home –
                                    LOINC</link></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Meaning</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>The interpretation or explanation field for a
                                    Pattern/Semantics, indicating the type of information a field is
                                    designed to hold.</entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Pattern</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>A Component that describes the fields and field types for a
                                    table, similar to a database schema, used to specify the
                                    structure needed to provide meaning to a Component.</entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>The specific role or function that a field within a Semantic
                                    is intended to serve, providing context for why the field and
                                    its data exist within the model.</entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">RxNorm</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>A standardized nomenclature for clinical drugs, providing
                                    codes for medications.</entry>
                                <entry><link
                                        xlink:href="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/research/umls/rxnorm/index.html"
                                        >RxNorm</link></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Semantic</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>Relating to or involving data which is structured and
                                        tagged according to its meaning or intention, allowing it to
                                        be read directly by computers.</para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>Semantic, adj. meanings, etymology and more | Oxford English
                                    Dictionary (oed.com)</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">SNOMED CT®</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Systematized Nomenclature of Medicine Clinical Terms</entry>
                                <entry><link xlink:href="https://www.snomed.org/">Home | SNOMED
                                        International</link></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Tinkar</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>A logical model designed to establish a robust knowledge
                                    architecture, integrating local systems with medical and
                                    laboratory terminologies to facilitate effective communication
                                    of clinical information across multiple systems.</entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </informaltable>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Tinkar Starter Data (Listed in alphabetical order)</title>
            <informaltable>
                <tgroup cols="5">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col5" colwidth="222pt"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col1" colwidth="143.25pt"/>
                    <colspec colnum="3" colname="col2" colwidth="117.75pt"/>
                    <colspec colnum="4" colname="col3" colwidth="117.75pt"/>
                    <colspec colnum="5" colname="col4" colwidth="204pt"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Destinations</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Fully Qualified Name</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Synonym</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Origins</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Acceptable (foundation metadata
                                    Concept)</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                            <entry>Specifies that a description is acceptable, but not preferred
                                within a language or dialect.</entry>
                            <entry>DESCRIPTION_ACCEPTABILITY</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Active status </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Active</entry>
                            <entry>Concept used to represent a status for Components that are
                                active.</entry>
                            <entry>STATUS_VALUE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Author</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Author</entry>
                            <entry> </entry>
                            <entry>ROOT_VERTEX</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Canceled status </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Canceled </entry>
                            <entry>Concept used to represent a status for Components that are
                                canceled</entry>
                            <entry>STATUS_VALUE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Chinese Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                            <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Component field</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Component field </entry>
                            <entry>A display field type that references a Concept ID.</entry>
                            <entry>DISPLAY_FIELDS</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Component Id list</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Component Id list </entry>
                            <entry>A display field that references an ordered list of Concept
                                IDs.</entry>
                            <entry>DISPLAY_FIELDS</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Component Id set field</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Component Id set </entry>
                            <entry>A display field that references an unordered list of Concept
                                IDs.</entry>
                            <entry>DISPLAY_FIELDS</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Czech Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                            <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Danish Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                            <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Descriptio</emphasis>n<emphasis role="bold"
                                    > not case sensitive </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Case insensitive</entry>
                            <entry>Value which designates character as not sensitive for a given
                                description </entry>
                            <entry>DESCRIPTION_CASE_SIGNIFICANCE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition description type
                                </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Definition</entry>
                            <entry>Semantic value describing the description type for the
                                description Pattern is a definition</entry>
                            <entry>DESCRIPTION_TYPE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Description</entry>
                            <entry>Human readable text for a Concept</entry>
                            <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">ACCEPTABLE; PREFERRED</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description acceptability
                                </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Description acceptability </entry>
                            <entry> Whether a given human readable text for a Concept is permissible </entry>
                            <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description case sensitive
                                </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Case sensitive </entry>
                            <entry>Assumes the description is dependent on capitalization </entry>
                            <entry>DESCRIPTION_CASE_SIGNIFICANCE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">DESCRIPTION_CASE_SENSITIVE;
                                    DESCRIPTION_NOT_CASE_SENSITIVE</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description case significance
                                </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Description case significance </entry>
                            <entry>Specifies how to handle the description text in terms of case
                                sensitivity </entry>
                            <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description Pattern </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Description Pattern</entry>
                            <entry>Contains all metadata and human readable text that describes the
                                Concept </entry>
                            <entry>PATTERN</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description Semantic </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Description Semantic </entry>
                            <entry>Purpose and meaning for the description Pattern and dialect
                                Patterns </entry>
                            <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">DEFINITION_DESCRIPTION_TYPE;
                                    FULLY_QUALIFIED_NAME_DESCRIPTION_TYPE;
                                    REGULAR_NAME_DESCRIPTION_TYPE</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description type </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Description type </entry>
                            <entry>Specifying what type of description, it is i.e., is it fully
                                qualified or regular and etc. </entry>
                            <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Descriptum </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Descriptum</entry>
                            <entry>The Semantic meaning for the EL++ Patterns </entry>
                            <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Development path </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Development path </entry>
                            <entry>A path that specifies that the Components are currently under
                                development</entry>
                            <entry>PATH</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">ENGLISH_DIALECT</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Dialect</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Dialect</entry>
                            <entry><link
                                    xlink:href="https://www.google.com/search?safe=active&amp;sca_esv=2802dad21c2aa82f&amp;rlz=1C1GCEA_enUS1093US1093&amp;q=peculiar&amp;si=AKbGX_qNq0Y8zql7SxzZAf2-HTTOVobuSeLnlL2tVO9M2fGNfebMB7TKBhol7Sqwuay6sY3kGrSwFLy9ZcG8n0EzEGwsbKROZpu_7GoFc3oiudVKoMYiSQE%3D&amp;expnd=1"
                                    >Specifies the dialect of the language.</link></entry>
                            <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">DiGraph field </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Instant/ DiGraph</entry>
                            <entry>A display field that references a di-graph whose edges are
                                ordered pairs of vertices. Each edge can be followed from one vertex
                                to another vertex.</entry>
                            <entry>DISPLAY_FIELDS</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">COMPONENT_FIELD; COMPONENT_ID_LIST_FIELD;
                                    COMPONENT_ID_SET_FIELD; DIGRAPH_FIELD; DITREE_FIELD;
                                    FLOAT_FIELD; INTEGER_FIELD; STRING</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Display Fields </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Display fields </entry>
                            <entry>Captures the human readable terms</entry>
                            <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">DiTree field </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>DiTree</entry>
                            <entry>A display field that references a graph obtained from an
                                undirected tree by replacing each undirected edge by two directed
                                edges with opposite directions.</entry>
                            <entry>DISPLAY_FIELDS</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Dutch Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                            <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">EL++ Inferred Axioms
                                Pattern</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Inferred definition Pattern</entry>
                            <entry> </entry>
                            <entry>PATTERN</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">NECESSARY_SET; SUFFICIENT_SET;
                                    IMPLICATION_SET; ROLE; ROLE_GROUP</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">EL++ Inferred terminological axioms
                                </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>EL++ Inferred terminological axioms</entry>
                            <entry> </entry>
                            <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">EL++ Stated Axioms
                                Pattern</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Stated definition Pattern</entry>
                            <entry> </entry>
                            <entry>PATTERN</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">NECESSARY_SET; SUFFICIENT_SET;v
                                    IMPLICATION_SET; ROLE; ROLE_GROUP</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">EL++ Stated terminological axioms
                                </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>EL++ Stated terminological axioms </entry>
                            <entry> </entry>
                            <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">US_ENGLISH_DIALECT;
                                    GB_ENGLISH_DIALECT</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">English Dialect </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>English Dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Specifies the dialect of the English language</entry>
                            <entry>DIALECT</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">English Language </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>English language </entry>
                            <entry>Value for description language</entry>
                            <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Existential restriction</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Existential restriction</entry>
                            <entry> Existential restrictions describe objects that participate in at
                                least one relationship along a specified property to objects of a
                                specified class.</entry>
                            <entry>ROLE_OPERATOR</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Float field </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Float field </entry>
                            <entry> Represents values as high-precision fractional values.</entry>
                            <entry>DISPLAY_FIELDS</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">French Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                            <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Fully qualified name description type
                                </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Fully qualified name </entry>
                            <entry>Fully qualified name is a description that uniquely identifies
                                and differentiates it from other Concepts with similar
                                descriptions</entry>
                            <entry>DESCRIPTION_TYPE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">GB Dialect Pattern</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>GB Dialect Pattern</entry>
                            <entry>Particular form of language specific form of English language,
                                particular to Great Britian</entry>
                            <entry>PATTERN</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">German Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                            <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Great Britian English dialect
                                </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>GB English dialect / GB English</entry>
                            <entry>Great Britain: English Language reference set </entry>
                            <entry>ENGLISH_DIALECT</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Identifier Pattern</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Identifier Pattern </entry>
                            <entry>An identifier Pattern is used to identity a Concept which
                                contains the identifier source and the actual value</entry>
                            <entry>PATTERN</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold"
                                >UNIVERSALLY_UNIQUE_IDENTIFIER</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Identifier Source </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Identifier source</entry>
                            <entry>An identifier used to label the identity of a unique
                                Component.</entry>
                            <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Implication set</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Implication set </entry>
                            <entry>A set of relationships that indicate something has an
                                implication. Not necessarily or sufficient but implicated.</entry>
                            <entry>EL_PLUS_PLUS_STATED_TERMINOLOGICAL_AXIOMS;
                                EL_PLUS_PLUS_INFERRED_TERMINOLOGICAL_AXIOMS</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Inactive Status </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Inactive</entry>
                            <entry>Concept used to represent a status for Components that are no
                                longer active</entry>
                            <entry>STATUS_VALUE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Inferred Navigation</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Inferred Navigation</entry>
                            <entry>The origins and destinations for Concepts based on the reasoner
                                generated inferred terminological axioms </entry>
                            <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Inferred Navigation
                                Pattern</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Inferred Navigation Pattern</entry>
                            <entry>A Pattern specifying the origins and destinations for Concepts
                                based on the inferred terminological axioms </entry>
                            <entry>PATTERN</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Integer Field </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Integer field</entry>
                            <entry>A data type that represents some range of mathematical
                                integers</entry>
                            <entry>DISPLAY_FIELDS</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">MODEL_CONCEPT; PATTERN; STATUS_VALUE; USER;
                                    MODULE; PATH</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Integrated Knowledge
                                Management</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Tinkar root Concept </entry>
                            <entry> </entry>
                            <entry> </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Irish Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                            <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Is-a</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Is a</entry>
                            <entry>Designates the parent child relationship</entry>
                            <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Italian Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                            <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Korean Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                            <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">ENGLISH_LANGUAGE;
                                    SPANISH_LANGUAGE</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Language </entry>
                            <entry>Specifies the language of the description text.</entry>
                            <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Language for Description</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Language for Description</entry>
                            <entry>The Semantic value indicating which language is used in the
                                description text</entry>
                            <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Lithuanian Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                            <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Logical Definition</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Logical Definition</entry>
                            <entry>The Semantic value describing the purpose of the stated and
                                inferred terminological axioms. </entry>
                            <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Master path</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Master path </entry>
                            <entry>A default path for Components</entry>
                            <entry>PATH</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Meaning </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Meaning </entry>
                            <entry>The interpretation or explanation field for a Pattern/Semantics </entry>
                            <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">DESCRIPTION; DESCRIPTION_ACCEPTABILITY;
                                    DESCRIPTION_CASE_SIGNIFICANCE; DESCRIPTION_SEMANTIC;
                                    DESCRIPTION_TYPE; DESCRIPTUM; DIALECT; DISPLAY_FIELDS;
                                    EL_PLUS_PLUS_INFERRED_TERMINOLOGICAL_AXIOMS;
                                    EL_PLUS_PLUS_STATED_TERMINOLOGICAL_AXIOMS; IDENTIFIER_SOURCE;
                                    INFERRED_NAVIGATION; IS_A; LANGUAGE; LANGUAGE_FOR_DESCRIPTION;
                                    LOGICAL_DEFINITION; MEANING; PHENOMENON;
                                    RELATIONSHIP_DESTINATION; RELATIONSHIP_ORIGIN;
                                    STATED_NAVIGATION; TEXT_FOR_DESCRIPTION;
                                PURPOSE</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Model Concept</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Model Concept</entry>
                            <entry> </entry>
                            <entry>ROOT_VERTEX</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">PRIMORDIAL_MODULE</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Module</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Module</entry>
                            <entry> </entry>
                            <entry>ROOT_VERTEX</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Necessary set</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Necessary set </entry>
                            <entry>A set of relationships that is always true of a Concept.</entry>
                            <entry>EL_PLUS_PLUS_STATED_TERMINOLOGICAL_AXIOMS;
                                EL_PLUS_PLUS_INFERRED_TERMINOLOGICAL_AXIOMS</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">DEVELOPMENT_PATH; MASTER_PATH;
                                    PRIMORDIAL_PATH; SANDBOX_PATH</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Path</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Path</entry>
                            <entry>A set of assets under version control that can be managed
                                distinctly from other assets. Paths ‘branch’ from other paths when
                                established and can be ‘merged’ with other paths as well.</entry>
                            <entry>ROOT_VERTEX</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">DESCRIPTION_PATTERN; GB_DIALECT_PATTERN;
                                    IDENTIFIER_PATTERN; INFERRED_NAVIGATION_PATTERN;
                                    STATED_NAVIGATION_PATTERN; US_DIALECT_PATTERN</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Pattern</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Pattern</entry>
                            <entry>A Pattern is a set of display fields and values that can be
                                asserted about a Concept</entry>
                            <entry>ROOT_VERTEX</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Phenomenon</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Phenomenon</entry>
                            <entry>A unique thought, fact, or circumstance</entry>
                            <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Polish Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                            <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Preferred</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Preferred </entry>
                            <entry>Specifies that a description is preferred within a language or
                                dialect. There will be one preferred description for each
                                description type.</entry>
                            <entry>DESCRIPTION_ACCEPTABILITY</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Primordial module</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Primordial module</entry>
                            <entry> </entry>
                            <entry>MODULE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Primordial path</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Primordial path</entry>
                            <entry> </entry>
                            <entry>PATH</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Primordial status</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Primordial </entry>
                            <entry>Concept used to represent a status for Components that have not
                                yet been released and exist in their most basic form.</entry>
                            <entry>STATUS_VALUE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Purpose</entry>
                            <entry>The reason for which a Tinkar value in a Pattern was created or
                                for which it exists. </entry>
                            <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Regular name description
                                type</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Regular name description type </entry>
                            <entry>There may be descriptions/synonyms marked as ‘regular.’</entry>
                            <entry>DESCRIPTION_TYPE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Relationship destination</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Relationship destination</entry>
                            <entry>Signifies path to child Concepts which are more specific than the
                                Tinkar term</entry>
                            <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Relationship origin</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Relationship origin</entry>
                            <entry>Signifies path to parent Concepts which are more general than the
                                Tinkar term</entry>
                            <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">ROLE_TYPE; ROLE_OPERATOR;
                                    ROLE_RESTRICTION</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Role</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Role</entry>
                            <entry>Is an abstract representation of a high-level role for a
                                therapeutic medicinal product; the Concepts are not intended to
                                describe a detailed indication for therapeutic use nor imply that
                                therapeutic use is appropriate in all clinical situations.</entry>
                            <entry>ROLE_GROUP; EL_PLUS_PLUS_STATED_TERMINOLOGICAL_AXIOMS;
                                EL_PLUS_PLUS_INFERRED_TERMINOLOGICAL_AXIOMS</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">ROLE</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Role group</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Role group</entry>
                            <entry>An association between a set of attribute or axiom value pairs
                                that causes them to be considered together within a Concept
                                definition or post coordinated expression.</entry>
                            <entry>EL_PLUS_PLUS_STATED_TERMINOLOGICAL_AXIOMS;
                                EL_PLUS_PLUS_INFERRED_TERMINOLOGICAL_AXIOMS</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">UNIVERSAL_RESTRICTION;
                                    EXISTENTIAL_RESTRICTION</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Role operator</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Role operator </entry>
                            <entry>Concept that is used to describe universal vs existential
                                restrictions.</entry>
                            <entry>ROLE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Role restriction</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Role value</entry>
                            <entry> </entry>
                            <entry>ROLE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Role type</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Role type</entry>
                            <entry>Refers to a Concept that represents a particular kind of
                                relationship that can exist between two entities. It defines the
                                specific function or responsibility that one entity plays in
                                relation to another. </entry>
                            <entry>ROLE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Russian Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                            <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Sandbox path</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Sandbox path</entry>
                            <entry>A path for Components under testing.</entry>
                            <entry>PATH</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Spanish language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Spanish language </entry>
                            <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                            <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Stated Navigation</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Stated Navigation</entry>
                            <entry>The origins and destinations for Concepts based on the reasoner
                                generated stated terminological axioms </entry>
                            <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Stated Navigation
                                Pattern</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Stated Navigation Pattern</entry>
                            <entry>A Pattern specifying the origins and destinations for Concepts
                                based on the stated terminological axioms </entry>
                            <entry>PATTERN</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">ACTIVE_STATE; CANCELED_STATE;
                                    INACTIVE_STATE; PRIMORDIAL_STATE;
                                WITHDRAWN_STATE</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Status value</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Status </entry>
                            <entry>The status of the STAMP Coordinate(Active, Cancelled, Inactive,
                                Primordial)</entry>
                            <entry>ROOT_VERTEX</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">String</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>String</entry>
                            <entry>a sequence of characters, either as a literal constant or as a
                                variable. Strings could be used to represent terms from code systems
                                or URLs, textual definitions, etc.</entry>
                            <entry>DISPLAY_FIELDS</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Sufficient set</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Sufficient set </entry>
                            <entry>A set of relationships that differentiate a Concept and its
                                subtypes from all other Concepts. A Concept that contains at least
                                one set of necessary and sufficient conditions is considered
                                defined.</entry>
                            <entry>EL_PLUS_PLUS_STATED_TERMINOLOGICAL_AXIOMS;
                                EL_PLUS_PLUS_INFERRED_TERMINOLOGICAL_AXIOMS</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Swedish Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                            <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Text for description</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Text</entry>
                            <entry>Captures the human readable text for a description in
                                Komet</entry>
                            <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">United States of America English
                                    dialect</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>US English dialect </entry>
                            <entry>Particular form of language specific form of English language,
                                particular to US</entry>
                            <entry>ENGLISH_DIALECT</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Universal Restriction</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Universal restriction</entry>
                            <entry> Universal restrictions constrain the relationships along a given
                                property to Concepts that are members of a specific class.</entry>
                            <entry>ROLE_OPERATOR</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold"
                                >UNIVERSALLY_UNIQUE_IDENTIFIER</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>UUID</entry>
                            <entry>A universally unique identifier that uniquely represents a
                                Concept in Tinkar </entry>
                            <entry>IDENTIFIER_SOURCE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">US Dialect Pattern </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>US Dialect Pattern </entry>
                            <entry> </entry>
                            <entry>PATTERN</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Withdrawn state</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Withdrawn state</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Concept used to represent a status for
                                    Components that are no longer active</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">STATUS_VALUE</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </informaltable>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Archive</title>
        <para>From the OWL Expressions, a set of stated relationships or axioms are automatically
            created through a reasoner. An alternative to having the description logic string can be
            to simply create the stated definition axioms inside of a Tinkar application like Komet
            directly. Here are the Stated Definition Axioms for each example:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Example 1: SNOMED CT®</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Create a ‘Sufficient Set’</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Add an Is-A relationship to ‘Disease’:</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Add a new Role Group</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Add a Role</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Role Type would be ‘Finding Site’</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Role Value would be ‘Kidney Structure’</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Example 2: LOINC®</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Create a ‘Necessary Set’</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Add an Is-A relationship to ‘Observable Entity’</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Add a new Role Group</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Add a Role</para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Role Type would be ‘System’</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Role Value would be ‘Ser’</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Add a new Role Group</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Add a Role</para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Role Type would be ‘Component’</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Role Value would be ‘Festuca elatior Ab.IgG’</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Add a new Role Group</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Add a Role</para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Role Type would be ‘Property’</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Role Value would be ‘ACnc ‘</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Add a new Role Group</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Add a Role</para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Role Type would be ‘Scale’</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Role Value would be ‘Qn’</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Add a new Role Group</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Add a Role</para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Role Type would be ‘Time’</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Role Value would be ‘Pt’</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
</chapter>
