<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Updated Advanced Analytics Platform Proof of Concept Use Case(s)</title>
        <section>
            <title>Challenges of Laboratory Data Quality</title>
            <para>In today’s current state, <emphasis role="bold">Laboratory Real-World Data (RWD)
                    is of remarkably low-quality </emphasis>which affects quality of care.
                Currently, standard test results and test information are encoded both
                inconsistently and incompletely. The current laboratory data standards alone (e.g.,
                Logical Observation Identifiers, Names, and Codes (LOINC®)) do not provide the level
                of detail or precision needed for the advanced analytics that power the clinical,
                regulatory, public health, and coverage determination decisions. </para>
            <para>As a result of this low-quality data, patient safety is at risk, quality of care
                diminishes, and accuracy of test results come into question. Simultaneously, this
                low-quality data has negatively impacted operational efficiency within both federal
                and private sectors. Examples of the negative effects on federal agencies are seen
                below: </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC)</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Epidemiologists studying disease mutation and forecasting
                                strain/variant proliferation (e.g., flu, Coronavirus Disease 2019
                                (COVID-19)) do not have access to granular test details (test
                                targets, test methods, specimen source and specimen collection
                                location —i.e., a pharyngeal location or a nasal location) that
                                could help identify new variants and assess real-time test
                                performance.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Food and Drug Administration (FDA)</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Reviewers and post-market surveyors do not have high-quality and
                                consistently represented RWD to help them evaluate and monitor the
                                safety and effectiveness of laboratory devices.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Clinical Care</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Practicing clinicians have limited ability to interpret individual
                                tests for false negative and false positive results because the
                                details of the test are unavailable.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Proposed Solution: Bridging Laboratory Data Gaps</title>
            <para>In order to address these gaps in data, the SHIELD Collaborative Community (CC)
                curated a device extension that creates interoperability between different systems.
                The extension was designed to be an authoritative source to educate end-users on
                populating their data dictionaries. The device extension will provide guidance and
                interact across systems on which data standards codes (e.g. LOINC®/Systematized
                Nomenclature of Medicine Clinical Term (SNOMED CT®)) are to be used for specific
                tests and/or devices. This source, designed by the CC, <emphasis role="bold"
                        ><emphasis role="italic">will link the laboratory analyzer with the
                        necessary information to support the comparison of test results without
                        switching laboratory codes, thus, increasing data
                    quality</emphasis></emphasis>.</para>
            <para>The device extension is <emphasis role="bold">intended to serve as a database that
                    improves the quality and interoperability of laboratory data</emphasis>. The
                extension does this by utilizing Unique Device Identifiers (UDI) to link individual
                In-Vitro Diagnostic (IVD) devices to a database that contains the test’s metadata,
                including units of measurement and data standard codes. It will provide insightful
                guidance on which data standard (e.g. LOINC®/SNOMED CT®) codes should be used on
                specific tests and devices. It will also enable linking laboratory analyzers with
                information to support the comparison of test results using the same laboratory
                codes. </para>
            <para> Our device extension was designed to address gaps in the current system. The
                extension is intended to be <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">a reliable
                        reference source to inform end users how to populate data
                        dictionaries</emphasis></emphasis>. This reduces the variance in laboratory
                data representation and will also provide laboratories with guidance on
                LOINC®/SNOMED CT® code usage for specific tests. This extension also <emphasis
                    role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">enables the linking of laboratory devices
                        through Unique Device Identifiers (UDIs) with supporting contextual
                        information to enable deeper insights and accurate comparison of
                        results</emphasis></emphasis>.</para>
            <para>These two benefits directly contribute to a dramatic enhancement of advanced
                analytical capabilities across a variety of mediums. Additional detail and
                consistent encoding of test results empower artificial intelligence (AI) algorithms
                to uncover deeper health insights that aid in treatment.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Advancing Interoperability: Development and Implementation Progress</title>
            <para>Data interoperability begins with the ability to represent data in a uniform way
                with quality standards that are adhered to by the community. SNOMED CT® and LOINC®
                are two international interoperability standards that both work to communicate
                clinical data information, LOINC® focuses on clinical and laboratory observations
                and SNOMED CT® focuses on clinical terminology for diagnoses, procedures, findings,
                and more. </para>
            <para>LOINC® and SNOMED CT® signed an agreement in October 2022 to collaborate on
                aligning and integrating their two standards. The shared effort worked to eliminate
                duplicative data between the standards and integrate shared information to create an
                extension of SNOMED CT® that incorporates LOINC® knowledge standards. The
                collaborative use of these terminologies will provide defined and accessible formats
                and concepts to represent data captured in laboratories or clinical settings.</para>
            <para>The LOINC® Ontology SNOMED CT® Browser builds on the capabilities of the SNOMED
                CT® Browser by providing visibility to LOINC® data through search or query. The
                impact the agreement has on the interoperability community spans across the
                healthcare IT industry by bridging two organizations who are leaders in terminology
                standards and interoperability. </para>
            <para>The collaborative efforts of the LOINC® Ontology SNOMED CT® Browser have produced
                a suite of increased functionality and tools that enable increased interoperability
                and integrated knowledge, including: </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Search functionality in the LOINC® Ontology SNOMED CT® Browser</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Concept viewing and detailed concept insights in the LOINC® Ontology
                        SNOMED CT® Browser</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Utilization of the LOINC® Ontology SNOMED CT® Browser for identifying
                        equivalence </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Contribution enabled integrations to continuously improve the LOINC®
                        Ontology SNOMED CT® Browser</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>The LOINC® and SNOMED CT® Collaborative Agreement has made significant strides in
                technical communications by providing comprehensive documentation on the processes
                used to link the two data standards. The ontology browser homepage offers an
                introductory technical explanation, detailing the content inclusions, modeling
                guidelines, concept/attribute representation, and future steps for improving the
                browser. This documentation is crucial for both technical and non-technical
                audiences, offering insights into the collaborative processes and technical efforts,
                and allowing individuals to understand the development and align their own
                implementations accordingly. The availability of this information ensures
                transparency and facilitates a deeper understanding of the integration efforts. </para>
            <para>Looking forward, the collaboration faces challenges in integrated knowledge communications and ensuring end-user adoption. The virtual location for the LOINC®-SNOMED CT® Ontology Browser showcases the progress made but lacks clear communication of the overarching goals. Engaging the community and building trust is essential to advancing healthcare information technology, and this can be achieved by enhancing understanding and support. The device extension will utilize the most recent updates published to the LOINC®-SNOMED CT® Ontology Browser. The ability of the device extension to utilize relevant standards from the source enhances effective communication strategies, which are critical for promoting tool adoption, requiring tailored messaging for different end-user segments. The end-user adoption strategy must balance detailed technical guidance for experts with non-technical communications that highlight the benefits and address specific pain points. This dual approach, including user guides, collaboration forums, and feedback channels, will support operational collaboration and encourage broader user engagement with the tools.</para>
        </section>
    <section>
        <title>Proof of Concept Use Cases</title>
        <section>
            <title>Demonstrating Device Extension Impact Through Use Cases</title>
            <para>To better understand the impact and value of the device extension, <emphasis
                    role="bold">a </emphasis><emphasis role="bold">use case </emphasis><emphasis
                    role="bold">diagram has</emphasis><emphasis role="bold"> been developed to
                    showcase the </emphasis><emphasis role="bold">multiple </emphasis><emphasis
                    role="bold">high-level functions and scope of systems a patient
                    </emphasis><emphasis role="bold">could</emphasis><emphasis role="bold"> interact
                    with as </emphasis><emphasis role="bold">a </emphasis><emphasis role="bold">part
                    of a unique care journey. </emphasis>SHIELD has utilized an infectious disease
                care diagram to highlight the functionality and impact of this tool in the patient
                care journey while focusing on a plethora of use cases with an emphasis on
                preventive care. The use case, while iterative, is subject to evolution based on
                additional stakeholder feedback. These use cases aim to comprehensively detail how
                the implementation of integrated knowledge resources, such as the device extension,
                will enrich data quality and empower advanced analytical tools to drive enhanced
                patient care.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Patient Journey Use Case: Emerging Infectious Disease</title>
            <para>The Emerging Infectious Disease Use Case, depicted in Figure 1, showcases the
                details of a patient's journey within medical facilities and processes taking place
                during an emerging infectious disease, covering an array of processes from symptom
                recognition to final diagnosis. As seen below, the primary patient journey is
                denoted by blue. This is where a patient who has been either notified of an exposure
                (Figure 1, Box 1) or begins to develop symptoms that align with that of an emerging
                infectious disease (Figure 1, Box 2) is interacting with the various points of care.
                This journey covers the patient's whole experience within the healthcare ecosystem,
                culminating in a diagnosis of chronic post-infectious disease (Figure 1, Box 1 –
                9).</para>
            <para>To fully understand the patient care journey, the individual sub-cycles (black in
                    <emphasis role="italic">Figure 2</emphasis>) denote the potential processes
                where a patient interacts with different care delivery individuals, systems, and/or
                organizations. These sub-cycles are utilized to collect data, inform decision-making
                for the patient outcome, and/or further exchange data to improve the healthcare
                ecosystem's understanding and diagnosis of emerging infectious diseases. This
                results in specific secondary processes that interconnect between the patient
                journey and differing state/federal health organizations that are responsible for
                the reporting and diagnostic device monitoring for public health reporting (Yellow,
                    <emphasis role="italic">Figure 1, </emphasis>Box 12, 16, 22).</para>
            <para>Our device extension was designed to interconnect these sub cycles, which
                correspond to health IT platforms or systems, to inform individual patient care
                outcomes and public health reporting. It can support the increased interconnectivity
                between healthcare ecosystem entities. These entities, often terminologists, are
                responsible for creating and extending relevant terminology subsets or modules.
                Supported by our Integrated Knowledge Management (IKM) environment, this procedure
                enables authoring a new extension record and integrates the newly formed terminology
                subsets. Figure 2 showcases how an IKM-powered ecosystem would interact with
                patients and evolve based on the advances in clinical diagnostics during an
                infectious disease outbreak.</para>
            <para>Like Figure 1, Figure 2 showcases a patient's journey through the healthcare
                system. For example, if a patient needs to order an Over-The-Counter (OTC) emerging
                infectious disease test kit, the patient must use a patient portal that has been
                enabled with the appropriate test listings. Figure 2 showcases that certain
                functions are only actionable if the current Information Technology (IT) Systems,
                relevant to the care journey, and key players across the organization update the
                existing health terminology gaps currently enacted and impacting patient care.
                Utilizing the IKM environment, our device extension provides the functionality to
                efficiently reconcile these gaps in standards that have been discovered as a result
                of:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The new emerging infectious disease prompting the identification of a
                        terminology gap (Figure 2, Box B, Box 9)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A patient recording their medical history in a digital health app (Figure
                        2, Box A, Box 1) <figure xml:id="EmergingInfectiousDiseaseUseCase">
                            <title>Figure 1: Emerging Infectious Disease Use Case</title>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata
                                        fileref="../images/Emerging%20Infectious%20Disease%20Use%20Case.svg
                                        " scale="40"
                                        align="center"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                        <figure
                            xml:id="EmergingInfectiousDiseaseUserJourneyDeviceExtensionCaptureFunctionality">
                            <title>Figure 2: Emerging Infectious Disease User Journey – Device
                                Extension Capture Functionality </title>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata
                                        fileref="../images/Emerging%20Infectious%20Disease%20User%20Journey%20Device%20Extension%20Capture%20Functionality.svg"
                                        scale="20" align="center"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Secondary Processes of Emerging Infectious Disease Use Case</title>
            <para>Secondary process documentation has been provided below to enhance understanding
                of these process flows and showcase the high-level process documentation of our
                device extension. These process flows provide a deeper look into the patient
                journey, emphasizing the unique data transfers involved. They detail the effective
                use of the device extension in Symptom Surveillance, which captures patient data
                related to acute symptoms—including questionnaires, reporting information, and
                documentation of negative symptoms—to better identify risk and inform clinical
                protocols. These secondary processes, in addition, highlight the advanced flow of
                data, expanding how Testing Recommendations occur and how Comparator Testing will
                take place. The following sections showcase the device extension’s ability to
                interconnect different large-scale organization databases and the potential for
                device interoperability.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Sub-Cycle 1: Symptom Surveillance</title>
                <para>The first secondary process documentation highlights the data processes and
                    flows that occur when individual patient data, along its emerging infectious
                    disease journey, integrates with the larger symptom surveillance ecosystem. As
                    individual data is obtained at the various collection points throughout
                    diagnosis, testing, and treatment processes, this information can be directly
                    aggregated into the larger data repository/lakes that will enable public health
                    entities to research and analyze macro-level data patterns and trends. These
                    data inputs into repositories can be supported by Integrated Knowledge Exchange
                    (IKE) solutions that enables seamless and lossless data transfer/exchange,
                    ensuring that data collection can be interoperable across disparate systems. As
                    this data is collected and assessed, new and/or unusual associated symptoms or
                    risk factors may be identified and reported, leading public health institutions
                    to update warnings and recommendations to clinical protocols to ensure the
                    collection of respective data is captured supporting the identification of these
                    newly identified facets. </para>
                <para>As public health institutions update this information, data collection
                    processes, such as questionnaires, need to be updated as well to coincide with
                    these updates. IKE solutions including Komet enable the modification of concepts
                    directly in a single source that can be integrated across the various data
                    standards and implemented into data collection tools automatically. Once the
                    data collection methods are updated with new concept definitions and
                    specifications based on public health recommendations, future patient care
                    journeys have the functionality to capture the new information effectively and
                    securely to track performance in the future. <figure
                        xml:id="FigureBox12SymptomSurveillance">
                        <title>Figure 3: Figure Box 12: Symptom Surveillance</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata
                                    fileref="../images/Figure%20Box%2012%20Symptom%20Surveillance.svg"
                                    scale="40" align="center"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure></para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Sub-Cycle 2: Comparator Testing</title>
                <para>Sub-Cycle 2 references FIGURE 1 box 16, specifying an additional process that
                    may occur when administering an over-the-counter (OTC) test to diagnose emerging
                    infectious disease(s). In this sub-cycle, the individual patient data entering
                    the cycle are additional samples collected during the OTC test that serve as the
                    samples for Return to Lab (RTL) testing. RTL testing can be utilized for (1)
                    providing a “Gold Standard” test that has a higher rate of accuracy of
                    positivity/negativity to ensure accurate diagnosis and/or (2) post-market
                    surveillance of diagnostic testing performance for regulatory test decisions. An
                    RTL test may be completed with its results returned to a patient’s care journey,
                    with the test result data being integrated with data repositories/lakes and
                    available for public health research. In this research, it may be determined
                    that a diagnostic test should be fully approved from an investigative test to a
                    full market test, or public health institutions may report warnings, recommend
                    alterations to specifications, or even fully remove the test. Regardless of
                    comparator testing outcomes, IKE solutions provide the functionality to modify
                    device-level data specifications to adhere to public health institutions’
                    updates seamlessly into knowledge resources and systems. <figure
                        xml:id="FigureBox16ComparatorTesting">
                        <title>Figure 4: Figure Box 16: Comparator Testing</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata
                                    fileref="../images/Figure%20Box%2016%20Comparator%20Testing.svg"
                                    scale="40" align="center"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure></para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Sub-Cycle 3: Revised Testing Recommendations</title>
                <para>The last secondary process documentation highlights the additional data flow
                    that occurs during a medical consultation during a patient’s journey through the
                    emerging infectious disease use case. When that medical consult occurs,
                    additional patient data is collected and will be integrated into the larger RWD
                    repositories for use amongst the greater research and public health institutions
                    to assess patterns and trends. As that data is analyzed, new associated risk
                    factors and/or comorbidities may be identified to bolster identification and
                    diagnosis of an emerging infectious disease. </para>
                <para>Public health institutions and peer-reviewed journals will submit insights and
                    publications for adoption within the healthcare ecosystem. These resources help
                    capture risk factors and comorbidities during medical consultations, enabling
                    providers to identify additional factors that may impact the diagnosis of
                    emerging infectious diseases. These new identifications can be implemented into
                    the healthcare information technology ecosystem using IKE solutions, such as
                    Komet, to modify concept data to include comorbidities within their definitions
                    to ensure the capture of that new factor to consider with the emerging
                    infectious disease. <figure xml:id="FigureBox22TestingRecommendations">
                        <title>Figure 5: Figure Box 22: Testing Recommendations</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata
                                    fileref="../images/Figure%20Box%2022%20Testing%20Recommendations.svg"
                                    scale="40" align="center"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure></para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Advanced Analytics Capabilities</title>
            <para>The patient journey as described in <emphasis role="italic">Figure 2</emphasis>
                depicts the patient moving through a variety of healthcare actions and processes.
                The incorporation of IKE solutions into these spaces provides an opportunity for
                increased support in the development and maintenance of high-quality data elements.
                The patient journey can be supplemented with IKE solutions such as Komet to modify,
                author and exchange novel data concepts in an application and share that information
                across disparate data platforms/systems. IKE is empowered by collaborative efforts
                across the healthcare ecosystem to develop, assess, and implement solutions to
                integrate knowledge resources into a shared environment with seamless capabilities
                for the variety of needs that healthcare information technology requires.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Implications and Considerations for Use</title>
            <para>The processes that the patient interacts with on their journey have a direct need
                for data to be available across systems to coordinate actions and recommendations
                accurately and effectively to the patient. </para>
            <para>Key drivers to consider for the critical need for the implementation of IKE
                solutions include:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Healthcare data requires reproducible standards:
                        </emphasis>Healthcare data exchange requires that data collection methods
                        are reproducibly encoded using industry coding standards. Without IKE tools,
                        such as Komet, to bring together disparate standards, the reproducibility of
                        data encoding is stunted.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Disparate standards require a centralized
                            repository:</emphasis> The knowledge from standard terminologies that
                        are used to encode data elements need to be managed so implementers can
                        easily handle dependencies, version control, and data provenance for the
                        integrity of patient records. Komet, via the IKE environment, can enable
                        such data management for informed decision making.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Data gaps require real-time modification:
                        </emphasis>Operational realities, such as those experienced during an
                        emergent infectious disease, necessitate the ability to dynamically adjust
                        clinical terminologies at a local level with the goal of reconciling those
                        adjustments with larger standards bodies once available. IKE tools and
                        functionality can enable near real-time authoring of new health data
                        terminology concepts to maintain care quality even in the midst of
                        unprecedented circumstances.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>The use of Komet is predicated on the successful development of the wider
                healthcare information technology ecosystem alongside regulatory, clinical, and
                terminology standard stakeholders working together to support guidance and the use
                of such a tool. To achieve this ideal state, the SHIELD program continues to address
                the goal of being able to represent the same healthcare information, the same way,
                every time though its Integrated Knowledge Management tools. With support from
                stakeholders across the ecosystem, SHIELD can achieve the shared foundation
                necessary to improve the quality and interoperability of laboratory data.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
